<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The three books of Hermas the disciple of Paul the Apostle. Viz. I. The church. II. The sheepherd. III. The similitudes. Englished by John Pringle.</title>
            <author>Hermas, 2nd cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 221 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 97 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43419</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1564A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216863</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828580</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828580</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33010</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43419)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33010)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1965:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The three books of Hermas the disciple of Paul the Apostle. Viz. I. The church. II. The sheepherd. III. The similitudes. Englished by John Pringle.</title>
                  <author>Hermas, 2nd cent.</author>
                  <author>Pringle, John, fl. 1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>189, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for John White in Threadneedle Street, behinde the Old Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"I. The church..III. The similitudes" are in brackets.</note>
                  <note>Includes a final errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33010:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33010:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE THREE BOOKS OF Hermas, the Diſciple of <hi>PA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>L</hi> the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Viz.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>I. The Church.</item>
                        <item>II. The Sheepherd.</item>
                        <item>III. The Similitudes.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Engliſhed by <hi>John Pringle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John White</hi> in Thread-needle Street, behinde the Old Exchange, 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="book">
            <pb facs="tcp:33010:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:33010:2"/>
            <head>The firſt Book of <hi>Hermas,</hi> the Diſciple of <hi>Paul,</hi> which is intituled, the <hi>CHURCH.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="vision">
               <head>VISION. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E who had brought me up, ſold a certain Girle at <hi>Rome;</hi> but after many years her being ſeen I again knew, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to love her as my ſiſter; but ſome time being finiſhed, I ſaw her waſhed in the River <hi>Tyber;</hi> And I ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out my hand to her, and led her out of the River: and having ſeen her, I thought in my heart, ſaying, Happy ſhould I be, if I could obtain ſuch a Wife both in beauty and manners. This on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nor any thing elſe did I think.</p>
               <p n="2">2 But after ſome time paſſing on with theſe cogitations, I honoured the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God, thinking how excellent and beautiful it is. And when I had walked, I fell aſleep. And the Spirit caught me, and carried me by a certain place at the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33010:3"/>
right hand, by which man could not tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel; But the place was among the Rocks, and craggy, and impaſſable by reaſon of waters. And when I had paſt over that place, I came into a plain, and my knees being bowed, I began to pray unto the Lord, and to confeſſe my ſins.</p>
               <p n="3">3 And while I prayed, the Heaven o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, and I ſee the woman whom I had deſired, ſaluting me from Heaven, and ſaying, <hi>Hail Hermas.</hi> And I looking up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her, ſay unto her, <hi>Lady, what doſt thou here?</hi> But ſhe anſwered unto me, <hi>I am received hither, that I may reprove thy ſinnes before the Lord. Lady,</hi> ſaid I, <hi>wilt thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove me? No,</hi> ſaith ſhe, <hi>but hear the words which I am about to ſay unto thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 God who dwelleth in the Heavens, and made out of nothing the things that are, and multiplied them for his holy Church, is angry with thee, becauſe thou haſt offended againſt me. <hi>I anſwering ſay unto her,</hi> Lady, if againſt thee I have offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, where, or in what place, or when did I ſpeak to thee any unſeemly word? Have I not alwayes eſteemed thee as my Miſtreſſe? Have I not alwayes reſpected thee as my Siſter? Why doſt thou ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine thoſe ſo hainous [crimes] againſt me</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:33010:3"/>5 <hi>Then ſhe ſmiling on me ſaith,</hi> The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence of wickedneſs hath ariſen in thine heart: ſeems it not to thee to be an unjuſt thing to a juſt man, if evil concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence ſhould ariſe in his heart? It is a ſin to him, and indeed a great one, for a juſt man thinks juſt things; therefore he thinking the things that are juſt, and he rightly proceeding, in the Heavens he ſhall have the Lord favourable in every buſineſſe of his; but who ſo think wicked things in their hearts, death and captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty do they chuſe to themſelves; chiefly they who love this world and glory in their riches, and who expect not the good things to come their ſouls are emptied; But theſe things the doubtful ones do, who have not hope in the Lord, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe and neglect their LIFE: but pray thou to the Lord, and he will heal the ſins of thee, and of thy whole houſe, and of all the Saints.</p>
               <p n="6">6 But after ſhe had ſpoken theſe words, the Heavens were ſhut, and I was alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in ſorrow and fear, and ſaid with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me, If this be imputed ſin unto me, how ſhall I be able to be ſaved? or how ſhall I entreat the Lord for my moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant ſins? with what words ſhall I
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33010:4"/>
beſeech the Lord, that he may be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to me?</p>
               <p n="7">7 Theſe things I revolving, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning in my heart, I ſee againſt me a great chair made of wools, white, as the ſnow: and an old Woman came, in a ſhining Veſture, having a book in her hand, and ſhe ſat alone, and ſaluted me, <hi>Hail Hermas.</hi> And I ſad and weeping, ſaid, <hi>Hail Lady.</hi> And ſhe ſaid unto me, <hi>Why art thou ſad</hi> Hermas, <hi>who waſt patient and modeſt, and alwayes cheerful?</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering ſay unto her, <hi>Lady, a reproach is caſt upon me by an excellent woman,</hi> ſaying, <hi>that I have offended againſt her.</hi> But ſhe ſaith unto me, <hi>Far be that thing from a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of God; but perhaps the concupiſence of her hath ariſen in thine heart. There is indeed in the Servants of God ſuch a thought, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſin; for this abominable thought ought not to be in the ſervant of God, nor a proved ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to covet an evil work, and eſpecially</hi> Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, <hi>who containeth from all wicked concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſence, and is full of all ſimplicity and great innocency.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>However not becauſe of thee is the Lord an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, but for thine houſe which hath committed-a wickedneſſe againſt the Lord, and againſt their Parents. And thou ſeeing thou art a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33010:4"/>
of thy ſons, haſt not ſtir'd up thine houſe, but haſt let them paſſe to be converſant violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for becauſe of this is the Lord angry with thee. But he will heal all the evils which are acted againſt thee in thine houſe; for becauſe of their ſins and iniquities, thou art conſumed through worldly employments; for now the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving kindneſs of God hath pitied thee, and thine houſe, and hath preſerved thee in GLORY. Onely do not thou WANDER, but be pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in mind, and ſtrengthen thine houſe. Even as a worker in braſs producing his work, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth them to him to whom he will: ſo alſo thou teaching the daily juſt word, wilt cut off great ſin. Ceaſe not therefore to admoniſh thy ſons, for the Lord knows that they will act re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance from their whole heart, and he ſhall write thee in THE BOOK OF LIFE.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9 And when ſhe had finiſhed theſe words, ſhe ſaith to me, <hi>Wilt thou hear me reading?</hi> I ſay unto her, <hi>Lady I will.</hi> Be thou then an hearer. And turning over the book, ſhe read gloriouſly and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently, and wonderfully, which I was not able to retain in memory; for they were terrifying words, which man was not able to ſuſtain. Yet the laſt words I commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to memory, for they were few, and profitable for us.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:33010:5"/>10 <q>Behold the God of powers, who by his inviſible power and great know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge hath built the World, and by his honourable Council compaſſed about his Creature with comlineſs, and by his moſt ſtrong WORD fixed the Heaven, and founded the Earth upon the waters, and by his powerfull ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue hath built his holy CHURCH, which he hath bleſſed; Behold he will remove the Heavens and Mountains, Little hills and Seas, and all ſhall be full with his choſen ones, that he may render unto them the promiſe which he re-promiſed, with much honour and joy, if they ſhall keep the ſtatutes of God, which they received in great faith.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11 And when ſhe had finiſhed in read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſhe aroſe from the chair, and four young men came and took up likewiſe the chair to the EAST. And ſhe called me to her, and touched my breaſt, and ſaith unto me, <hi>did my reading pleaſe thee?</hi> I ſay unto her, <hi>Lady, theſe laſt pleaſed me, but the former are cruel and hard;</hi> but ſhe ſaith un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, <hi>theſe latter to the Juſt, but the former to the fugitives and Heathens.</hi> And whileſt ſhe was ſpeaking with me, two certain
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33010:5"/>
men appeared, and took her up upon their ſhoulders, and went away, whither alſo the chair was towards the EAST; but ſhe departed cheerfull, and when ſhe was to go away, ſhe ſaith to me <hi>Be comforted</hi> Hermas.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="vision">
               <head>VISION. II.</head>
               <p n="1">1 BUt whileſt I went on with theſe [thoughts,] about that time wherein alſo the year before walking, I called to memory the former years Viſion; And again the Spirit took me away, and led me into the ſame place, wherein the firſt year [I was] and I ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured his Name becauſe he ſhould eſteem me worthy, and ſhould manifeſt unto me my old ſins; and when I had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſen from prayer, I ſee over againſt me that old woman, whom alſo the former year I had ſeen walking, and reading ſome certain Book; And ſhe ſaith to me, <hi>canſt thou rehearſe theſe things to the choſen ones of God?</hi> I ſay unto her, <hi>Lady, ſuch great words I cannot retain in memory, but give me the Book and I will write it down. Take it</hi> ſaith ſhe, <hi>and reſtore it unto me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:33010:6"/>2 But as ſoon as I had gotten it, going aſide into a certain place of the field, I wrote down all to a letter, for I found not Syllabs; And when I had finiſhed the writing of the book, ſuddenly from my hand the Book was ſnached, but by whom I ſaw not. But after fifteen dayes when I had faſted, and had much entreated the Lord, the knowledge of the writing was revealed to me; But the Writing was this.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <q>Thy SEED <hi>Hermas</hi> hath treſpaſt againſt the Lord, and have betrayed their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents in great wickedneſs; And the betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Parents have heard, and the ſubtile have gone on. But alſo now they have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to their ſins luſts, and the defilements of wickedneſs; And ſo have they filled up their iniquities.</q> 
                  <hi>But haſten thou theſe words to all thy Sons, and to thy Wife who is to be thy Siſter; And ſhe therefore may bridle her tongue wherein ſhe curſeth; And theſe words being heard, ſhe ſhall contain herſelf, and ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain mercy, for ſhe ſhall be inſtructed after that thou ſhalt have imparted unto her theſe words which that R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LER Commanded, that they ſhould be revealed to thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 Then ſhall the ſins be remitted to them which long ago they ſinned, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33010:6"/>
to all the Saints who have ſinned, untill this very day, if from their whole heart they ſhall act repentance, and take away doubtings from their hearts; for that RULER hath ſworn by his glory upon his choſen ones, that day being finiſhed, alſo now if any one ſhall ſin, that he ſhall not have Salvation, for the repentances of the juſt have ends; The dayes of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance are fulfilled to all the Saints, but to the Gentiles repentance until in the laſt day.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Thou ſhalt therefore ſpeak unto them that are over the Church, that they may direct their wayes in Righteouſneſſe, that they may receive in full the RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PROMISSION with much Glory; Continue ye therefore who work righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and ſo do ye that your change may be with the holy Angels: Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ye whoſoever ſuſtain the great preſſure coming upon [you,] and whoſoever ſhall not deny HIS OWNE LIFE; For the Lord hath ſworn by his Son, he who ſhall deny his Son and himſelf, promiſing themſelves his LIFE, they alſo are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to deny him in the dayes approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but they who never denyed [him] through his exceeding great mercy is he
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33010:7"/>
become propitious to them.</p>
               <p n="6">6 But thou <hi>Hermas</hi> do not thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the injuries of thy ſons, but nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mayſt thou neglect thy Siſter, but take care that they be amended from their former ſins, for they ſhall be inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by that Doctrine, if now thou ſhalt not be mindful of their injury, for the memory of injuries worketh death, but the oblivion of them Life Eternal.</p>
               <p n="7">7 But thou <hi>Hermas</hi> haſt ſuſtained great worldly Tribulations, becauſe of the overſlippings of thy houſe, becauſe them thou haſt neglected, as pertaining no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to thee, and in thy malitious buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes haſt been involved; But that ſhall ſave thee, that thou haſt not departed from the living God, and thy ſimplicity and ſingular continency they ſhall ſave thee, if thou ſhalt continue, and they ſhall ſave all whoſoever work the like, and enter in, in innocency and ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p n="8">8 Thoſe who are of this ſort, ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail againſt all wickedneſs, and ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue unto life eternal; Happy are all they that work righteouſneſſe, they ſhall not be taken away untill into life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall; <hi>But thou wilt ſay,</hi> Behold great
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33010:7"/>
Tribulation cometh if it ſeem [good] to to thee again, deny it, NIGH IS THE LORD TO THOSE THAT TURN, as it is written in <hi>HELDAM</hi> and <hi>MODAL,</hi> who did Propheſie in the Wilderneſs to the people.</p>
               <p n="9">9 But Brethren it was revealed to me ſleeping, by a comly youth, and ſaying unto me, <hi>that old Woman from whom thou haſt got the Book, whom thinkſt thou to be?</hi> And I ſaid <hi>SYBILLA.</hi> Thou erreſt quoth he, ſhe is not. <hi>Who is ſhe then Lord? And he ſaid to me, She is the CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH of GOD. And I ſaid to him, why therefore is ſhe an old Woman? Becauſe quoth he,</hi> of all ſhe was firſt Created, therefore an old Woman, and for her was the World made.</p>
               <p n="10">10 But after theſe I ſaw a Viſion in mine houſe, and that old Woman came and asked me, <hi>if already I had given the Book to the Elders;</hi> And I anſwered, <hi>as yet not;</hi> But ſhe ſaid, <hi>Thou haſt well done, For I have certain words to command thee, but when I ſhall finiſh all the words, they ſhall be aptly known by the Elect;</hi> Thou ſhalt therefore write two Books, and thou ſhalt ſend one to <hi>CLEMENT,</hi> and one to <hi>GRAPTE;</hi> But <hi>Clement</hi> ſhall ſend it into forreign
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33010:8"/>
Citties, for to him it is permitted, but <hi>Grapte</hi> ſhall admoniſh the Widows and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes; But thou ſhalt read it in this City, with the Elders that are over the Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="vision">
               <head>VISION. III.</head>
               <p n="1">1 THe Viſion which I ſaw Brethren, was ſuch a Viſion, when I had frequently faſted, and had prayed the Lord that to me he would ſhow the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, which he promiſed to ſhow by that old Woman; That ſame night ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared that old Woman to me, and ſaid unto me,</p>
               <p n="2">2 Becauſe thou ſo languiſheſt and art troubled to know all things, <hi>come thou in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the field, where thou wilt, and about the ſixt hour I will manifeſt me to thee, and I will ſhow thee what things it behoveth thee to ſee;</hi> I asked her ſaying, <hi>Lady into what place of the field? Where thou wilt</hi> quoth ſhe, <hi>chooſe out a good place, ſecret.</hi> But before I had begun to ſpeak, and to tell her the place, ſhe ſaith to me, <hi>I will come where thou wilt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 I was therefore Brethren in the field,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33010:8"/>
and <hi>I</hi> obſerved the hours, and I came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the place where <hi>I</hi> had appointed to her to come, and I ſee a ſeat ſet; It was a lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen pillow, and ſpread upon a linnen ſheet; ſeeing theſe ſet, and none to be in the place, I began to be aſtoniſhed, and my hairs roſe up, and as it were a horrour ceized on me, ſeeing I was alone; But being returned to my ſelf, and having remembred the Glory of God, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken courage, having bowd my knees, I confeſſed to God again the ſins which before.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Behold ſhe cometh thither with ſix young men, whom alſo I had ſeen before, and ſhe ſtood behind me, and heard me praying and confeſſing unto the Lord my ſins, and touching me ſhe ſaid, <hi>Leave off now to pray ſo much for thy ſins, pray alſo for Righteouſneſſe, that thou mayſt receive part of it in thine houſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 And ſhe raiſed me up from the place, and took hold of my hand, and led me to the ſeat, and ſhe ſaith to theſe young men, <hi>Go ye and build;</hi> but after the youths had departed, and we were alone, ſhe ſaith to me, <hi>ſit thou here;</hi> I ſay to her, <hi>Lady ſuffer the Elders before to ſit down.</hi> What I ſay to thee quoth ſhe, <hi>Sit thou down;</hi> And
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33010:9"/>
when I would ſit at the right ſide, ſhe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered not, but beckned to me with her hand, that I ſhould ſit at the left ſide.</p>
               <p n="6">6 But I bethinking and remaining ſad, that ſhe had not ſuffered me to ſit at the right ſide, ſhe ſaith to me, <hi>Why art thou ſad Hermas? The place which is at the right ſide is theirs who already have deſerved GOD, and have ſuffered for the cauſe of his Name; But to thee there remains much that thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſit with them; as thou remaineſt in thy ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, remain thou, and thou ſhalt ſit with them; and whoſoever ſhall have wrought their works, and ſhall ſuſtain what they have ſuſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7 <hi>I ſay unto her,</hi> Lady I would know what they have ſuſtained; <hi>Hear quoth ſhe,</hi> wild Beaſts, Whips, Priſons, Croſſes for the cauſe of his Name, for this theirs are the right ſides of Holineſſe, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſhall ſuffer for the Name of God; but the reſt's are the left ſides, but to both of them, both who at the right hand, and who at the left do ſit, are the gifts and promiſes, only that, who ſit at the right ſide have a certain glory; but thou art deſirous to ſit at the right hand with them, but thy infirmities are many, but thou ſhalt be purged from thy failings,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33010:9"/>
but alſo all who ſhall not be doubtfull ſhall be made clean from all their ſins unto this day.</p>
               <p n="8">8 And when ſhe had ſaid theſe things ſhe would go away, and falling down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her at her feet, I beſought her by the Lord, that to me ſhe would demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the fight which ſhe had re-promiſed; But ſhe again took hold of my hand and lifted me up, and made me to ſit upon the ſeat at the left hand, and having lifted up a certain ſplendent rod, ſhe ſaith to me, <hi>Seeſt thou a mighty thing?</hi> I ſay to her, <hi>Lady, I ſee nothing.</hi> Behold, <hi>Seeſt thou not over againſt thee a great Tower which is built upon the waters, with four-corner'd ſtones ſhining.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9 For in a Quadrangle was there a Tower builded by theſe ſix Youths who had come with her, but others many thouſands of men did bring ſtones, but ſome drew forth ſtones from the DEEP, others took them up from the EARTH and gave them to theſe ſix Youths, more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over they took them and builded, but thoſe ſtones which were extracted out of the deep they did all place ſo into the ſtructure, for they were poliſhed, and convenient for commixture with other
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:33010:10"/>
ſtones, and ſo were they conjoyned one to another, ſo that their commixtures could not appear, and on this manner did the ſtructure of the Tower appear, as if builded of one ſtone.</p>
               <p n="10">10 But the reſt of the ſtones which were brought from off the earth, ſome [of them] indeed they rejected, but ſome they fitted for the ſtructure, others they hewed and did caſt far from the Tower; but many other ſtones were placed about the Tower, and they did not uſe them for the ſtructure, for ſome of them were RUGGED, but others had RENTS, but others [were] WHITE and ROUND, not agreeing for the ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of the Tower.</p>
               <p n="11">11 But I ſaw other ſtones to be caſt far from the Tower, and tumbling into the WAY, and not remaining in the way, but to be rolled from the way into a deſert place, but others falling into the FIRE and burning, others falling be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the WATER, nor to be able to be rolled into the water, they indeed being willing to enter into the Water.</p>
               <p n="12">12 And when ſhe had demonſtrated unto me theſe things, ſhe would depart, I ſay to her, <hi>Lady, what doth it profit me to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33010:10"/>
have ſeen theſe things, and not to know what theſe things are?</hi> She anſwering ſaid to me, <hi>Thou art a cunning man, willing to know theſe things that are about the Tower,</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſay I, Lady, <hi>that I may declare it to my Brethren, and they may be made more chearful, and hearing theſe things may honour the Lord with much glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13 And ſhe ſaith, <hi>many indeed ſhall hear, and when they ſhall hear ſome of them ſhall rejoyce, but ſome ſhall weep, but alſo they hearing, if they ſhall act repentance they alſo ſhall rejoyce:</hi> Hear now concerning the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of the Tower all theſe [things] and hitherto be thou not more trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom to me concerning revelation, for theſe revelations have an end, for they are ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, but thou deſiſteſt not in asking re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations, for thou art importunate.</p>
               <p n="14">14 The Tower indeed which thou ſeeſt to be builded, Am I the Church, who have appeared to thee both now and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? Whatſoever therefore thou wouldſt, ask thou concerning the Tower, and I will reveal it to thee, that thou mayeſt rejoyce with the Saints. I ſay unto her, Lady, <hi>becauſe thou haſt once eſteemed me wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, that thou mayeſt reveal all things to me, reveal [them.]</hi> She ſaith to me, <hi>whatſoever
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33010:11"/>
muſt be revealed to thee, ſo much ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, that thy heart may be with the Lord, and doubt thou not whatſoever thou ſeeſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15 I asked her, <hi>Why is the Tower built upon the waters, Lady?</hi> I had ſaid unto thee <hi>alſo before thee to be ſubtle, enquiring diligently about the ſtructures, therefore thou ſhalt find the Truth: Why therefore the Tower is builded upon the WATERS,</hi> hear thou, <hi>becauſe your life is ſaved by water, and ſhall be, for it is founded with the word of [his] omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and honourable Name, for it is contained by the inviſible power of God.</hi> I anſwering ſay to her, <hi>highly do theſe things carry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16 But theſe ſix young men that build who are they Lady? <hi>Theſe are the Angels of God, who at firſt were conſtitute, to whom the Lord hath delivered his univerſal Creature of the building, edifying, and ruling over his Creature, for by them ſhall the structure of the Tower be conſummate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">17 But the reſt that bring ſtones, who are they? <hi>They alſo the holy Angels of the Lord, but they are more excellent then theſe, therefore when the building of the Tower ſhall be accompliſhed, they ſhall altogether feaſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the Tower, and ſhall honour the Lord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſtructure of the Tower ſhall be fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="18">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:33010:11"/>18 I asked her ſaying, I would know the event of the ſtones, and the force of them what it is, but ſhe anſwering ſaid to me, <hi>art thou better before all, that that may be revealed to thee? for others are before thee, and better then thee, to whom it behoved theſe viſions to be revealed, but that the Name of God may be honoured, to thee it is revealed, and ſhall be revealed, becauſe of the doubtful ones, who think in their hearts whether theſe things be or be not, ſay unto them that all theſe things are true, and nothing is out of the truth, but all [are] firm, and are ſurely grounded.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="19">19 Hear now alſo of the ſtones that are in the ſtructure, indeed theſe four-cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner'd-ſtones, and white, agreeing in their commixtures, theſe are the APO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STLES, and Overſeers, and Teachers, and MINISTERS, who have entred in in the clemency of God, and ruled their charge, and taught, and miniſtred holily and modeſtly to the elect of God, who have ſlept, and who as yet are, and have alwaies agreed with them, and had peace in themſelves, and have heard themſelves mutually, for this alſo into the ſtructure of the Tower do their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixtures agree.</p>
               <p n="20">20 But theſe who are drawn out of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33010:12"/>
deep, and placed into the ſtructure, and their commixtures agree with the reſt of the ſtones which are already builded, are theſe who already have fallen aſleep, and have ſuffered for the cauſe of the Name of the Lord.</p>
               <p n="21">21 <hi>But the reſt of the ſtones that were brought from the earth, I would know who they are Lady; ſhe ſaith,</hi> Thoſe indeed who go in the earth, and are not poliſhed, thoſe God hath proved, becauſe they have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in into the Righteouſneſſe of the Lord, and have directed their wayes in his Commandments.</p>
               <p n="22">22 But theſe that are brought, and are put in the ſtructure of the Tower, theſe are the young ones in the faith, and the faithful, but they are commoniſhed by the Angels to do good, for that cauſe there is not wickedneſſe found in them.</p>
               <p n="23">23 <hi>But thoſe whom they did reject, and placed beſide the Tower, who are they?</hi> Theſe are they who have ſinned, and would do repentance, for this they are not caſt out far from the Tower; becauſe they ſhall be profitable in the ſtructure, if they ſhall act Repentance. They therefore that are about to act Repentance, if they ſhall do Repentance they ſhall be ſtrong in the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33010:12"/>
faith, if now they ſhall act Repentance while the Tower is a building. For if the ſtructure ſhall be finiſhed, now any ſhall not have a place where he may be put, but he ſhall be a reprobate: but he onely ſhall have this who already is placed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the Tower.</p>
               <p n="24">24 <hi>But theſe that were hewed and thrown far from the Tower, wilt thou know who they are?</hi> Theſe are the SONS OF INI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>QUITY, and they have believed in diſſimulation, and all wickedneſſe hath not departed from them, for this they have not Salvation, becauſe they are not profitable in the ſtructure, by reaſon of their wickedneſſes. Wherefore they are hewn and thrown far away becauſe of the anger of the Lord, becauſe they have ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him up.</p>
               <p n="25">25 But the reſt of the ſtones whom thou didſt ſee very many placed, not going in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſtructure, theſe indeed were rugg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Theſe are they who have known the Truth, and have neither remained in it nor have been joyned to the Saints, for this cauſe they are unprofitable.</p>
               <p n="26">26 But theſe that had rents; becauſe they have diſcord in their hearts one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another, and have not peace among
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33010:13"/>
themſelves. In preſence indeed having peace, but when one ſhall go away from another, their wickedneſſe remains in their hearts. Theſe therefore are the rents which the ſtones have.</p>
               <p n="27">27 But thoſe that are maimed are they who indeed believed, having the moſt part of iniquity, for this cauſe they are broken, and not intire.</p>
               <p n="28">28 <hi>But the white and round, and not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing into the ſtructure of the Tower, who are they Lady? She anſwering to me ſaid,</hi> How long hitherto art thou fooliſh and ſenſeleſſe, and ask eſt all things and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeſt nothing? Theſe are they that have indeed faith, but having alſo the riches of this world. Therefore when tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation ſhall come, for their riches and negotiations they deny the Lord.</p>
               <p n="29">29 <hi>I anſwering ſay to her, Lady,</hi> when therefore ſhall they be profitable to the Lord? when their riches, <hi>quoth ſhe,</hi> ſhall be circumciſed, which delight them, then ſhall they be profitable to the Lord unto the building. For as a round ſtone, unleſs it ſhall be hewn, and caſt off ſomewhat from it, cannot be made four-corner'd, ſo alſo they that are rich in this world, unleſſe their riches ſhall be circumciſed
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33010:13"/>
they cannot be profitable to the Lord.</p>
               <p n="30">30 From thee firſt know it, when thou waſt rich, thou waſt unprofitable, but now thou art profitable and fit for thy LIFE, for alſo thou thy ſelf waſt of theſe ſtones.</p>
               <p n="31">31 But the reſt of the ſtones which thou didſt ſee caſt far from the Tower, and running in the way, and to be rolled from the way into deſert places, theſe are they who have indeed believed, but with their doubting have left their own true WAY, thinking themſelves to be able to find a better way; but they wander, and are miſerable, entering into deſert wayes.</p>
               <p n="32">32 But theſe that fell into the fire and did burn, are they who for ever have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from the Living God; nor doth it any more aſcend into their hearts, to act repentance, becauſe of the deſire of their luſts, and wickedneſſes which they work.</p>
               <p n="33">33 <hi>But the reſt which fell beſides the waters, and could not be rolled into the waters, who are theſe?</hi> Theſe are they who have heard the WORD, willing to be baptized in the NAME of the Lord, to whom when the Sanctity of the TRUTH
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33010:14"/>
came into their memory, they draw back themſelves, and do again walk after their wicked deſires.</p>
               <p n="34">34 Therefore ſhe finiſhed the narration of the Tower; but I, ſeeing I was obſtinate, asked her, Whether to all theſe ſtones which were thrown away, nor did agree into the ſtructure of the Tower, is there Repentance, and ſhall they have a place in this Tower? They have, <hi>quoth ſhe,</hi> Repentance, but in this Tower they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not agree fitly.</p>
               <p n="35">35 But they ſhall be put in another place much inferiour to this, when they ſhall have been vexed, and have fulfilled the dayes of their tranſgreſſions; and for this ſhall they be taken up, becauſe they have received THE JUST WORD; and then ſhall it befall them to be relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from their puniſhments, if the wicked works which they have wrought ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend up into their hearts; but if they ſhall not aſcend into their hearts, they ſhall not be ſaved becauſe of the hardneſs of their hearts.</p>
               <p n="36">36 <hi>When therefore I left off to ask her of all theſe things, ſhe ſaith to me, wilt thou ſee another? and ſeeing I was deſirous to ſee, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came chearful in countenance; ſhe looking back
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33010:14"/>
on me ſmiled, and ſaith to me, Seeſt thou ſeven women about the Tower? I ſee them, quoth I, Lady.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="37">37 This Tower is ſupported by them according to the Precept of the Lord: Hear now the effects of them; The firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed of them who takes hold with her hand is called FAITH, by her ſhall the choſen of God be ſaved; but the other who is guirded about and acteth manfully is called ABSTINENCE, ſhe is the Daughter of Faith; whoſoever therefore ſhall follow her, ſhall become happy in his LIFE, becauſe he ſhall abſtain from all evil works, believing that if he ſhall contain himſelf from all Concupiſcence, he ſhall be an heir of Life Eternal.</p>
               <p n="38">38 <hi>But the other five Lady who are they?</hi> They are Daughters mutually, <hi>quoth ſhe,</hi> but one is called SIMPLICITY, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother INNOCENCY, another MODESTY, another DISCI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PLINE, but another CHARITY: Therefore when thou ſhalt have kept the works of their Mother, thou ſhalt be able to keep all things.</p>
               <p n="39">39 <hi>I would know Lady what vertue each of them hath; Hear quoth ſhe,</hi> They have equal vertues, but their vertues are mutually
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33010:15"/>
connected, and do follow them by courſe as they are born; of Faith is born Abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, of Abſtinence Simplicity, of Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity Innocency, of Innocency Modeſty, of Modeſty Diſcipline and Charity. Therefore their works are holy, chaſt, and right; whoſoever therefore ſhall ſerve them, and would hold their works, he ſhall have an habitation in the Tower with the Saints of God.</p>
               <p n="40">40 <hi>I asked her of the times, if now is the conſummation? But ſhe exclaimed with a great voice, ſaying,</hi> O ſenſeleſſe man, doſt thou not ſee the Tower to be alwaies builded? Therefore when the Tower ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummate and builded it hath an end; but alſo ſwiftly ſhall it be finiſhed, do not thou any more ask me any thing, let this commemoration ſuffice thee and all the Saints, and this renovation of your Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits.</p>
               <p n="41">41 But not to thee alone are theſe things revealed, but that thou mayeſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo demonſtrate them to all, for after three dayes thou muſt underſtand, <hi>Hermas,</hi> theſe words which I begin to ſay unto thee, that thou mayeſt ſpeak them in the ears of the Saints, that they hearing them when they ſhall have done them, they may be
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33010:15"/>
cleanſed from their wickedneſſes, and thou with them.</p>
               <q>
                  <p n="42">42 Hear me my Sons, <hi>I nouriſhed you in much ſimplicity, and innocency, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, becauſe of the loving-kindneſſe of God which diſtilled upon you in Righteouſneſſe, that ye may be ſanctified and juſtified from all naughtineſſe and wickedneſſe, but ye will not ceaſe from your wickedneſſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="43">43 <hi>Now therefore hear me, and have peace one with another, and viſit ye one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and take ye by courſe, and do not ye alone take the Creatures of God; alſo impart ye more abundantly to the needy, for ſome with many meats, contract infirmity of their fleſh, and violate their fleſh; but of others who have not meat the fleſh of them wither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, for that becauſe they have not food ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and their body is conſumed; therefore this intemperance is hurtful to you that have and do not communicate to the needful, At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ye the judgement coming upon [you.]</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="44">44 <hi>Ye that are more eminent, enquire ye out the hungry, while as yet the Tower is not conſummate, for after the Tower ſhall be fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, ye will be willing to do good, and ſhall not have place; See therefore ye that glory in your riches, leaſt perhaps they groan who ſtand in need, and their groan aſcend
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33010:16"/>
to the Lord, and ye be excluded with your goods out of the gate of the Tower.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="45">45 <hi>Now therefore I ſay to you who are over the Church, and love the chief ſeats, do not ye become like unto witches; and the witches indeed carry their poyſons in boxes, but ye contain your poyſon and drugs in the heart, and ye will not purge your hearts, and mix your ſenſe with a pure heart, that you may have tender mercy from the great KING.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="46">46 <hi>See therefore Sons, leaſt perhaps theſe your diſſentions betray your LIFE, how will ye inſtruct the elected Ones of God, when your ſelves have not Diſcipline? Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh therefore your ſelves mutually, and be ye appeaſed among them, that alſo I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your Father appearing, may render a reaſon for you to the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p n="47">47 And when ſhe had left off to ſpeak with me, theſe ſix young men that build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed came, and took her away to the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and the other four took up the ſeat, and they went again into the Tower, their faces I ſaw not, becauſe they were aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; I asked her going away, that ſhe would reveal to me concerning the three ſhapes in which ſhe had appeared to me; But anſwering ſhe ſaid to me, concerning theſe thou muſt ask another, that it may be revealed to thee.</p>
               <p n="48">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:33010:16"/>48 But Brethren ſhe appeared to me in the firſt viſion a very old woman in the former year, and ſitting in a chair. But in another viſion ſhe had indeed a youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful face, but fleſh and hairs ancient, and ſtanding did ſpeak to me, but ſhe was more chearful than firſt. But in the third viſion ſhe was all more youthful, and comely in countenance, onely that ſhe had ancient hairs, but ſhe was chearful in face, and ſitting upon a ſeat.</p>
               <p n="49">49 For theſe very things I was exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly ſad, untill I ſhould know this viſion; I ſee that old woman in a viſion of the night, ſaying to me, <hi>All [thy] asking ſtands in need of humility, faſt therefore, and thou ſhalt receive from the Lord what thou requireſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="50">50 Therefore I faſted one day, in the ſame night there appeared to me a youth and ſaid, <hi>Why doſt thou frequently ask reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations in thy prayer? ſee, leaſt ſeeking many things thou hurt thy fleſh: let theſe revelations ſuffice thee, canſt thou ſee more ſtrong revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons then what thou haſt ſeen?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="51">51 <hi>I anſwering ſay unto him,</hi> Lord, this alone I ask, for the three figures of that old Womon, that the Revelation may be made compleat; <hi>He anſwered me,</hi> Ye are not ſenſeleſſe, but your dubitations make
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:33010:17"/>
ſenſeleſſe, becauſe that ye have not your heart to the Lord.</p>
               <p n="52">52 <hi>I anſwered to him and ſaid,</hi> but from thee we ſhall know theſe things more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently, <hi>hear ſaith he, of the figures which thou enquireſt;</hi> In the firſt viſion indeed why an old Woman appeared to thee ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upon a chair, becauſe your Spirit is more ancient, alſo is withered, and not having force for your infirmities and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation of heart.</p>
               <p n="53">53 For even as Elderly men who have not hope of renewing, and nothing elſe expect but their ſleep; ſo alſo ye infirmed by worldly buſineſſes, have delivered up your ſelves unto ſlothfulneſſe, and have not thrown off ſolicitude from you in the Lord, and your ſenſe is confuſed, and ye have waxed old in your ſadneſſes.</p>
               <p n="54">54 <hi>Why therefore ſhe ſate upon a chair I would know Lord; He anſwered,</hi> becauſe every infirm [man] ſitteth on a chair, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his infirmity, that his infirmity may be conteined; behold thou haſt the figure of the firſt viſion.</p>
               <p n="55">55 <hi>But in the ſecond viſion thou didſt ſee her ſtanding, and having a youthful face, and more chearful then the former, but fleſh and hairs ancient; Hear quoth he alſo this parable,</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:33010:17"/>
When any one hath now become older, he deſpairs of himſelf, becauſe of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity, and poverty, and he expecteth nothing elſe but the laſt day of his life: after that ſuddenly to him there is left an inheritance, and hearing he riſeth up, and being become chearful, he indueth ſtrength, and now he ſits not down, but ſtandeth, and is freed from his former ſorrows, and now he ſits not, but does manfully.</p>
               <p n="56">56 So alſo ye, hear ye the revelation which God hath revealed to you, becauſe the Lord hath had pitie on you, and hath renewed your Spirit, and ye have put off your infirmities, ſtrength hath come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, and ye have grown ſtrong in Faith, and God having ſeen your valour hath rejoyced, for this cauſe he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated to you the ſtructure of the Tower, and he will ſhew [you] other things, if from your whole heart ye ſhall have peace among your ſelves.</p>
               <p n="57">57 But in the third viſion thou ſaweſt her more youthful, honeſt, and chearful, and her countenance ſerene, for even as if any good meſſenger ſhould come upon any one ſad, immediately he forgets his ſorrow, and expecteth nothing elſe but
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33010:18"/>
the meſſage which he hath heard, he is comforted concerning the reſt, and his Spirit is renovated, becauſe of the joy which he hath taken; So alſo ye have got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the renovation of your ſpirits, ſeeing theſe good things.</p>
               <p n="58">58 And becauſe upon a ſeat ye ſaw her ſitting, it is a ſtrong poſition, becauſe a ſtool hath four feet, and ſtands ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; For alſo the world is contained by the four Elements, therefore they that ſhall do Repentance compleatly ſhall be youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and they that from their whole heart ſhall act Repentance ſhall be grounded: Thou haſt in full the revelation, ſeek no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more of things to be revealed, but if any thing muſt, it ſhall be revealed to thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="vision">
               <head>VISION. IV.</head>
               <p n="1">1 BRethren, I ſaw a viſion after twenty daies of the former viſion, the figure of tribulation about to come upon [us;] for I was going on in that way to <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pana,</hi> but from the publick way unto the village are nigh ten furlongs, but ſeldom is [any] journey made by that place.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:33010:18"/>2 And <hi>I</hi> walking alone, entreated the Lord, that theſe revelations, which he ſhewed to me by his holy Church, he would confirm, and would grant Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance unto all his Servants that are ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalized, that his Great and Honourable Name may be honoured, and becauſe he eſteemed me worthy, that he ſhould ſhew unto me his wonders, and <hi>I</hi> ſhould honour him, and give him thanks, as it were a voice anſwered unto me, <hi>DOVBT NOT</hi> HERMAS.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>I</hi> began therefore to think within me, and to ſay, What have I to doubt ſo grounded by the Lord, and who have ſeen honourable things?</p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>I</hi> went forward a little, Brethren, and behold I ſee the duſt up to Heaven, I began to ſay within me, What? do the Cattel come and ſtir up the duſt, but it was diſtant from me as it were a furlong; and behold, I ſee the duſt more and more ariſing, ſo that I ſuſpected it to be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from above.</p>
               <p n="5">5 But the Sun ſhone a little, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I ſee a great beaſt like unto a Whale, and out of his mouth proceeded fiery Locuſts, but the ſtature of that beaſt was almoſt an hundred foot, but he had an
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33010:19"/>
head like a round urnal veſſel; I began to weep and invoke the Lord that he might deliver me from it: then I remembred the word which I had heard, DOUBT NOT <hi>HERMAS.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6 Therefore brethren, having put on the faith of God, and remembred [him] that taught me great things, I delivered my ſelf boldly upon the Beaſt, but ſo did that beaſt come, ſo that it could in one ſtroke cruſh a City; I came near it, and the beaſt ſo huge extended it ſelf upon the Earth, and did ſhew forth nothing but it's tongue, and at all did not move it ſelf until I had paſt over it all.</p>
               <p n="7">7 But that beaſt had upon its head four colours, black, then red and bloudy, then golden, then white; but after I had gone over it, I went forward nigh thirty foot, and behold, there met me a certain vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin well adorned, as if coming out of her bed, all in white, and ſhod with white ſhoes, and down to her face having a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, but for a covering ſhe had her neat hairs.</p>
               <p n="8">8 I knew therefore by my former viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, becauſe ſhe is the CHURCH, and I became more chearful, <hi>but ſhe ſaluted me ſaying,</hi> Hail thou Man. <hi>And I ſaluted her,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:33010:19"/>
ſaying,</hi> Hail Lady; <hi>But ſhe anſwering ſaid to me,</hi> Hath nothing met thee, Man? <hi>I ſay to her, Lady,</hi> there hath met me ſuch a beaſt as could conſume a people; but by the power of God, and his ſingular loving kindneſſe, I have eſcaped it.</p>
               <p n="9">9 <hi>Thou haſt well eſcaped it, ſaith ſhe,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt thrown down thy ſolitude and ſolicitude before the Lord, and haſt opened thy heart unto him, believing that by no other thou couldſt be ſafe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept by his Great and Honourable Name; for this cauſe the Lord hath ſent his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, who is over the BEASTS, whoſe name is HEGRIN, and he hath ſtopt it's mouth, leaſt it ſhould ſlaughter thee. Great tribulation haſt thou eſcaped, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of thy faith, and who haſt not ſtood in doubt of ſuch a beaſt.</p>
               <p n="10">10 Go therefore and declare to the elected of God his great things; and thou ſhalt ſay unto them, that this beaſt is the figure of preſſure about to come upon [them;] if therefore ye ſhall prepare you, ye ſhall be able to eſcape it, if your heart ſhall be pure, and without ſpot, and if the reſt of your dayes ye ſhall ſerve God without complaint, caſt your ſolicitudes upon the Lord, and he ſhall direct them;
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:33010:20"/>
Believe God ye who are DOUBTFUL; becauſe he can do all things, both avert his wrath from you, and ſend you ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guards.</p>
               <p n="11">11 Wo to theſe doubtful ones who ſhall hear theſe words, and ſhall deſpiſe them, it had been better for them not to have been born.</p>
               <p n="12">12 <hi>I asked her of theſe four colours which the Beaſt had in his head, but ſhe anſwered unto me, ſaying,</hi> Again thou art curious, asking concerning things of this ſort; <hi>And I ſaid, Lady,</hi> demonſtrate unto me what theſe are; <hi>Hear ſaith ſhe,</hi> That BLACK is the World in which ye ſtay; but the FIERY and BLOUDY, becauſe this World muſt periſh by bloud and fire.</p>
               <p n="13">13 But the GOLDEN part are ye who have eſcaped this World; for as by fire Gold is tried, and becomes profitable, ſo alſo are ye tryed who dwell in them: Therefore they that ſhall continue, and ſhall be tried by them, ſhall be purged, and as Gold is made better, and puts off its droſſe, ſo alſo ye ſhall caſt off all ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and anguiſh, and ye ſhall be made clean for the ſtructure of the Tower; but the WHITE part is of the age about
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:33010:20"/>
to come on, in which the elected Ones of God ſhall dwell, becauſe the elect of God ſhall be immaculate and pure, into Life Eternal.</p>
               <p n="14">14 Thou therefore ceaſe not to ſpeak theſe things in the ears of the Saints; ye have alſo the figure of great tribulation about to come upon you, for if ye would it ſhall be nothing. In your mind retain theſe things that are preſcribed; Theſe things when ſhe had ſaid ſhe departed, but I ſaw not to what place ſhe went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; But there was a noiſe made, and I turned behind me, being afraid, and did think that beaſt was approaching.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End of the firſt Book.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="book">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:33010:21"/>
            <head>The ſecond Book of <hi>Hermas,</hi> the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Paul,</hi> which is intituled, the <hi>SHEEPHERD.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Proaem.</head>
            <p n="1">1. WHen I had prayed at home, and had ſat down upon the Bed, there entered a certain man of a reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend face, in a Paſtoral habit, cloathed with a white Cloak, carrying a bag in his ſhoulders, and a Rod in his hand, and he ſaluted me, and I reſaluted him, and forthwith he ſitteth down next me.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>And ſaith to me,</hi> I am ſent from that venerable Meſſenger, that I may dwell with thee the reſt of the daies of thy life. And I thought him to have come to tempt me; <hi>And I ſay to him,</hi> for who art thou? for I know to whom I am deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; <hi>He ſaith to me, knoweſt thou not me? No quoth I;</hi> I am that Sheepherd to whom thou art delivered.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>He as yet ſpeaking,</hi> his figure was
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:33010:22"/>
changed, and when I had known it to be him to whom I was delivered, I was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, and forthwith a fear came in upon me, and <hi>I</hi> was wholly broken with ſorrow, becauſe <hi>I</hi> had anſwered to him ſo unwiſely; <hi>He ſaith to me, be not confounded, but receive power in thy mind in my command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which I am about to give thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>For I am ſent, quoth he,</hi> that what things thou didſt before ſee, <hi>I</hi> may ſhew thee them all again, chiefly of theſe which are uſeful for YOU. Firſt of all my Commandments, and the figures of ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes write thou, but the reſt, as <hi>I</hi> ſhall ſhew [them thee] ſo ſhalt thou write them: But therefore I injoyn thee firſt to write my Commandments, and the Similitudes; that after that by reading, thou may'ſt more eaſily keep them.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Therefore I wrote the commands and ſimilitudes even as he had enjoyned me, which being heard, if YE ſhall keep them, and in them ſhall walk, and ſhall exerciſe them in a PURE MIND, ye ſhall receive from the Lord what things he promiſed you; but if theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heard, ye ſhall not act Repentance, but ſhall add unto your tranſgreſſions, ye ſhall receive the adverſe things from the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:33010:22"/>
Lord; all theſe that Sheepherd, the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger of Repentance, commanded me to write.</p>
            <div n="1" type="command">
               <head>COMMAND I.</head>
               <p n="1">1 FIrſt of all believe thou, that there is one God who creat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and finiſhed all things, and made all things of nothing, He capable of all things is alone great, who can neither with word be defined, nor by the mind con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Believe therefore on him, and fear him, and fearing, have ABSTINENCE; Theſe keep, and caſt away from thee all naughtineſſe, and put on the virtue of Righteouſneſſe, and thou ſhalt LIVE TO GOD, if thou ſhalt keep this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="command">
               <head>COMMAND II.</head>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>HE ſaid to me,</hi> have thou ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and be thou innocent and thou ſhalt be as the infant who knows not malice, who hath loſt the life of men. Firſt, of none ſpeak evilly, nor willingly hear one
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:33010:23"/>
ſpeaking evilly; But if thou alſo ſhalt hear, thou ſhalt be partaker of the ſins of the evil ſpeaker, and believing, thou likewiſe ſhalt have ſin, becauſe thou haſt believed him that ſpeaketh evilly of thy brother.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Detraction is pernitious, it is an unconſtant devil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, it conſiſteth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in peace, but remaineth alwaies in diſcord; contain thee from it, and have alwaies peace with thy brother; Put on holy CONSTANCY in which are no ſins, but all are gladſome, and do good out of thy labours, to all needful ones give ſimply, nothing doubting to whom thou mayſt give, give to all; FOR TO ALL WOULD GOD GIVE OF HIS GOOD THINGS.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Therefore they that get ſhall render account to God, why they received it, and to what; <q>
                     <hi>But they who get, having feigned neceſſity, ſhall render a reaſon, but he that giveth ſhall be innocent;</hi>
                  </q> for as he receiveth from the Lord he accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Miniſtry, in doubting nothing to whom he ſhould give, and to whom he ſhould not give, and he did this Miniſtry ſimply gloriouſly to God; Keep there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this command as I have ſpoke to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:33010:23"/>
thee, that thy repentance may be found ſimple, and it may become well to thy houſe, and have thou A CLEAN HEART.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="command">
               <head>COMMAND III.</head>
               <p n="1">1 A <hi>Gain he ſaid to me,</hi> love the truth, and let all true ſpeech proceed out of thy mouth, that THE SPIRIT WHICH THE LORD HATH PLAC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ED IN THY FLESH, may be found TRUE with all men, and the Lord may be magnified who HATH GI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEN A SPIRIT IN THEE, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord is true in every word, and there is not a lie in him; Therefore they that lie deny the Lord, not reſtoring to God the PLEDGE which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
               <p n="2">2 FOR THEY RECEIVED A SPIRIT WITHOUT LYE. This if they render ſubject to lying, they do ſtain the command of the Lord, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come deceivers; I having heard theſe things wept vehemently, who when he ſaw me weeping, he ſaid to me, why weepeſt thou? And I ſaid, becauſe Lord I know
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:33010:24"/>
not if I can be able to be ſaved; Why ſaith he?</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>And I ſaid,</hi> becauſe never Lord have I ſpoken a true word in my life, but have alwayes lived in ſimulation, and a lye, for the truth I have affirmed to all, and there hath not any one contradicted me, but truſt hath been had to my word; how then can I live ſeeing I have ſo done? <hi>And he ſaid to me,</hi> thou indeed thinkeſt well and truly, for it became thee as the ſervant of God, to walk in the truth, and not to conjoyn an evil conſcience with the SPIRIT OF TRUTH, nor to cauſe ſadneſs to the holy and true Spirit of God.</p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>And I ſaid to him,</hi> Never Lord have I heard theſe words ſo diligently; <hi>And he ſaid to me,</hi> Now thou heareſt them take care after this, that alſo theſe falſe things which before thou haſt ſpoken for thy employments, with theſe words [that] alſo they may receive faith, for alſo they can receive faith, if after this thou ſhalt ſpeak true things, and if thou ſhalt keep the truth, thou ſhalt be able to attaine LIFE; And whoſoever ſhall hear this command, and ſhall do it, and ſhall depart from lying, he ſhall LIVE TO GOD.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="command">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:33010:24"/>
               <head>COMMAND IIII.</head>
               <p n="1">1 I Command thee quoth he, that thou keep CHASTITY, &amp; let not the thought of [thine] heart ariſe to thee of a ſtrange matrimony or of Fornication, for this begetteth great ſin; but be thou alwaies mindfull of the Lord at all hours, and thou ſhalt NEVER SIN; For if this ſo evil cogitation aſcend into thine heart, thou commiteſt a great ſin; And they that do theſe things follow the way of death; See thou therefore abſtain thy ſelf from this cogitation, for where chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty remains in the heart of a juſt man, there ought an evil cogitation never to ariſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>And I ſaid to him,</hi> Lord permit me to ſpeak a few words with thee; <hi>Speak ſaith he; And I ſaid to him,</hi> Lord, if any ſhould have a Wife faithfull in the Lord, and ſhould find her in adultery, doth the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band ſin, if he live together with her? <hi>And he ſaid to me,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 As long as he knoweth not her ſin, the Husband is without blame, dwelling together with her; But if the Husband
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:33010:25"/>
ſhall know his Wife to have transgreſſed, and the Wife ſhall not do Repentance, and remains in her Fornication, and the Husband live with her, he ſhall be guilty of her ſin, &amp; partaker of her Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery; <hi>And I ſaid to him,</hi> What then if the Woman ſhall continue in her faults? <hi>And he ſaid,</hi> Let the Husband ſend her away, and let the Husband remain by himſelf; but if he ſhall ſend away his Wife, and ſhall marry another, he alſo committeth Adultery.</p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>And I ſaid to him,</hi> What if the woman put away ſhould do repentance, and would be returned to her Husband, ſhall ſhe not be received by her Husband? <hi>And he ſaid to me,</hi> Yea, if her Husband ſhall not receive her, he ſinneth, and admitteth a great ſin to himſelf; but he ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive her a ſinner, who hath done repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; But not often; for to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God the Repentance is one.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Becauſe of repentance therefore, the Husband having put away his Wife, ought not to marry another. Here the act is alike both in the Husband and in the VVife, not only is it adultery to them who pollute their own fleſh, but alſo ſhe who maketh an Image commits Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery;
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:33010:25"/>
But if in theſe deeds ſhe perſevere, and do not repentance, depart from her, and do not live together with her other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, alſo thou ſhalt be partaker of her ſin.</p>
               <p n="6">6 For this cauſe it is commanded you that ye remain ſingle both the Husband and the VVife, for there may be repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in [a deed] of this ſort; but alſo <hi>I</hi> give not occaſion that theſe be ſo done, but that he who hath ſinned, ſin no more, but of his former ſins God who hath the power of giving ſoundneſs, ſhall give a remedy, becauſe it is he that hath power of all things.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Again, <hi>I asked and ſaid,</hi> becauſe my Lord hath eſteemed me to be worthy, that thou ſhouldeſt dwell with me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, declare unto me a few words, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>I</hi> underſtand not any thing, and my heart is ſtopped by my former converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and open to me my ſence, becauſe I am vehemently ſtupid, and of the the whole <hi>I</hi> underſtand nothing.</p>
               <p n="8">8 And anſwering, <hi>he ſaid unto me,</hi> I am ſet over to repentance, and to all that do repentance I give feeling; Doth it not ſeem to thee to be great wiſdome to do repentance, becauſe he that doth repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:33010:26"/>
obtaineth great feeling, for he feels himſelf to have ſinned, and to have done wickedly in the ſight of the Lord, and he is remembred BY THE INTEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LECT that he hath treſpaſſed, and he doth repentance, and he worketh not wickedly any more, but worketh well, and humbleth his Soul and vexeth it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it hath ſinned.</p>
               <p n="9">9 Thou ſeeſt therefore that repentance is great SENSE, <hi>And</hi> I <hi>ſaid to him,</hi> for this cauſe Lord <hi>I</hi> deligently inquire all things, becauſe I am a ſinner, that I may know what things I may work and may live, becauſe many are my ſinns; <hi>And he ſaid unto me,</hi> thou ſhalt live if thou thou ſhalt keep theſe my commandments, and whoſoever ſhall hear and do theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands ſhall LIVE TO GOD.</p>
               <p n="10">10 <hi>And I ſaid to him,</hi> even now Lord, I have heard from certain DOCTORS that other repentance there is not except that, when we deſcend into the water, and receive the remiſſion of our ſinns, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that not to ſin, but to remain in CHASTITY.</p>
               <p n="11">11 <hi>And he ſaith to me,</hi> Thou haſt rightly heard, but now becauſe diligently thou askeſt all things, alſo this I demonſtrate
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:33010:26"/>
to thee, not giving occaſion to them who are about to believe, or who have believed the Lord.</p>
               <p n="12">12 For they who have already believed, or who are about to believe, the repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of ſins they have not but the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; For to thoſe who were called be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe dayes hath the Lord ordained repentantance, becauſe the cogitations of the heart, God doth know, and he knows the infirmity of men, and the manifold wickedneſſe of the Devil, with which he endevoureth ſome miſchief to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God, and layes wait for them malitiouſly.</p>
               <p n="13">13 Therefore the mercifull God hath had compaſſion of his handy-work; And hath placed that repentance, and the power of this repentance hath he given to ME; And therefore <hi>I ſay to thee,</hi> that after that calling great and holy, if any one ſhall be tempted by the Devil, and ſhall ſin, he hath one repentance; But thenceforth if he ſin and doth repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, it ſhall not be profitable to the man that doth ſuch things, for difficultly ſhall he LIVE TO GOD.</p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>And I ſaid,</hi> Lord I have revived whenas ſo diligently I have heard theſe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:33010:27"/>
Commandments, for I know that if after this I ſhall add nothing to my ſins, I ſhall be ſaved, <hi>And he ſaid,</hi> ſafe, I ſay and all whoſoever ſhall do theſe commands ſhall be ſafe; And again <hi>I ſaid to him,</hi> Lord becauſe thou patiently heareſt me, demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate unto me this, <hi>ſay it quoth he.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15 If the Husband or Wife of any one ſhall depart, and any of them ſhall marry, what? Doth he ſin? He that marrieth, ſinneth not quoth he; but if he would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main by himſelf, he acquireth great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to himſelf with the Lord; Keep therefore CHASTITY, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, and thou ſhalt live to God; Theſe things that I ſpeak with thee, keep thou henceforth from [the time] wherein I was delivered to thee, and dwell in thine houſe, and there ſhall be remiſſion to thy former ſins, if thou ſhalt keep my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments; But alſo to all there ſhall be remiſſion, who ſhall keep my command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="command">
               <head>COMMAND V.</head>
               <p n="1">1 BE thou of a poyſed mind quoth he, and patient, and thou ſhalt
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:33010:27"/>
have dominion over all moſt wicked works, and ſhalt work ALL righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; Becauſe if thou ſhalt be PATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ENT, THE HOLY SPIRIT THAT DWELLETH IN THEE, ſhall be clean, and ſhall not be obſcured by any moſt wicked Spirit; But rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing it ſhall be inlarged, and ſhall feaſt in the VESSELL in which it inhabiteth, and it ſhall obey the Lord chearful in great peace.</p>
               <p n="2">2 But if any wrath ſhould come over it, immediately the holy Spirit, which is IN THEE ſhall be ſtraitened, and ſhall ſeek to depart, for it is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>focated by a moſt wicked fight, and it hath not a place of obeying the Lord, as it would, for it is tribulated by AN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GER; Therefore both Spirits when they inhabit together, it is pernitious to man.</p>
               <p n="3">3 For if any one ſhall pluck up a little wormwood, &amp; put it into a pot of honey, ſhall not all the honey be deſtroyed? And ſo much honey by a little wormwoode periſheh, and looſeth the ſweetnſſe of honey; And now it hath not accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with its Lord, becauſe all the honey is made bitter, and hath loſt its uſe; but
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:33010:28"/>
if wormwood be not put into honey, it ſhall be ſweet, and in uſe to its Lord.</p>
               <p n="4">4 See therefore how much ſweeter equall mindedneſſes is then honey, and he ſhall be profitable to the Lord that ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in it, for WRATH is unprofitable; If therefore anger ſhall be mixt with AEQUANIMITY, the mind is afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and its prayer is not profitable to God.</p>
               <p n="5">5 <hi>And I ſaid to him,</hi> I would know Lord the wickedneſſe of anger, that I may keep me from it; <hi>And he ſaid to me,</hi> Thou ſhalt know it, and if thou ſhalt not keep thy ſelf from it, thou ſhalt looſe thy hope with thy whole houſe; But depart from it, for I am with thee the MESSENGER OF EQUITY. And all that depart from it, whoſoever ſhall do repentance with all their hearts, they ſhall LIVE TO GOD; but alſo I will be with them, and will preſerve them all.</p>
               <p n="6">6 For they are all juſtified who ſhall do repentance through the moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ANGELL. Hear now quoth he, the noughtineſs of anger how wicked and how noxious it is, and by what manner it overthrows the ſervants of God, for they who are full in the faith, it cannot
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:33010:28"/>
hurt them, becauſe the power of God is with them, for it over-turns the DOUBTFULL and EMPTY ones.</p>
               <p n="7">7 But as oft as it ſhall ſee ſuch men, it injecteth it ſelf into their hearts, and of NOTHING either a Husband or a Wife taketh bitterneſſe, becauſe of the things which are in uſe, or for a check, or for any ſuperfluous word (if any thing by chance ſhould happen,) or for any friend, or debt, or for ſuch like ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous things, for theſe are fooliſh and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous, and vain to the ſervants of God.</p>
               <p n="8">8 But AEQUANIMITY is vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant and ſtrong, and hath great power, and fitteth in great Majeſty, chearful, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing in peace, and honouring the Lord in every time meekly; for this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quanimity dwelleth with the firm belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.</p>
               <p n="9">9 For ANGER is fooliſh, and light, and witleſſe; but of fooliſhneſſe is born bitterneſſe, and of bitterneſſe wrath, but of wrath madneſſe; This madneſſe created of ſo many evils, worketh great ſin, and uncurable, for when all theſe are in ONE VESSEL, VVHERE alſo
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:33010:29"/>
THE HOLY SPIRIT RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAINS; The Veſſel endures not this, but floweth over, becauſe the tender Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit cannot with the evil Spirit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit, it departeth and dwelleth with the MEEK. After that when it ſhall have departed from the man, IN VVHOM IT DVVELT, the man becomes empty from the holy Spirit, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is filled with malignant Spirits, and is blinded by evil cogitation.</p>
               <p n="10">10 Depart thou therefore from wrath, and put on AEQUANIMITY, and reſiſt wrath, and thou ſhalt be found with modeſty and chaſtity with God; See therefore leaſt perhaps thou neglect this Command, for if to this Commandment thou ſhalt perform obedience; Alſo the reſt of my commands which I am about to injoyn thee ſhalt thou be able to keep; Therefore now confirm thy ſelf in theſe commands, that thou mayeſt live to God, and whoſoever ſhall keep theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, ſhall LIVE TO GOD.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="command">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:33010:29"/>
               <head>COMMAND VI.</head>
               <p n="1">1 I Had injoyned thee quoth he in the firſt command, that thou ſhouldeſt keep FAITH, and FEAR, and PE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NITENCY; Yea quoth I Lord; But now I will ſhew unto thee the vertues of theſe commandments, that thou mayſt know their effects, how they are placed to the juſt, likewiſe, and to the unjuſt; Thou therefore believe the juſt, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the unjuſt [in] nothing, for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe hath the right way, but unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs the evil; but keep thou the right way, but the wicked [way] forſake thou; But the evil way, hath not a good end, but hath many offences.</p>
               <p n="2">2 It is rough and thorny and leads to deſtruction, and it is noxious to the men that walk in it; but whoſo ſeek the right way, they walk equally without offence, becauſe it is not rough, neither thorny; Thou ſeeſt therefore that better it is to go by this way, for thou ſhalt go ſaith he, &amp; whoſoever from their whole heart have believed in the Lord, they ſhall go through it.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:33010:30"/>3 <hi>Hear now ſaith he,</hi> firſt of FAITH, there are two SPIRITS with man, one of equity, and one of iniquity; <hi>And I ſaid to him,</hi> how Lord ſhall I know that there are two SPIRITS with a man? <hi>Hear ſaith he,</hi> and underſtand; The ſpirit of righteouſneſſe is tender, gentle and baſhfull, affable and quiet, when there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ſhall aſcend into thine heart, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately it ſpeaketh with thee of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, of modeſty, of chaſtity, of bountifulneſſe, of pardon, of charity, of piety; All theſe when they ſhall aſcend into thine heart, know that the ſpirit of equity is with thee; to this GENIUS therefore, and to its works give thou credit.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Take now alſo the works of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of iniquity, firſt it is bitter, wrathful, and fooliſh, and its works are pernitious and overthrow the ſervants of God; when therefore theſe things ſhall aſcend into thine heart, thou ſhalt underſtand from its works this to be the ſpirit of INI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>QUITY.</p>
               <p n="5">5 How Lord ſhall I underſtand? Hear quoth he, and underſtand, when wrath ſhall happen to thee or bitterneſſe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that to be IN THEE; After
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:33010:30"/>
that the deſire of many works, and of the daintieſt meats, and of drunkenneſſes, and the deſirings of many ſtrange things, and pride and much ſpeaking, and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and whatſoever things are like theſe; Thou therefore when thou ſhalt know its works, depart from them all, &amp; believe it in nothing, becauſe its works are evil, and do not agree to the ſervants of God.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Thou haſt therefore the works of both the Spirits, underſtand now and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Genius, of Righteouſneſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe its TEACHING is good. For though a man be moſt happy, and the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitation of the other GENIUS aſcend into his heart, that man or woman muſt needs ſin; But alſo if a man ſhall be moſt wicked, or a woman, and the works of the GENIUS of righteouſneſſe aſcend up into his heart, it muſt needs be that he or ſhe do ſomthing of good; Thou ſeeſt therefore that it is good to follow the Spirit of equity, if therefore thou ſhalt follow it, and ſhalt believe its works, thou ſhalt LIVE TO GOD; And they who ſhall believe its works ſhall live to God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="command">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:33010:31"/>
               <head>COMMAND VII.</head>
               <p n="1">1 FEar the Lord quoth he, and keep his Commandments, for keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the precepts of God, thou ſhalt be potent in every act, and every buſineſſe of thine ſhall be incomparable; for fearing the Lord, thou ſhalt work all good things; This is the FEAR wherewith thou muſt fear, that thou mayeſt be able to be ſaved; but the Devil fear thou not, for fearing the Lord thou ſhalt have domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over him; Becauſe there is no power in him.</p>
               <p n="2">2 But he in whom power is not, he is not ſo much as to be feared; but in whom there is glorious power, he alſo is to be feared; for every one having power is alſo to be feared, for he that hath not power is contemned by all; fear thou plainly the fictions of the Devil, becauſe they are malignant; for fearing thou ſhalt fear the Lord, and the works of the Devil thou ſhalt not do, but ſhalt abſtain thee from them.</p>
               <p n="3">3 For fear is twofold; for if thou wouldſt work evil, fearing the Lord, that
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:33010:31"/>
indeed thou ſhalt not do; but if thou wouldſt work good, verily the fear of the Lord is ſtrong, great, and glorious. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore FEAR God, and thou ſhalt live, &amp; whoſoever ſhall fear him, keeping his Commandements, their LIFE is with the Lord; but of thoſe that keep them not, neither is life in them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="command">
               <head>COMMAND VIII.</head>
               <p n="1">1 I Said to thee, <hi>quoth he,</hi> that the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God are double, and AB<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STINENCE is double; therefore from ſome things it behoves to abſtain, but from ſome things not. Manifeſt, <hi>quoth I,</hi> to me Lord from what things I muſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain, and from what not. <hi>Hear, ſaith he,</hi> from evil abſtain, and do not do it, but from good do thou not abſtain, but do it; for if thou ſhalt abſtain from good, and ſhalt not do it, thou ſhalt ſin: Abſtain therefore from all evil, and thou ſhalt know all Righteouſneſſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2 What wicked things are theſe, <hi>quoth I,</hi> from which I muſt abſtain? <hi>Hear, ſaith he,</hi> from Adulteries, Drunkenneſſes, and evil Riotings, from too much meat, from
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:33010:32"/>
gorgeouſneſſe and unhoneſty, from pride, from abnegation, from lying, from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faming, from feigned wickedneſſe, from remembrance of injury, and from moſt evil fame, for theſe are the works of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, from which it is needful for the ſervant of God to abſtain; for he that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abſtain in theſe cannot LIVE TO GOD.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Hear now, <hi>quoth he,</hi> alſo the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of them, and indeed there are many things as yet from which the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of God ought to abſtain, from theft, from denying, from falſe teſtimony, from covetouſneſſe, from pride, and whatever are like to them. Theſe therefore ſeem to be evil to thee, do they not? Truly they are very evil to the Servants of God, from all theſe therefore ought the ſervant of God to abſtain.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Abſtain thou therefore from all theſe, that thou mayeſt live to God, and mayeſt be wrote with the ABSTEINERS; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe are they from wch thou ought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to abſtein; But from which thou ought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not to abſtein, <hi>Hear thou,</hi> from all good works abſtein not, but do them; <hi>Hear, quoth he,</hi> the vertue of the good works which thou oughteſt to work, that thou mayeſt be ſafe.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:33010:32"/>5 The firſt of all is Faith, the fear of the Lord, Charity, Concord, Equity, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, Patience, Chaſtity, then theſe there is nothing better in the life of men, who ſhall keep theſe, and do them in their life. Next hear their conſequences, To adminiſter to Widows, not to deſpiſe Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans and poor men, and to redeem the Servants of God out of neceſſity, to be apt to entertain, for in Hoſpitality often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times is found good fruit, not to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, to be quiet, to become moſt humble of all men, to reſpect the Elders in birth, to ſtudy unto Righteouſneſſe, to preſerve brother-hood, to ſuffer reproaches, to be of a contented mind.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Not to reject thoſe fallen from the Faith, but to make them quiet in mind, to admoniſh the ſinners, not to preſſe the debters, and if there be any thing like theſe: Theſe ſeem to thee to be good, do they not? For what ſay I, is better then theſe words; Live thou therefore in theſe Commandments, and do not depart from them, for if thou ſhalt keep all theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements thou ſhalt live to God, and all who ſhall keep theſe Commandements ſhall LIVE TO GOD.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="command">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:33010:33"/>
               <head>COMMAND IX.</head>
               <p n="1">1 AGain he ſaid to me, remove from thee DOVBTING, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all ſhalt thou doubt, asking any thing from the Lord, ſay not within thee, <hi>But how can I ſeek any thing from the Lord, and obtein? Seeing I am a ſinner of ſuch great evils againſt the Lord;</hi> Do not think this, but from thy whole heart be converted to the Lord; Ask without doubting, and thou ſhalt know the tender mercy of the Lord, that thee he will not forſake, but ſhall fulfill the petition of thy Soul.</p>
               <p n="2">2 For God is not, like men mindful of injuries, but he is unmindful of inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and he hath compaſſion on his han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy-work; Purge therefore thine heart from all the vices of this world, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the predicted words given to thee by God, and thou ſhalt receive all the good things which thou askeſt, and of all thy petitions nothing ſhall be wanting to thee, if without doubting thou ſhalt ask of the Lord.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Who therefore are not ſuch, they obtein not at all any thing of theſe which
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:33010:33"/>
they ask; for whoſo are full of Faith, they ask all things believing, and they receive of the Lord, becauſe without DOVBT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ING they ask, for every doubting man if he ſhall not do repentance, ſhall diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultly LIVE TO GOD.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Purifie therefore thine heart from doubting, and put on faith, and believe God, and all things which thou askeſt ſhalt thou obtein; but if ſometimes thou askeſt a petition &amp; doſt not get it, do not doubt, becauſe thou getteſt not quickly the petition of thy Soul; for perhaps, becauſe of tentation, or for thy ſin, which thou art ignorant of, thou ſhalt more ſlowly get thy petition; but do not thou deſiſt in ſeeking the petition of thy Soul, and thou ſhalt get it; but if thou ceaſeſt in asking, complain of thy ſelf, and not of God, that he hath not given it thee.</p>
               <p n="5">5 See therefore this DOUBTING, how pernicious it is, and fierce, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny by the roots it plucks up from the Faith, even very faithful and firm [ones;] for why this doubting is the Daughter of the Devil, and very wickedly dealeth ſhe with the Servants of God. Contemn therefore doubting and thou ſhalt rule over her in every thing, put on firm and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:33010:34"/>
potent faith, for faith promiſeth all things and accompliſheth all things, but doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing doth not believe it ſelf about to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein any thing in all its works which it doth.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Thou ſeeſt therefore, <hi>quoth he,</hi> That faith is from above, from God, and hath great power; but dubitation is an earthly Spirit, and from the Devil, not having power; Keep thou therefore the vertue of faith, but from doubting depart thou which hath not vertue, and thou ſhalt live to God, and they ſhall all LIVE TO GOD whoſoever ſhall do theſe things.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="command">
               <head>COMMAND X.</head>
               <p n="1">1 DRive far from thee all SADNESSE for ſhe is the ſiſter of doubting, and wrath; <hi>How quoth I Lord,</hi> is ſhe the Siſter of theſe? Sadneſſe ſeems to me one thing, another wrath, another doubting; <hi>And he ſaith,</hi> without ſenſe, thou under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeſt not, for ſadneſſe of all Spirits is the moſt wicked, and worſt to the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God, and it deſtroyeth all their
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:33010:34"/>
Spirits, and vexeth the holy Spirit, and again makes it whole.</p>
               <p n="2">2 I am fooliſh, <hi>quoth I, Lord,</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not theſe queſtions, how it can vex, and again make whole, I underſtand not; <hi>Hear, quoth he, and underſtand?</hi> They who never ſought out the Truth, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of [its] Majeſty, but onely belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved they are involved in the employments and riches of the Heathen men, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is a lying Prophet, who deſtroys the ſenſes of the Servants of God, (but not of theſe doubtful ones) who truſt in the Lord fully.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Therefore theſe doubtful ones come as to a Divine, and ask him, what is about to befall them; and that lying Prophet having none of the power of the divine Spirit in him, ſpeaketh to them according to their asking, and fills their ſouls with promiſes, even as they would; but that PROPHET is empty, and anſwereth empty things to the empty; for whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is asked [him] of vain men, he will anſwer them vain things.</p>
               <p n="4">4 But ſome words he ſpeaketh true, for the Devil filleth him with his Spirit, that he may caſt down ſome of the juſt; who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever therefore are ſtrong in the faith
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:33010:35"/>
of the Lord, and are cloathed with the TRUTH, to ſuch Spirits they are not joyned, but depart from them, but as many as are doubtful, and thenceforth act Repentance, they conſult even as the Heathens, and heap up very great ſin to themſelves, ſerving IDOLS.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Whoſoever therefore are ſuch, they ask for any buſineſſe, they worſhip ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and are fools, and empty from the TRUTH, for EVERY SPIRIT GIVEN OF GOD IS NOT ASKED; but having the vertue of the Divinity, from it ſelf ſpeaketh all things, becauſe it is from above, from the power of the divine Spirit; but whoſo being asked ſpeaketh according to the deſire, and of many other things of this world, they of this ſort underſtand not the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions of the DIVINITY, for they are darkned by theſe buſineſſes, and are corrupted, and broken.</p>
               <p n="6">6 As good vines that are neglected, by weeds and thorns are preſſed and killed, ſo alſo the men who have credited ſuch, they have fallen into many buſineſſes and actions, and are made empty from their FEELING, and underſtand nothing at all, thinking about riches; but if at
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:33010:35"/>
any time they ſhall hear of the Lord, their SENSE is in their buſineſſes, but they that have the fear of the Lord, and ſearch out from God the Truth, they have every thought unto the Lord; all things that are ſpoken to them they perceive, becauſe they have the fear of the Lord in them; for WHERE THE SPIRIT OF THE LORD IN HABITETH, THERE alſo IS adjoyned MUCH FEELING; adjoyn thy ſelf therefore to the Lord, and thou ſhalt underſtand, and perceive all things.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Hear now, O unwiſe, after what manner SADNESSE vexeth the holy Spirit, and how it makes it whole; when a DOUBTFUL one ſhall fall into any buſineſſe, and it doth not ſucceed to him becauſe of dubitation, this ſorrow entreth into the man, and MAKETH SAD THE HOLY SPIRIT, and vexeth it; after that again, when WRATH ſhall happen to a man for any buſineſſe, he is vehemently enraged, and this wrath entreth in into the inward parts of him that is angry, and he is vexed in his bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe which he doth, and after that repenteth him that he hath done e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villy.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:33010:36"/>8 Therefore both theſe things hurt the holy ſpirit, DOUBTING and SAD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NESSE. Doubting, becauſe his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſucceeded not; and Sadneſſe, becauſe he cauſed wrath to his SPIRIT; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move ſorrow therefore from thee, AND DO NOT THOU OFFEND THE HOLY SPIRIT WHICH DWELETH IN THEE, LEAST IT intreat the Lord and DEPART from thee, for the ſpirit of the Lord which is given into the FLESH indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not ſadneſſe.</p>
               <p n="9">9 Cloath thee therefore with chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which alwaies hath favour with the Lord, and thou ſhalt be joyful in it; for every chearful man worketh well and ſavoureth good things, and diſpiſeth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe; But a ſorrowful man doth evilly, becauſe he maketh ſad the holy Spirit, which is given to the chearful man: and again he doth evil in that, the ſorrowful man intreats the Lord, and doth not before make confeſſion, and he obtaineth not of God what he asketh; for alwaies the prayer of the ſorrowful man hath not the force that it may approach the ALTAR of God.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:33010:36"/>10 <hi>And I ſaid to him,</hi> Lord why hath not the prayer of the ſorrowful man the power to aſcend to the Altar of the Lord? Becauſe heavineſſe ſitteth in his heart; Therefore when the prayer of a man ſhall be mixed with ſorrow, it will not ſuffer the prayer to aſcend pure to the ALTAR of God; for as Wine mixed with Vinegar hath not the ſame ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo alſo heavineſſe mixed with the holy Spirit, hath not the ſame prayer clean; Therefore cleanſe thee from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſadneſſe and thou ſhalt live to God, and they ſhall all LIVE TO GOD who ſhall caſt away from themſelves ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſhall put on chearfulneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="command">
               <head>COMMAND XI.</head>
               <p n="1">1 HE ſhewed me men ſitting on ſeats, and one ſitting in a Chaire, <hi>and he ſaid to me, Seeſt thou thoſe who ſit on benches?</hi> I ſee them Lord, <hi>quoth I;</hi> Theſe are the Faithful, and he that ſitteth in the Chair is the TERRESTRIALL SPIRIT: For into the Church of the men it approacheth not but flyeth away, but it applieth it ſelf to the DOUBT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FUL
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:33010:37"/>
ones, and empty and in corners, and hidden places it divineth to them, and it delighteth them in ſpeaking ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to all the deſires of their heart.</p>
               <p n="2">2 For what is committed to empty veſſels doth not run over, but they agree one to another, but when it ſhall come into the company of juſt men having the SPIRIT of the Divinity, and their prayer is to the Lord, that man is fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtated becauſe that Tereſtrial Spirit flyeth from him, and he becometh dumb, nor can ſpeak any thing.</p>
               <p n="3">3 As in a CELLAR, if thou ſhalt cover Wine or Oyl, and amongſt theſe veſſels ſhalt put an empty veſſel, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain wouldeſt take off the covering, that veſſel which thou didſt put, thou ſhalt find empty; So alſo EMPTY PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PHETS when they ſhall come among the ſpirit of juſt men, ſuch as they come, ſuch are they found.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Thou haſt the life of both the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, try therefore by life and works, the man that ſaith himſelf to have the holy Spirit, but believe thou the Spirit coming from God, having vertue; but to the earthly empty ſpirit which is from the Devil, in which there is not faith, nor power, do not give credit.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:33010:37"/>5 Hear therefore a Similitude which I am about to tell thee; Take a ſtone and caſt it toward Heaven; Or again, take a ſquirt of water and ſquirt it out towards Heaven, and ſee if thou canſt ſmite the Heaven. <hi>How, quoth I,</hi> Lord can theſe things be? For both theſe which thou haſt ſpoken cannot be done; even as there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe cannot be done, So the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtrial ſpirit is without power, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out effect.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Take now the power coming down from above in this ſimilitude; The hail is the leaſt grain, and when it falls upon the head of a man, how doth it bring griefs? Or again, look on the drop of rain which from the eaves falls on the earth and makes hollow the ſtone: So therefore the leaſt things which from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove fall upon the earth have great pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Adjoyn thee therefore to this man having the POWER, and from that empty one depart thou.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="command">
               <head>COMMAND XII.</head>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>AGain he ſaid to me,</hi> remove from thee all evil DESIRE, and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:33010:38"/>
put on the good and holy deſire; for having put on the good deſire, Thou ſhalt hate the evil and ſhalt refrain it, even as thou wouldeſt; For evil deſire is to be abhored, and it is difficultly miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated, it is very horrible and wild, and with its wildneſſe conſumeth men, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if into it a ſervant of God ſhall fall, and unleſſe he ſhall be wiſe, he ſhall be conſumed by it badly.</p>
               <p n="2">2 But it conſumeth ſuch who have not the cloathing of the good deſire, and it involves them in the buſineſſes of this World, and delivers them to death. What are the works Lord, <hi>quoth</hi> I, of the evil deſire which deliver men up to DEATH? Demonſtrate unto me, that I may depart from them; Hear <hi>ſaith he,</hi> in what works evil deſire delivers the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God to death: The ſpirit of all men is earthly and light, and hath not power at all, and ſpeaketh many things; <hi>And I ſaid,</hi> how then can any know them?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Hear <hi>quoth he,</hi> of both the VESSELS, and as <hi>I</hi> ſay to thee, ſo ſhalt thou try the Prophet of God, and the falſe prophet; Firſt, ſo prove the man THAT HATH THE SPIRIT OF GOD, becauſe
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:33010:38"/>
the ſpirit which is from above is quiet, and humble, and it departeth from ALL wickedneſſe, and the vain deſire of this World, and maketh it ſelf more humble then every man, AND AN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SWERETH TO NO MAM BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ING ASKED, nor doth it anſwer to all men; NEITHER WHEN MAN WILL, DOTH THE SPIRIT OF GOD SPEAK, but then it ſpeaketh when God will.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Therefore WHEN A MAN WHO HATH THE SPIRIT OF GOD SHALL COME IN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TO THE CHURCH OF JUST MEN having the faith of God, and prayer is made to God; then THE holy MESSENGER OF the DIVI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NITY FILLETH THAT MAN WITH THE HOLY SPIRIT, AND HE SPEAKETH IN THE THRONG AS GOD WILL</p>
               <p>So therefore is the ſpirit of Divinity known in whomſoever the ſpirit of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity ſpeaketh.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Hear now alſo of the TERRES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TRIALL SPIRIT empty and fooliſh, not having power; But firſt a
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:33010:39"/>
man is conceived to have this ſpirit, for he exalteth himſelf, and WILL HAVE THE UPPERMOST CHAIR <q>
                     <hi>and he is wicked and talkative, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeth in delights, and in many pleaſures,</hi>
                  </q> and TAKETH THE REWARD OF HIS DIVINATION, WHICH IF HE SHALL NOT GET, HE DOTH NOT DI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VINE. Can the Spirit <q>
                     <hi>of God take rewards thus and Divine? it doth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeem the Prophet of God to do theſe things.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6 But EVIL DESIRE is to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet anothers wife, or a woman to covet anothers husband, and to covet the ſumptuouſneſſe of riches, and the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of ſuperfluous meats, and much drunkenneſſe, and many pleaſures, for many delights are fooliſh, and many pleaſures are ſuperfluous to the ſervants of God; Therefore this evil deſire is pernitious, which deadneth the ſervants of God, for this deſire is of the Devil.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Therefore whoſoever ſhall depart from evil deſire, they ſhall LIVE TO GOD, for whoſoever ſhall be ſubjected to evil deſire, ſhall die for ever, for this evil deſire is mortiferous.</p>
               <p n="8">8 Thou therefore put on the deſire of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:33010:39"/>
righteouſneſſe, and armed with the fear of the Lord reſiſt the evil deſire, for fear dwelleth in the good deſire; and the evil deſire when it ſhall ſee thee arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the fear of the Lord reſiſting it, it ſhall flie far from thee, and ſhall not appear before thee, fearing thy weapons, and thou ſhalt obtain the victory, and thou ſhalt be crowned becauſe of her, and attaining unto the good deſire, and thou ſhalt give the victory to God which thou haſt gotten, and ſhalt ſerve him in working as thou thy ſelf wouldeſt.</p>
               <p n="9">9 But if thou ſhalt ſerve the good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and ſhalt be ſubject unto it, thou ſhalt be able to rule over the evil deſire, and it ſhall be ſubjected to thee, even as thou wouldeſt.</p>
               <p n="10">10 I would know Lord, how I ought to ſerve the GOOD DESIRE? Hear quoth he, have thou the fear of God and faith in God, and love the Truth, and love the Righteouſneſſe, and do good; Theſe things working thou ſhalt be a proved ſervant of the Lord, and ſhalt ſerve to God, and all whoſoever ſhall ſerve the Good deſire, ſhall LIVE TO GOD.</p>
               <p n="11">11 Theſe twelve Commands being
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:33010:40"/>
finiſhed, <hi>He ſaid to me,</hi> Thou haſt theſe Commands, walk in them, and exhort the men that hear them that they do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and their repentance ſhall be made pure the reſt of the dayes of their life And this Miniſtry which to thee I give, unfold thou diligently, and thou ſhalt attain much fruit, and ſhalt find favour with all thoſe who ſhall Act Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and ſhall believe thy words, for I am with thee and will conſtrain them to believe.</p>
               <p n="12">12 <hi>And I ſaid to him,</hi> Lord theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands are great and excellent, and they are able to make glad the heart of that man, who ſhall be able to keep theſe Commands. But I know not Lord whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe Commandments can be kept by man; He <hi>ſaith to me,</hi> theſe commands thou ſhalt eaſily keep, and they ſhall not be hard.</p>
               <p n="13">13 But notwithſtanding if thou ſhalt affirm in thine heart, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be kept by man, thou ſhalt not keep them. <hi>But now I ſay unto thee,</hi> if thou ſhalt not keep theſe Commandments and ſhalt omit them, thou ſhalt not be ſaved, nor thy ſons, nor thine houſe, becauſe thy ſelf haſt judged that theſe Commands
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:33010:40"/>
cannot be kept by man.</p>
               <p n="14">14 Theſe things he ſpoke to me vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently angry, ſo that he terrified me greatly, for he had changed his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, ſo that man could not be able to ſuſtain his wrath; And when he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held me all diſturbed, and confounded, he began to ſpeak more moderately and chearfully, ſaying,</p>
               <p n="15">15 O Fooliſh and unſenſible, Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and ignorant of the Majeſty of God, how great &amp; how admirable is it, who hath Created the world for man, and ſubjected every Creature to man, and hath given him ALL POWER THAT HE MAY HAVE DOMINION OVER THESE COMMAND<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENTS, he can have Dominion quoth he over all theſe Commands WHO HATH THE LORD IN HIS HEART, but they who have the Lord in their lips, and their heart is benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, theſe are far from the Lord, to them theſe Commands are hard and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult.</p>
               <p n="16">16 Therefore propoſe unto your ſelves ye that are empty, and light in the faith, TO HAVE THE LORD YOUR GOD IN THE HEART:
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:33010:41"/>
And ye ſhall underſtand that nothing is more eaſie then theſe Commands, nor more ſweet, nor more gentle, nor more holy, and convert you to the Lord God, and forſake the Devil and his pleaſures, becauſe they are evil and bitter, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean, and fear ye not the devil, becauſe in you he hath no power, for I am with you, the MESSENGER OF RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PENTANCE who rule over him, but the Devil cauſeth fear, but the fear of him is vain; Therefore do not ye fear him, and he ſhall fly from you.</p>
               <p n="17">17 <hi>And I ſaid to him,</hi> Lord hear me, ſpeaking a few words to thee; Speak quoth he; Man indeed deſireth to keep the Commands of God, and there is none who doth not ask from the Lord that he may keep his Commandments, but the Devil is hard, and his power hath domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over the ſervants of God.</p>
               <p n="18">18 <hi>And he ſaid,</hi> he cannot quoth he have power over Gods ſevants, who from their whole hearts believe on the Lord; But the Devil can ſtrive, but overcome he cannot, for if ye reſiſt him he ſhall fly from you confounded, for whoſoever are not full of faith, they fear the Devil, as if having power; for the Devil tempteth
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:33010:41"/>
the ſervants of God, and if he ſhall find them empty, he deſtroyes them.</p>
               <p n="19">19 For even as a man when he hath filled veſſells with good wine, and among theſe veſſels hath put a few half-full, and cometh that he may try and taſte the veſſells, he tryes not the full ones, for he knows that they are good, but the half-ful he taſteth leaſt they have become ſower: for the half-full veſſells grow ſoon ſower and looſe the ſavour of Wine.</p>
               <p n="20">20 So alſo the Devil cometh to men the ſervants of God that he may tempt them, but whoſoever are full in the faith, they reſiſt him ſtrongly, and he departeth from them, becauſe he hath not a place of entering in; Then goeth he to them who are not full in the faith, and becauſe he hath a place, thereat he entereth into them, &amp; whatſoever things he will he doth with them, and they become his ſervants.</p>
               <p n="21">21 But I THE MESSENGER OF REPENTANCE ſay unto you, fear ye not the Devil, for I am ſent that with you I may be; Whoſoever from your whole hearts ſhall act repentance, that I may confirm you in the faith; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve ye therefore who becauſe of your ſins have forgot God, and who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:33010:42"/>
your ſafety, with your ſins DO BURTHEN YOUR LIFE, That if ye ſhall be converted to the Lord from your whole Hearts, and ſhall obey him according to his will, he ſhall give remedy to your former ſins, and ye ſhall have power of ruling over ALL the works of the Devil.</p>
               <p n="22">22 But his threats fear ye not at all, for they are without power, as the nerves of a dead man; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hear me and fear the Lord Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent, who can ſave you and deſtroy you, and keep ye his commands that ye may live to God.</p>
               <p n="23">23 And I ſaid to him, Lord even now I am confirmed in all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the Lord, as long as thou art with me, and I know that thou wilt break in pieces all the power of the devil. But alſo we ſhall overcome him if we can (the Lord confirming) keep theſe Commands which thou haſt injoyned. Thou ſhalt keep them quoth he, if thou ſhalt purifie thine heart to the Lord; But alſo all theſe ſhall keep them who ſhall purifie their hearts from the vain deſires of this World, and ſhall LIVE TO GOD.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End of the ſecond Book.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="book">
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:33010:42"/>
            <head>The Thirk Bood of <hi>Hermas</hi> the Diſciple of Paul which is Intituled of <hi>SIMILITUDES.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="similitude">
               <head>SIMIL. I.</head>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>ANd he ſaid to me,</hi> know ye the Servants of the Lord to be detained in Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage? For your City is far from this City; If therefore ye know your City in which ye are about to dwell, why do ye here buy fields, and prepare ſumptuous things and buildings, and ſuperfluous habitations? For he who getteth theſe things in this City, doth not bethink to return into his own CITY.</p>
               <p n="2">2 O fooliſh, O dubious and wretched man! Who doſt not underſtand all theſe to be ſtrange, and under the power of another, for the Lord of this City ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth unto thee, either make uſe of my Laws, or depart out of my City.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Thou, therefore what wilt thou do,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:33010:43"/>
haſt a Law in thine own City? What? willſt thou be able for thy fields, or for any of thy furnitures, to deny thy LAW, which if thou ſhalt deny, and wouldeſt return into thy City, thou ſhalt not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, but ſhalt be excluded thence.</p>
               <p n="4">4 See Therefore, that as one living a far off, thou getteſt nothing more for thy ſelf, then may be neceſſary and ſufficient for thee; And be thou prepared leaſt when the Lord of this City would expell thee, thou contradict his Law, and thou mayſt go into thine own City, and mayſt uſe thy Law without injury, Chearfull.</p>
               <p n="5">5 See ye therefore who ſerve God, AND HAVE HIM IN YOUR HEARTS, work ye the works of God, mindfull of his Commands and Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes which he promiſed, and believe him that he will perform [them] to you, if ye ſhall keep his Commands.</p>
               <p n="6">6 For the fields therefore which ye would buy, redeem the ſouls out of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, even as every one is able, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve the Widows, judge for the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes, and in works of this ſort ſpend your riches and wealths; For unto this hath the Lord inriched you, that ye may fulfill ſuch like Miniſtries; Much
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:33010:43"/>
better is it to do theſe things, then to buy fields and houſes, becauſe all [theſe] things ſhall periſh in this world.</p>
               <p n="7">7 But what things thou ſhalt do for the Name of God, thou ſhalt find in thy City, and ſhalt have joy without heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and fear; Therefore the Riches of the Nations do not ye deſire, for they are pernitious to the Servants of God, but of your own which ye have, do theſe things by which ye may attain unto joy; And do not ye adulterate, nor touch ye the Wife of another, nor covet her, Covet after thine own work, and thou ſhalt be ſaved.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="similitude">
               <head>SIMIL. II.</head>
               <p n="1">1 WHen I walked into the field, and conſidered the ELM and the VINE, and thought within me of their fruits; An Angell appeared to me, and ſaid to me, What doſt thou think within thee? <hi>I ſaid to him,</hi> I rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Lord of this Vine and Elm, becauſe the fruits of them are comly.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>And he ſaid to me,</hi> Theſe two Trees are placed for an example to the Servants
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:33010:44"/>
of God. <hi>And I ſaid to him,</hi> I would know Lord, the exemple of them which thou ſpeakeſt of; Hear quoth he, Seeſt thou this Vine and this Elm? I ſee them quoth I, Lord; This Vine ſaith he, is fruitfull, But the Elm is a Tree without fruit, but this Vine unleſſe it ſhould be wrapped a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ELM, and ſhould reſt upon it, it cannot make much fruit.</p>
               <p n="3">3 For lying in the earth, it yields bad fruits, becauſe it hangeth not upon the Elm, but if the Vine ſhould be hanged up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Elm, it giveth fruit both for it ſelf and for the Elm; See therefore that the Elm yields no leſs fruit then the Vine, but rather more.</p>
               <p n="4">4 How, quoth I Lord, more then the Vine? Being hanged ſaith he on the Elm it yieldeth much, and good fruit; But lying on the earth, it yieldeth little and bad fruit; Therefore this Similitude is put to the ſervants of God; To the poor and to the rich, I anſwered, ſaying Lord demonſtrate it to me.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Hear, quoth he, the RICH hath rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, but from the Lord he is poor for he is diſtracted about his riches and hath ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little prayer to the Lord, and what he hath he hath it ſluggiſh, and not having
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:33010:44"/>
power, when therefore the rich affords the POOR what things are needfull for him; The poor prayeth to the Lord for the Rich, and God gives to the Rich all good things, becauſe the poor is rich in prayer, and his prayer hath great pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er with the Lord.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Then therefore the rich affordeth all things to the poor, becauſe he percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth him to be heard by the Lord, and more willingly without dubitation he gives him all things, and takes care leaſt any thing be wanting to him; The poor giveth thanks to God for the rich, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do a work before the Lord.</p>
               <p n="7">7 With men therefore the Elm is not thought to yield fruit, and they know not, neither underſtand that if fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip ſhall be adjoyned to the Vine, alſo the Vine gives double fruit, both for it ſelf and for the Elm: So alſo the poor praying for the rich to the Lord are heard, and their riches are augmented, becauſe they afford to the poor of their riches.</p>
               <p n="8">8 They are therefore both conſorts of their good works; Therefore whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall do theſe things, ſhall not be deſerted by the Lord, and he ſhall be
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:33010:45"/>
written in THE BOOK OF LIFE; Therefore happy they that poſſeſſe, and perceive themſelves to be inriched, for they who ſhall perceive this, ſhall be able to Miniſter ſomething.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="similitude">
               <head>SIMIL. III.</head>
               <p n="1">1 HE ſhewed me many trees with leaves caſt off, which to me ſeemed as if withered, for they were all alike; <hi>And he ſaid to me,</hi> ſeeſt thou theſe trees? I ſee them quoth I, like to wither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ones; he anſwering ſaid to me, theſe trees are for a ſimilitude of them who ſtay in this world.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>I anſwered, ſaying,</hi> why are they like unto withered ones? Becauſe quoth he neither the juſt nor the unjuſt are known, but are alike in this world; For this world is to the juſt the WINTER, who are not known dwelling with ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Even as in Winter all trees having caſt their leaves are like unto dry ones, nor can it be known which are dry or which green; So alſo in this World nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the juſt nor the unjuſt are known, but they are alike all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="similitude">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:33010:45"/>
               <head>SIMIL. IV.</head>
               <p n="1">1 HE ſhewd me again many trees, of which ſome ſent forth leaves, others were withered; And he ſaid to me, ſeeſt thou not theſe trees? <hi>I anſwered,</hi> I ſee Lord, ſome withered, others bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing leaves; Theſe trees quoth he that are green, are the juſt which are about to dwell in the WORLD TO COME, for that world to come is the SUMMER to the juſt, but to the ſinners WIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Therefore when the tender mercy of the Lord ſhall ſhine forth, then ſhall they be declared who ſerve God, and they ſhall all be perſpicuous; For as in the Summer the fruit of the Tree of what ſort ſoever is declared, and is manifeſt; So alſo the deed of the juſt ſhall be declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſhall be manifeſt; And being alſo chearfull and rejoycing, they ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored in that world.</p>
               <p n="3">3 For the other Nations, to wit the ſinners, even as the Trees which thou dideſt ſee withered, ſuch are found dry and without fruit in that world, and as
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:33010:46"/>
dry ſticks, ſhall be burned, and ſhall become manifeſt, becauſe they have done wickedly in all the time of their life; And therefore they ſhall be burnt up, becauſe they have ſinned, and of their ſins have not done repentance. But alſo the reſt of the Nations ſhall be burnt, becauſe they have not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged God their Creator.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Do thou therefore good fruit, that in the Summer thy fruit may be known; And ABSTAIN THEE FROM MANY IMPLOY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENTS, and thou ſhalt omit no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, for whoſoever do many buſineſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes omit many things, becauſe they are ſtraitned about their imployments, and ſerve not to God.</p>
               <p n="5">5 For how can a man who ſerveth not to God, ask any thing from God and obtain it? For they that ſerve God, do ask and obtain their deſires; And if any one meddle with one buſineſſe, he ſhall be able to ſerve to God, becauſe his mind is not alienated from the Lord, but in a pure mind he ſerves to God; Therefore if thou ſhalt do this, thou canſt have fruit in the World to come; But alſo all
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:33010:46"/>
who ſhall do theſe things, ſhall bear fruit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="similitude">
               <head>SIMIL. V.</head>
               <p n="1">1 WHileſt I faſted and ſat on a certain Mountain, and gave thanks unto God for all that he had done with me; I ſee that SHEEP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HERD ſitting next me, and ſaying to me, Why haſt thou come hither ſo early in the morning? <hi>I anſwered,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Lord I have a STATION, what is the Station quoth he? <hi>And I ſaid,</hi> a FAST; <hi>and he ſaid,</hi> what is that faſt? As I was wont, quoth I, ſo faſt I.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Ye know not quoth he, [how] to faſt to God, neither is this a faſt which ye faſt, nothing profiting unto God; Why ſay I, doſt thou ſo ſay Lord? For I ſay, this not to be a faſt which ye think your ſelves to faſt; But I will teach thee what is a compleat faſt, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Hear quoth he, The Lord doth not deſire ſuch a ſuperfluous faſt, for in ſo faſting thou performeſt nothing
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:33010:47"/>
to righteouſneſs; For the true faſt is ſuch a faſt.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Thou muſt do nothing in thy life wickedly, but with a pure mind ſerve to God, keeping his Commands and going in his precepts, nor ſhalt thou admit an hurtfull deſire in thy mind, but believe the Lord; Theſe if thou ſhalt do, and ſhalt have his fear, and ſhalt abſtain from every evil buſineſs, thou being about to live to God; Theſe if thou ſhalt do, thou ſhalt accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh a great faſt, and acceptable to the Lord.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Hear the ſimilitude which I am about to tell thee, pertaining to a faſt. A certain man having ground and many ſervants, in a certain place of his ground he planted a Vineyard to his Succeſſors: After that going a far journey, he chuſed out the moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſervant whom he had, and apro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve'd to him, and to him he aſſigned the Vineyard, Commanding that to the Vines he ſhould joyn props, which if he ſhould do and ſhould finiſh his Command, he promiſed that he would give to the ſame man his Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:33010:47"/>6 Neither commanded he any other thing beſides to him, which he ſhould do in it, and ſo he went a far journey; but after that ſervant had taken care, he did whatſoever his Lord in joyned, and when he had propped that vineyard, and had taken heed, that it was filled with weeds, he began ſo to think with himſelf.</p>
               <p n="7">7 I have finiſhed what my Lord had commanded me, I will now dig this vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, and it ſhall be more beautiful when it ſhall be digged, and the weeds being extracted it ſhall yeild greater fruit, and ſhall not be choakt by weeds.</p>
               <p n="8">8 Having gone after that he digged it, and all the weeds which were in it he drew out, and ſo the vineyard became moſt beautiful, and ſprightly, not choakt by weeds. But after a certain time his Lord cometh, and he went into his vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, which when he had ſeen decently propped, and digged about, and the weeds extracted from it, and the vines to be joyous; for this deed he took joy of his Servant.</p>
               <p n="9">9 Having therefore adjoyned his Son whom he eſteemed his heir, and moſt dear, and his friends whom he aſſembled in the Council, he declares theſe things that he <pb n="94" facs="tcp:33010:48"/>
had charged his Servant with to be done, what things he had done beſides, but they forthwith gratulated that Servant, that he had acquired ſo full a teſtimony of his Lord.</p>
               <p n="10">10 After that he ſaith to them, I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed promiſed to this Servant his liberty if he ſhould keep my command which I had given, and he hath kept it, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides hath added a good work on the vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard which hath exceedingly pleaſed me; for this work therefore that he hath done I will make him co-heir with my Son, becauſe when he had perceived what was good, he omitted not but did it.</p>
               <p n="11">11 This counſel of the Lord both his Son and his Friends approved of, to wit, that this Servant ſhould be made co-heir with the Son; after that not many dayes, the Maſter of the Family having called together his Friends, ſent of his ſupper to that Servant many viands.</p>
               <p n="12">12 Which when he had got, he took of them what was ſufficient to him, but the reſt be diſtributed to his fellow-ſervants, which being got they became joyful, and began to wiſh to him that he ſhould obtein greater favour with the Lord, for theſe things which he had done to them.</p>
               <p n="13">
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:33010:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>13 All theſe when his Lord had heard, he took again exceeding great joy, and having called again his friends, and his Son, he declares to them the deed of his Servant of his victuals which he had ſent to him; Therefore they ſo much the more aſſented to the Maſter of the Family, that that ſervant ought to be made co-heir with his Son.</p>
               <p n="14">14 I ſay to him, Lord, theſe ſimilitudes I know not, nor can underſtand, unleſſe thou expound them unto me; I will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound all things to thee, <hi>quoth he,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I ſhall ſpeak with thee, or ſhall ſhew thee, keep the commands of the Lord, and thou ſhalt be approved, and ſhalt be wrote in the number of them that keep his commands.</p>
               <p n="15">15 But beſides what the Lord hath commanded, if thou ſhalt adde ſomething of good, thou ſhalt acquire greater dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to thy ſelf, and ſhalt be more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable with the Lord then thou waſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to be; Therefore if thou ſhalt keep the commands of the Lord, and ſhalt alſo adde unto them theſe <hi>STATIONS,</hi> thou ſhalt rejoyce, eſpecially if accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my injunction thou ſhalt keep them.</p>
               <p n="16">
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:33010:49"/>16 <hi>I ſay to him,</hi> whatever thou ſhalt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn me Lord, I will keep, for I know thee to be about to be with me; <hi>I will quoth he,</hi> be with thee who haſt ſuch a purpoſe. But alſo I will be with all, whoſoever have the ſame purpoſe This FAST, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> the commands of the Lord being kept, is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding good.</p>
               <p n="17">17 So therefore thou ſhalt keep it; firſt of all, beware from every wicked and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy word, and from every noxious deſire, and purifie thy ſenſe from all the vanity of this world, if thou ſhalt keep theſe things this ſhall be a juſt faſt.</p>
               <p n="18">18 Therefore ſo thou ſhalt do, the things above-written being finiſhed, in that day wherein thou ſhalt faſt, thou ſhalt taſte nothing at all, except bread and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and compute the quantity of food, which the reſt of the dayes thou wouldſt eat, the coſt of that day which thou wouldſt have made, thou ſhalt lay up, and ſhalt give it to the widow and pupil, or to the needy, and ſo ſhalt thou conſummate the humility of thy ſoul, that he who ſhall get of it, ſhall fill his ſoul, and for thee his prayer ſhall go to the Lord God.</p>
               <p n="19">19 So therefore, if thou ſhalt accompliſh
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:33010:49"/>
thy faſt even as I enjoyn thee, thy ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice ſhall be accepted by the Lord, and this thy faſt ſhall be written. This ſtation ſo acted is good, chearful, and accepted by the Lord. Theſe things if thou ſhal keep with thy Children, and thy whole houſe, having kept them thou ſhalt be happy; and whoſoever ſhall keep theſe things heard, they ſhall be happy, and whatſoever they ſhall ask from the Lord they ſhall obtein it.</p>
               <p n="20">20 And I prayed him that to me he would explain this ſimilitude of the ground, and the Lord, and the vineyard, and of the Servant who had propped the vineyard, and the herbs which were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted from the vineyard, and of the Son, and of the friends which he called into Council; for I underſtood that to be a ſimilitude.</p>
               <p n="21">21 <hi>He ſaith to me,</hi> thou art very bold to ask, for thou oughteſt to ask nothing; for if it ſhall be fit to be demonſtrated, it ſhall be demonſtrated to thee; <hi>I ſay to him,</hi> Lord, what things ſoever thou ſhalt ſhew me, and ſhalt not declare them, in vain ſhall I ſee them, if I ſhall not underſtand what they are, and if thou ſhalt propoſe any ſimilitudes, and ſhalt not expound
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:33010:50"/>
them, in vain ſhall I hear them.</p>
               <p n="22">22 He anſwered me again, ſaying, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is a Servant of God, and HATH THE LORD IN HIS INWARD PARTS, he asketh from him an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellect, and obteineth it, and every ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude he unfoldeth, and underſtands the words of the Lord, which need inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but whoſo are ſluggiſh and ſlow to pray, they doubt to ask of the Lord, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he is a Lord of ſuch profound good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that he affords all things without intermiſſion to the askers from him.</p>
               <p n="23">23 Thou therefore who art confirmed by his MESSENGER, and haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſuch a potent prayer, ſeeing thou art not ſluggiſh, why now doſt thou not ask an Intellect from the Lord, and get it; <hi>I ſay to him,</hi> while I may have thee preſent, it is neceſſary that from thee I ask and require, for thou ſheweſt me all things, and ſpeakeſt when thou art pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
               <p n="24">24 For if without thee I ſhould ſee theſe things, or hear them, then I ſhould ask the Lord that he would ſhew them to me; <hi>And he anſwered,</hi> I had ſaid to thee a little before, thee to be cunning and bold, who askeſt the ſolutions of ſimilitudes; but
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:33010:50"/>
becauſe thou art ſo importunate, I will reſolve thee this ſimilitude which thou deſireſt, that thou mayeſt make it known to all.</p>
               <p n="25">25 <hi>Hear now, quoth he,</hi> and perceive in thy mind, that GROUND ſignifieth the world, which is put for a ſimilitude; but the LORD of the ground is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated to be he who created all things and finiſht them, and gave them power; but the SON is the holy Spirit, but that SERVANT is the Son of God, but the VINEYARD is the people whom he keepeth, but the PROPS are the Meſſengers who are ſet over by the Lord to gather in his people.</p>
               <p n="26">26 But the WEEDS which were pluckt out from the Vineyard, are the treſpaſſes of the Servants of God; but the VICTUALS which he ſent of his Supper, are the Commandments which by his Son he hath given to his people, but theſe FRIENDS whom he called in Counſel are the holy Angels whom he at firſt created; but the abſence of that Maſter of the family, is the time which remains until his coming.</p>
               <p n="27">27 <hi>I ſay to him,</hi> Lord, magnificently and wonderfully, and honeſtly do all theſe
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:33010:51"/>
things carry themſelves; therefore can I be able to underſtand theſe Lord, <hi>quoth I?</hi> Indeed not any man beſides, although he be very prudent, ſhall be able to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand theſe; but even now Lord demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to me what I ask, ask what thou wilt, <hi>quoth he.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="28">28 Why, <hi>quoth I,</hi> is the Son of God in this ſimilitude put in a ſervile place? Hear, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> in a ſervile condition the Son of God is not put, but in great power and authority; <hi>And I ſaid,</hi> how ſay I Lord, I underſtand not, becauſe <hi>quoth he,</hi> to thoſe whom he hath delivered to his Son, hath his Son ſet over MESSENGERS to preſerve them all; but he hath labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed very much, and hath endured very much that he ſhould aboliſh their treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes</p>
               <p n="29">29 For no Vineyard can be digged without labour and grief; therefore the ſins of his people being blotted out, he himſelf hath ſhewed unto them the JOURNEYS OF LIFE, having given them the LAW which he had got from the Father; thou ſeeſt therefore him to be the Lord of the people, having got from his Father all power.</p>
               <p n="30">30 But why the Lord ſhould adde in
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:33010:51"/>
his counſel the ſon of his inheritance, and the good ANGELS? Becauſe the Meſſenger heareth THAT HOLY SPIRIT, WHICH WAS INFU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SED FIRST OF ALL things IN THE BODY IN WHICH GOD SHOULD DWELL, for the IN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TELLECT hath placed it in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as it ſeemed to him.</p>
               <p n="31">31 Therefore this body into which the holy ſpirit is brought in, hath obeyed that ſpirit rightly, walking in modeſty, and chaſtly, nor hath at all defiled that ſpirit, Therefore when that body had obeyed at every time the holy ſpirit rightly and chaſtly, and had laboured with it, nor had fainted at any time, that wearied bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy converſed ſervilely, but ſtrongly with the holy ſpirit approved to God it was received.</p>
               <p n="32">32 Therefore its potent courſe of this ſort pleaſed God, becauſe it had not been Maculated in the earth, POSSES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SING IN IT SELF THE HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LY SPIRIT IN COUNSEL. Therefore he called his Son and the good Meſſengers, to wit, that alſo to this body which hath ſerved the holy Spirit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out complaint, ſome place of remaining
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:33010:52"/>
ſhould be given, leaſt it ſhould ſeem to have loſt the reward of its ſervitude.</p>
               <p n="33">33 For every Body found pure and without ſpot ſhall receive a reward, IN WHICH TO DWEL IN, THE HOLY SPIRIT WAS CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STITUTE. Thou haſt alſo the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of this ſimilitude. I have percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>quoth I,</hi> thy will, Lord, having heard this expoſition. Hear further <hi>ſaith he,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="34">34 Keep this thy body pure and clean, that THAT SPIRIT WHICH INHABITETH IN IT may bear teſtimony to it, and may be judged to have been with thee. And alſo ſee thou, leaſt at any time thou be perſwaded to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy this body, &amp; do abuſe it in any luſt.</p>
               <p n="35">35 For if thou ſhalt defile thy body, thou ſhalt defile alſo at the ſame time the HOLY SPIRIT alſo, and if thou ſhalt maculate thy body thou ſhalt not live. <hi>And I ſaid,</hi> What if through any ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance that hath been committed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that theſe words were heard? by what means attaineth he unto ſafety who hath defiled his body?</p>
               <p n="36">36 To the former things, <hi>quoth he,</hi> which they have committed througe ignorance, only God can afford a remedy, for his is
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:33010:52"/>
all power. But now keep thy ſelf, &amp; ſeeing the Lord is omnipotent and merciful, he ſhall grant remedy to thy former treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes if for the future thou defile not thy BODY and SPIRIT, for they are both Comſorts, and ANY OF THE TWO IS NOT TAINTED WITH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OUT THE OTHER. Therefore keep both of them clean, and thou ſhalt LIVE TO GOD.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="similitude">
               <head>SIMIL. VI.</head>
               <p n="1">1 WHile I ſat at home, and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the Lord for all that I had ſeen, and thought of his Commands, them to be exceeding good, and great and honeſt and gladſom, and which can bring the ſafety of men, <hi>within my ſelfe theſe things I ſaid,</hi> Happy ſhall <hi>I</hi> be if <hi>I</hi> ſhall walk in theſe Commands, and whoſoever ſhall walk in theſe, ſhall <hi>LIVE TO GOD.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 Theſe things whileſt I was ſpeaking with my ſelf, I ſee him whom alſo before, ſitting beſide me, <hi>and ſaying theſe things to me,</hi> Why doubteſt thou of my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands which <hi>I</hi> have in joyned thee? they
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:33010:53"/>
are good, thou ſhalt doubt nothing at all, but put on the Faith of the Lord, and thou ſhalt walk in them; for I in them will give thee ſtrength.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Theſe Commands are profitable to them who of their fore-done ſins are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to do repentance, if for the future they ſhall walk in them. Therefore who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever do repentance, Caſt off from you the naughtineſſe of this World, but put ye on all virtue and equity, and ye ſhall be able to keep theſe Commands, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hereafter ſin ye.</p>
               <p n="4">4 For if after this ye SIN NOT, very much of the former [ſins] ſhall ye cut off; in my Commandments walk ye and ye ſhall live to God. <hi>Theſe things by we are ſpoken to you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 After he had ſpoke, theſe things with me, <hi>He ſaith to me,</hi> let us go into the field and I will ſhew thee the SHEEP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HERDS of the ſheep. <hi>Let us go, quoth I Lord,</hi> And we came into a certain field, and there he ſhewed me a youthful ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd clothed in an upper ſcarlet coat, of the colour of his cloaths.</p>
               <p n="6">6 But he fed plentious ſheep, and theſe ſheep were as it were in pleaſures, and many delights, and they exulted <pb n="105" facs="tcp:33010:53"/>
with Joy, and leaping did run hither and thither; And the ſheepherd himſelf ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly took delight of his flock, and the countenance of that ſheepherd was very chearful, running among the ſheep.</p>
               <p n="7">7 <hi>The Angel ſaith to me,</hi> But ſeeſt thou this ſheepherd? I ſee him, <hi>quoth I,</hi> Lord, <hi>And he ſaid to me,</hi> He is the Meſſenger of inticements, ſweetneſſe and pleaſure; he therefore corrupts the minds of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God, and turns them away from the TRUTH, delighting them with luſts, and they periſh, for they forget the Commands of the living God, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe in luxuries &amp; in vain delights, and they are corrupted by this evil MES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SENGER, ſome even until death, but others even until falling back.</p>
               <p n="8">8 <hi>I ſay unto him, Lord I underſtand</hi> not what is UNTO DEATH and what, unto falling back; Hear quoth he, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſheep thou ſaweſt very joyous and leaping are they who have for ever de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from God, and have given up themſelves to the deſires of this world, to them therefore there is not a returning by repentance to life, becauſe they have added certain things to their other tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, and have reviled the NAME
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:33010:54"/>
of the Lord with hainous words; This ſort of men are deſigned to death.</p>
               <p n="9">9 But what ſheep thou ſawſt not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulting, but feeding in one place; Theſe are they who have indeed delivered themſelves to delights and pleaſures, but have ſpoken nothing hainous againſt the Lord; Therefore theſe have fallen away from the Truth, and therefore they have as yet a hope reſerved of life in Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, for defection hath ſome hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation, but death ſhall be detain'd in perpetual deſtruction.</p>
               <p n="10">10 Again, we went forwards a little, and he ſhewed me a great Sheepherd, and having as it wer an agreſtick counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, cloathed with a white Goat skin, carrying a bag in his ſhoulder, and in his hand a rod knotty and exceeding hard, and a whip in his hand, but he had a cruell and fierce look, that he could terrifie any one ſuch was his aſpect.</p>
               <p n="11">11 He therefore did take from that young Sheepherd theſe ſheep which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed excerciſed delights, but did not leap; And he drove them into a certain ſteep place, and thorny, and filled with thiſtles, ſo much that from the thorns
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:33010:54"/>
and thiſtles they could not unfold them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; But being involved there they were fed [among] thorns and thiſtles.</p>
               <p n="12">12 And heavy vexations did they feel from his WORDS, for he toſſed them, neither alſo did he grant to them a place of ſtanding before a time; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for when <hi>I</hi> ſaw them to be ſo ſcourged, and to experience miſeries, I grieved for them becauſe they were greatly torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor was any reſt granted to them.</p>
               <p n="13">13 I ſay to the Sheepherd who was with me, who is this ſo implacable Sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd Lord, and ſo bitter, who by no means is moved with compaſſion towards theſe ſheep; This Sheepherd, quoth he, is indeed a meſſenger for the juſt, but ſet over to puniſhment; To him therefore are they delivered who have gone aſtray from God, and have ſerved the deſires and pleaſures of this world; Therefore he puniſheth them even as every one of them hath deſerved, with cruel and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious puniſhments.</p>
               <p n="14">14 I would know, <hi>quoth I,</hi> Lord theſe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious puniſhments of what ſort they are; Here <hi>ſaith he:</hi> the various pains, and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are theſe which men daily in their life undergo, for ſome ſuffer loſſes, others
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:33010:55"/>
poverty, others divers diſeaſes, ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy, others ſuffering injuries from unworthy men, and many other exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and diſcommodities; for very many by unconſtant counſel endeavour many things, nor doth any thing conduce to them, and they ſay themſelves not to have ſucceſſe in their doings, theſe things which they have wickedly acted, come into their minds, and do excuſe the Lord.</p>
               <p n="15">15 Therefore when they ſhall have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered every vexation, and every diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity, then they are delivered to me for good admonition, and they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in the Faith of the Lord, and throughout the reſt of the days of [their] life they ſerve to God in a pure mind; and when they ſhall begin to do repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of their iniquiries, then their works aſcend up in their INWARD PARTS, in which they have exerciſed themſelves wickedly.</p>
               <p n="16">16 And then they give to God the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, ſaying him to be a juſt Judge, and themſelves to have deſervedly ſuffered all things according to their deeds. But for the remainder, they ſerve God with a pure mind, and they have ſucceſſe in all their
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:33010:55"/>
imployments, receiving from the Lord whatſoever they required; and then they give thanks to the Lord that they are delivered to me, nor do now indure any cruelty.</p>
               <p n="17">17 <hi>I ſay to him,</hi> even now Lord demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to me; What inquireſt thou, <hi>quoth he, I ſaid to him,</hi> Whither for the ſame time ſhall they be vexed, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the Fear of God, how much they ſhall uſe the falſe ſweetneſs and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures? <hi>He ſaith to me,</hi> for the ſame time alſo they are vexed; <hi>And I ſaid to him,</hi> A ſmall [time] then are they vexed, but it behoved theſe who do ſo injoy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures that they forget the Lord, to ſuffer ſeven times as much of puniſhments.</p>
               <p n="18">18 <hi>He ſaith to me,</hi> thou art fooliſh, nor underſtandeſt the power of this puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>And I ſaid,</hi> for if I underſtood, Lord, I would not ask that thou ſhouldſt demonſtrate it to me; Hear, <hi>quoth he,</hi> how great is the force of both the ſweetneſſe and pleaſure. One hour of ſweetneſs ends in its own ſpace, but one hour of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment retains the force of thirty dayes.</p>
               <p n="19">19 Therefore whoſoever in one day receives the fallacious ſweetneſſe &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, &amp; in one day is vexed, the day of his
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:33010:56"/>
vexation ſhall have the force of a years ſpace. Therefore how many dayes any one ſhall receive pleaſure, by ſo many years is he vexed; Thou ſeeſt therefore, <hi>quoth he,</hi> the time of worldly ſweetneſſe and pleaſure to be ſmall, but of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and of torments, more.</p>
               <p n="20">20 <hi>I ſaid to him,</hi> Lord, becauſe I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not all theſe TIMES of ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, pleaſure, and pain, expound thou more clearly to me of theſe; <hi>He anſwered me, ſaying,</hi> Thy fooliſhneſſe inhereth in thee conſtantly, wilt thou not rather pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie thy mind and ſerve to God; ſee, leaſt perhaps the time being finiſhed, thou be found unwiſe.</p>
               <p n="21">21 Hear now even as thou wilt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thou mayſt more eaſily underſtand. He who one day ſhall commit himſelf to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and pleaſures, and ſhall do what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever his ſoul deſireth, he is filled with very much folly, neither underſtands he what he committeth, and the day ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding he forgets what he had done the day before, for ſweetneſſe and pleaſure have no remembrance, becauſe of the folly which is rooted in them.</p>
               <p n="22">22 But when one day there ſhall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to a man vexation and pain, he is
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:33010:56"/>
tormented the whole year, for great me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory doth puniſhment poſſeſſe; therefore the whole year grieving, he remembers, and then he remembreth that vain ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and pleaſure, and he perceives for that himſelf to ſuffer puniſhments.</p>
               <p n="23">23 Whoſoever therefore ſhall deliver themſelves to ſweetneſſe and pleaſure, ſo they are puniſhed; becauſe having LIFE they render themſelves obnoxious to death; <hi>I ſaid to him,</hi> What Lord are the hurtful pleaſures? To every man, <hi>quoth he,</hi> that is PLEASURE, whatſoever he doth willingly, for the angry man ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying his manners, receiveth his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and the Adulterer, and Drunkard, and Defamer, and Lyar, and Covetous, and Fraudulent, and who ever commits ought like to theſe, obeying his diſeaſe, he receives out of that thing pleaſure.</p>
               <p n="24">24 All theſe ſweets and pleaſures are noxious to the Servants of God, becauſe of theſe therefore are they vexed, and ſuffer puniſhments; There are alſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures bringing ſafety to men, for many doing the works of goodneſſe, take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, drawn with their ſweetneſſe.</p>
               <p n="25">25 Therefore this pleaſure is profitable to the Servants of God, and it gets life
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:33010:57"/>
to men of this ſort, but theſe evil ones which were ſpoken before, beget torments and pains; but whoſoever ſhall remain in them, nor of their treſpaſſes ſhall act Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, they will acquire to themſelves DEATH.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="similitude">
               <head>SIMIL. VII.</head>
               <p n="1">1 AFter a few dayes I ſee him in that field in which I had ſeen theſe Sheepherds before; <hi>And he ſaith to me,</hi> What enquireſt thou? I came, <hi>quoth I,</hi> to entreat thee, Lord, that thou command that Sheepherd ſet over to puniſhment, to go out of my houſe, becauſe he vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly afflicteth me; <hi>And anſwering,</hi> it is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, <hi>quoth he,</hi> that thou ſuffer diſcommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities and vexations, for ſo that good Meſſenger commanded concerning thee, becauſe he will try thee.</p>
               <p n="2">2 What ſo hainous ſin, <hi>quoth I,</hi> Lord, have I committed, that I ſhould be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to this Meſſenger? Attend, <hi>ſaith he:</hi> Thou haſt indeed very many ſins, but not ſo many that thou oughteſt to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to this Meſſenger, but many ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities and tranſgreſſions hath thy houſe
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:33010:57"/>
committed, and therefore that good Meſſenger ſtirred up with their deeds, hath commanded them a certain [ſpace] of time to experience vexation, that alſo they of their treſpaſſes may act Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and may waſh themſelves from all the luſt of this world; Therefore when they ſhall have done Repentance, and shall be purified, then that Meſſenger shall depart from thee, who is ſet over to puniſhment.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>I ſay to him,</hi> Lord, if they have ſo carried [themſelves] that they have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperated the good Meſſenger, what have I done? <hi>He anſwering ſaith,</hi> otherwiſe they cannot ſuffer torment, unleſſe thou who art the HEAD of the whole houſe doſt labour; for whatſoever thou ſhalt ſuffer, it muſt needs be that they alſo feel it, but as long as thou ſhalt be well eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they can experience no vexation.</p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>And I ſaid,</hi> but alſo behold now Lord they do Repentance with their whole hearts; And I know, <hi>quoth he,</hi> them to act Repentance with all their hearts; doſt thou therefore forth-with think <hi>ſaith he,</hi> their tranſgreſſions to be aboliſhed, who do Repentance?</p>
               <p n="5">5 Not forthwith immediately, but it
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:33010:58"/>
becomes him who doth Repentance, to afflict his ſoul, and make himſelf humble in mind, in every buſineſſe, and to ſuffer many and various vexations; and when he ſhall have ſuffered all things which ſhall be appointed him, then perhaps he who created him, and who formed all things, ſhall be moved towards him with his clemency, and ſhall give ſome remedy, and that, ſo if he ſhall ſee his heart, who doth Repentance to be pure from every moſt wicked work.</p>
               <p n="6">6 But for thee and for thine houſe it is expedient now to be vexed, and it is needful to undergo much vexation, even as the Meſſenger of the Lord enjoyned, who delivered thee unto me; but rather give thou thanks to the Lord, that fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowing the thing to come, he hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed thee worthy, to whom he ſhould foretell the tribulation to be at hand to thoſe that can be able to ſuſtein it.</p>
               <p n="7">7 <hi>I ſay to him,</hi> and be thou with me, Lord, and I ſhall eaſily ſuſtein all vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I <hi>quoth he,</hi> will be with thee, but alſo I will entreat that Meſſenger who is ſet over to puniſhment, that he may more lightly afflict thee, but alſo in a little time thou ſhalt undergo the adverſe things,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:33010:58"/>
and again in thy place ſhalt be reſtored; onely in the humility of mind perſevere thou.</p>
               <p n="8">8 Obey the Lord in a pure mind, and thy houſe, and thy ſons, and in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands walk thou, which I enjoyned thee, and thy repentance ſhall be able to be firm, and pure, and if theſe thou with thy houſe ſhalt keep, the diſcommodities ſhall depart from thee, but alſo from all whoſoever in theſe Commandments ſhall walk, every vexation ſhall depart.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="similitude">
               <head>SIMIL. VIII.</head>
               <p n="1">1 HE ſhewed me a willow covering the fields and mountains, under whoſe ſhadow all theſe came who were called in the NAME of the Lord; and beſides that willow ſtood the Meſſenger of the Lord exceeding illuſtrious and eminent, and did cut with a great hook from that willow, branches, and held forth to that people who was under the ſhaddow of that willow, ſmall, and as it were rods of a cubit long.</p>
               <p n="2">2 But after that they had all gotten them, he laid down the hook, and that
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:33010:59"/>
tree remained whole, even as before I had ſeen it, which thing I admired, and diſputed within me: That Sheepherd <hi>ſaith to me,</hi> ceaſe to wonder, that that whole tree, the branches being cut off ſhould remain whole, but expect thou now it ſhall be demonſtrated to thee what that Angell may ſignifie, which ſtretched forth the rods to the people.</p>
               <p n="3">3 And asked them from them again, and in what order every one had taken them, in the ſame alſo was he called to him, and reſtored the rods, which when he had got, he conſidered; for from ſome he received them withered and putrid, as if touched by the moth; and he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded theſe who had delivered this ſort of rods, to be ſeparate, and ſet by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; others offered them withered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but not touched by the Moth, and theſe he commanded to be ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Others offered half-withered rods, and theſe alſo were ſet by themſelves. But ſome gave their rods half withered, and having rents, and theſe were ſet aſide; others brought their rods, of whom the half part was withered, but the [other] half green, and theſe were ſet aſide;
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:33010:59"/>
others brought their rods of whom two parts were green, but the third withered, and theſe were ſet aſide.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Others brought their rods of whom two parts were withered, but the third green, and theſe were ſet aſide; Some of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered their rods a little withered (for a very little was withered in their rods, that is the very top) but they had rents, and theſe were ſet aſide; but in the rods of others there was a little green, but the reſt withered, and theſe were ſet aſide.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Others came bringing their rods as they had got them, green, and the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of the people brought rods of this ſort, and of theſe this Meſſenger took great joy, and theſe were ſet aſide; others brought their rods green, and having bloſſoms, and theſe were ſet aſide, and theſe alſo that Meſſenger received with great joy.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Others brought their rods green, out of which their bloſſoms budded forth, wch bloſſoms bare certain fruits; they that brought this ſort of rods were exceeding chearful of countenance, but alſo the Meſſenger himſelf indeed took great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of them, no leſſe that Sheepherd for the ſame cauſe took pleaſure.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:33010:60"/>8 Then the Meſſenger of the Lord commanded Crowns to be brought, but there were brought Crowns as if made of Palms, and the Meſſenger crowned theſe men in whoſe rods he had found bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoms and fruit, and commanded them to go into the TOWER.</p>
               <p n="9">9 But alſo theſe men he ſent into the Tower, in whoſe rods without fruit he had found bloſſoms, having given them [his] SEAL, for they had the ſame veſture, that is white as ſnow, with which he commanded them to go into the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; no leſs alſo theſe who had reſtored their rods, even as they had got them green, having given them a white veſture, and ſo he ſent them away to go into the Tower.</p>
               <p n="10">10 Theſe things being finiſhed he ſaith to that Sheepherd, I go, but ſend thou theſe within the walls in that place where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in every one hath merited to dwell; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving firſt conſidered their rods diligently, notwithſtanding leaſt any deceive thee, conſider thou, but alſo if any one ſhall get by, <hi>quoth he,</hi> I will try them upon the ALTAR.</p>
               <p n="11">11 Theſe things being ſaid to the Sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, he departed, after he had departed <pb n="119" facs="tcp:33010:60"/>
the Sheepherd ſaith to me, Let us take the rods from all, and let us plant them, if they can flouriſh again. <hi>I ſay to him,</hi> Lord, theſe that are withered rods, how can they re-flouriſh? <hi>He ſaith to me,</hi> that tree is a WILLOW, and it alwayes loves Life; Therefore if theſe rods ſhall be planted, and ſhould receive a little of moiſture, very many of them will re-flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh; for I will try, and will pour under them water, and if any of them can live I will gratulate it, but if not, ſurely I ſhall not ſeem to have been negligent.</p>
               <p n="12">12 After that he commanded me to call them, and as every one of them ſtood they came in their own order, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered their rods, whom having gotten, he planted every one of them in their orders, and after he had planted them he poured much water upon them, ſo that they were covered by the water, nor ſtood out of it.</p>
               <p n="13">13 After that when he had watered them, <hi>he ſaith to me,</hi> let us go, and after a few dayes let us return, let us viſit them, for he who created this Tree WOULD HAVE ALL THESE TO LIVE who have taken thereof rods; but I hope ſeeing theſe rods are poured upon with
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:33010:61"/>
water, many [of them] are about to live, having taken moiſture.</p>
               <p n="14">14 <hi>I ſay to him,</hi> this Tree, Lord, demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to me what it is, for I am greatly moved, that ſo many branches being cut off, it ſeems to be whole, nor doth any thing of it ſeem to be leſſe, in which I am greatly amazed.</p>
               <p n="15">15 Hear, <hi>quoth he,</hi> this great Tree which covereth the fields and the mountains, and the whole earth, is the LAW of God GIVEN UNTO THE WHOLE WORLD; But by this law the SON of God is preached in all the ends of the globe of the Earth, but the PEOPLE ſtanding beneath its ſhaddow, are theſe who have heard his Preachings and have BELIEVED.</p>
               <p n="16">16 But that MESSENGER mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent and good, is MICHAEL, who of this people hath power, and governs them, for he INSERTETH THE LAW IN THEIR HEART, who have believed; Therefore he viſiteth them to whom he hath given the law, if they have kept it; but he ſeeth the rod of every one, and of them many faulty, for theſe RODS of the Lord are the LAW.</p>
               <p n="17">
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:33010:61"/>17 But after that he knows all thoſe who have not kept the Law, knowing the ſeat of every one of them; I <hi>ſay unto him,</hi> Why, <hi>quoth</hi> I, Lord, ſent he ſome into the Tower, others left here to thee? theſe <hi>quoth he,</hi> whoſoever have tranſgreſſed the law which from him they got, are left in my power, that of their treſpaſſes they may do Repentance, but who have ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the law, and have kept it, are under his power.</p>
               <p n="18">18 Who are they therefore Lord, <hi>quoth</hi> I, going in CROWNED into the Tower? <hi>He ſaith to me,</hi> Whoſoever ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving wreſtled with the devil have OVER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COME HIM, theſe are crowned. But they are theſe, who that they might keep the Law, have ſuffered iniquous things; But theſe who delivered their GREEN rods, and having BLOSSOMS with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fruit, have indeed for the ſame law ſuſtained vexation, but have not ſuffered Death, but neither have they denied the Holy Law.</p>
               <p n="19">19 But theſe who delivered them GREEN as they GOT them, are the MODEST and Juſt, and they have li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in an exceeding PURE MIND, and have kept the Commands of God;
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:33010:62"/>
But the reſt thou ſhalt know when I ſhall conſider theſe rods which I have planted and watered.</p>
               <p n="20">20 But after a few dayes we returned, and in that ſame place ſat that Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Meſſenger, but I ſtood by him; <hi>Then he ſaith to me,</hi> Gird thee about with a gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, and miniſter unto me. I <hi>girded me about with a clean girdle which was made of ſack-cloth, but as ſoon as he ſaw me girded, and prepared to miniſter unto him, he ſaith,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="21">21 C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll theſe men whoſe rods are plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, every one in his own order, as they gave them, and he led me into the field, and I called them all, who alſo all of them ſtood in their own orders. <hi>After that he ſaid to them,</hi> let every one pluck up his own rod, and bring it to me.</p>
               <p n="22">22 And firſt they delivered them who had withered and putrid ones, and whoſe rods were found putrid and withered, he commanded theſe to ſtand aſide. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that they gave, who had them wither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed indeed, but not putrid; ſome of theſe gave green rods, but ſome withered and putrid ones, as if touched by the moth; Theſe who had delivered them green he commanded to ſtand apart, but thoſe that delivered them arrid and putrid, he
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:33010:62"/>
commanded to ſtand with the firſt.</p>
               <p n="23">23 After that theſe gave who had had them half withered and having rents; many of theſe gave them green, nor ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving rents; but ſome green having bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoms, and in the bloſſoms fruit, even as thoſe who had gone into the Tower crowned. Others offered them withered and rotten: but ſome as they were half withered, and having rents he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded every one of theſe to ſtand apart, ſome every one in his own order, others apart.</p>
               <p n="24">24 After that they offered, who had their rods indeed green, but having rents. All theſe delivered them green, and ſtood in their own order; But this ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd took delight of them that all of them were poliſhed, and had put off their rents. After that they offered, who had the half green, and the half withered, but of ſome there were found all green, of others half withered, of others green and having bloſſoms, all theſe were ſent every one to his own order.</p>
               <p n="25">25 After that they who had two parts of the Rods green and the third wither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, many of theſe gave them green, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny half withered, but the reſt withered
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:33010:63"/>
but not putrid, all theſe were ſent every one into his own order; Afterward they gave who had had in their rods two parts withered, and the third green; many alſo of them offered half withered ones, but ſome withered and putrid, but others half withered and having rents, but few green; Therefore all theſe ſtood every one in his own order.</p>
               <p n="26">26 After that they gave who had had the third green, but the reſt withered; the rods of theſe for the greater part were found green, having little branches, and in theſe little branches fruit, and the reſt all green; Of theſe rods that ſheepherd exceedingly took delight, becauſe ſo he ſhould find them; and alſo they went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way into their orders</p>
               <p n="27">27 But after he had conſidered all their rods, <hi>he ſaith to me,</hi> I had ſaid to thee this tree to love LIFE; Thou ſeeſt that many have done repentance and have attained Salvation; <hi>I ſee quoth I,</hi> Lord. That thou mayſt know, <hi>quoth he,</hi> the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and clemency of the Lord to be great and honourable, who hath GI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEN [his] SPIRIT TO THOSE WHO WERE WORTHY to do Repentance.</p>
               <p n="28">
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:33010:63"/>28 <hi>And I ſaid,</hi> why therefore Lord have not all done Repentance? <hi>He ſaith to me,</hi> whoſe mindes the Lord had ſeen about to be pure, and they about to ſerve him from their whole hearts, to them he hath offered Repentance; but them whoſe deceit and wickedneſſe he hath beheld, and hath taken notice that they were about to return to him deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, he hath denied a regreſſe unto them to Repentance; leaſt again they ſhould curſe the LAW with theſe hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous words.</p>
               <p n="29">29 <q>I ſay to him, now Lord demonſtrate un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me what that place is to every one of them, who reſtored their rods, and their ſeats; that theſe things being heard and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, theſe who have not kept whole, but have broke in pieces the SEAL which they have got, having known their deeds, may act Repentance; and having got from thee a ſeal, may give the honour to the Lord, that he is moved with his clemency over them, and hath ſent thee that thou mayſt renew their ſpirits.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="30">30 <hi>Hear quoth he,</hi> theſe whoſe rods were found dry and putrid, and as if touched by the moth; theſe are the fugitives, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayers of the Church, who amongſt
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:33010:64"/>
their other iniquities, with hainous words, having reviled the Lord, have denied his NAME, which upon them was invoked; All theſe therefore are dead to God; and alſo thou ſeeſt none of them to have done Repentance, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they heard my Commandments, which thou haſt brought unto them, therefore from this ſort of men life is gone away.</p>
               <p n="31">31 Likewiſe theſe who delivered them withered and not putrid, were not far from them, for they were feigned, and brought in evil doctrines and perverted the ſervants of God, chiefly thoſe who had ſinned, not ſuffering them to return to repentance; but detaining them with fooliſh doctrines, theſe therefore have a regreſs unto hope, and alſo thou ſeeſt many to do repentance ſince thou haſt brought forth my commands to them, and as yet they will act Repentance; but whoſoever ſhall not have acted repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, they ſhall looſe both repentance, and their life.</p>
               <p n="32">32 But theſe who have done [Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance] at firſt, the wall hath begun to be their ſeat, even thoſe who have not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended into the Tower; thou ſeeſt
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:33010:64"/>
therefore <hi>quoth he,</hi> in the repentance of ſinners, life to be inherent; but of thoſe that do not repentance, death prepared.</p>
               <p n="33">33 But of thoſe who offered half wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered rods, and [who] had CLEFTS hear thou; whoſe rods were only half withered, theſe are the doubtful, for they were neither alive nor dead, but theſe who gave half withered ones, and having Clefts, are both the DOUBT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FULL, and the revilers, backbiting the abſent, and never among themſelves having peace; envying among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to theſe indeed is Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance propoſed, for thou ſeeſt of theſe ſome to repent; But whoſoever of them have ſwiftly done Repentance, theſe have a ſeat in the Tower; but they who have ſlowly done it, dwell in the Walls: But who have not done Repentance, but in their own deeds have continued, ſhall die with Death.</p>
               <p n="34">34 But they who delivered indeed green rods, but having clefts, were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies faithful and good; but having a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves a certain envy and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of principality and dignity, notwithſtanding all of this ſort are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe and fooliſh, who have among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:33010:65"/>
emulation concerning Principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, But yet theſe ſeeing they are other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe good, if having heard theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, they ſhall amend themſelves, and ſuddenly by (thy) perſwaſion ſhall do Repentance, in the Tower at length they ſhall begin to dwell, even alſo as theſe who have worthily done Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
               <p n="25">25 But if any of them again ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to diſſention, he ſhall be beaten back from the Tower, and ſhall looſe his LIFE, for their LIFE who keep the the Commands of the Lord, CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SISTETH IN COMMAND<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENTS, NOT IN PRINCI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PALITY, OR ANY DIGNI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TY, for by patience and humility of ſoul men attain life; but by ſedition and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the LAW, they acquire death to themſelves.</p>
               <p n="36">36 But they who in their rods had the half withered, and the half green; theſe are thoſe involved in negotiations, and not joyned to the Saints, and therefore alſo the half of them live, but the [o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther] half is dead; therefore many of theſe having heard the Commandments, have done Repentance, and have begun
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:33010:65"/>
to dwell in the Tower, but ſome of them have wholly fallen away; to theſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is not a place of repentance.</p>
               <p n="37">37 For by their negotiation, they have ſpoken hainous things againſt the Lord, and have denied him; Therefore becauſe of this wickedneſſe they have loſt LIFE. But many of theſe have put on a doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful mind: As yet alſo to them is there returning, who if ſuddenly they ſhall do repentance, in the Tower ſhall have a ſeat; but if more ſlowly they ſhall do it, they ſhall dwell in the walls; but if they ſhall not do it, they ſhall purchaſe Death to themſelves.</p>
               <p n="38">38 But theſe who had two parts of their rods green, and the third withered, by many wayes, being depraved, they have denied the Lord; Therefore of theſe, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have done repentance, and ſo have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to dwell in the Tower. And many have from God departed for ever; theſe therefore have wholly loſt life.</p>
               <p n="39">39 But ſome, having conceived a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bious mind, have ſtirred up diſſentions, to them as yet there is regreſſe, if ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly they do repentance, nor ſhall be delayed by their pleaſures; but if in their deeds they ſhall remain, they ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:33010:66"/>
death to themſelves.</p>
               <p n="40">40 But theſe that gave their rods, of whom two parts were withered, and the third green, were indeed faithful, but being inriched and filled with goods, have deſired to be more famous in foreign Nations, and have faln into great pride, and have begun to exſpect high things, and to deſert the Truth; neither have they been adjoyned to the juſt, they have lived with foreign Nations, and this life, ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more ſweet to them: Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, from God they have not departed, and they have perſevered in the faith, but the works of Faith they have not exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed.</p>
               <p n="41">41 Therefore many of them have done repentance, and their ſeats have begun to be in the Tower; but others living with foreign Nations, and puft up with their vanities, have faln away for ever from God, ſerving to the crimes and works of the Nations; therefore this ſort of men are numbred with foreign Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p n="42">42 Others of theſe have begun to have a doubtful mind, not hoping, themſelves, becauſe of their deeds, to be able to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſafety: others become doubtful, have
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:33010:66"/>
ſtired up diſſentions: Therefore to theſe and to them who becauſe of their deeds have begun to be doubtful, as yet there is returning; but this repentance ought to be ſwift, that their ſeat may be in the Tower: but to thoſe who do not repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, but continue in their pleaſures, Death is nigh.</p>
               <p n="43">43 But theſe who gave their rods green, except their tops which above were wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, and had clefts, have been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways good and faithful, and honeſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, but have a little tranſgreſſed for [their] vain pleaſures and mean cogitations, which they have had with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in themſelves; Therefore my words being heard, very many have done Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance ſwiftly, and have begun to dwell in the Tower; but certain of them have become doubtful, certain have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a doubtful mind, alſo to ſtir up diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſions: In theſe therefore alſo now is there hope of returning, becauſe they have been always good, but difficultly ſhall they be moved.</p>
               <p n="44">44 But they who ſtretched forth their rods withered, except their tops which alone were green, theſe indeed have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved God, but have been converſant
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:33010:67"/>
in iniquities, notwithſtanding have never departed from God, but always have willingly born the NAME of the Lord, and willingly in their Hoſpitalities have intertained the ſervants of God; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore having heard this, being returned without delay, they have done Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and have exerciſed all the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of vertue; but ſome of them have died the death, and others willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have ſuffered adverſe things, mindful of their deeds.</p>
               <p n="45">45 After he had finiſhed the explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of all the rods, <hi>he ſaith to me,</hi> Go and ſay unto all, that they act Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and they ſhall LIVE TO GOD, becauſe the Lord moved with his great clemency, hath ſent me that I ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare Repentance to all, alſo to thoſe who do not deſerve becauſe of their deeds to attain Salvation.</p>
               <p n="46">46 But patient is the Lord, and the invitation made by his SON he will keep; <hi>I ſay to him,</hi> I hope Lord it will be, that theſe things being heard, all will do Repentance; for I believe every one his deeds being acknowledged, and the fear of God being accepted, to be about to return to Repentance.</p>
               <p n="47">
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:33010:67"/>47 <hi>He ſaith to me,</hi> whoſoever with their whole heart ſhall do Repentance, and ſhall purifie themſelves from ALL the wickedneſſe which is aboveſaid, and as yet ſhall not add unto their treſpaſſes, every one [of them] ſhall receive from the Lord the remedy of their former ſins, if they ſhall nothing doubt of theſe Commandments, and they ſhall LIVE TO GOD.</p>
               <p n="48">48 But they who ſhall add, <hi>quoth he,</hi> unto their trangreſſions, and ſhall be converſant in the luſts of this World, ſhall damn themſelves unto Death; But walk thou in theſe Commands, and thou ſhalt live to God; and whoſoever ſhall walk in them, and ſhall rightly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe them, ſhall LIVE TO GOD; But after he had ſhewed me all theſe, <hi>he ſaith to me,</hi> the reſt after a few dayes I will ſhew unto thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="similitude">
               <head>SIMIL. IX.</head>
               <p n="1">1 AFter I had written the Mandat's and Similitudes of that Sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, THE MESSENGER OF REPENTANCE, he came unto
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:33010:68"/>
me, <hi>and ſaid unto me,</hi> I will ſhew to thee what things ſoever the SPIRIT hath ſhown thee, which in the figure of the CHURCH ſpake with thee, for the Spirit is the Son of God. And becauſe thou waſt more infirm in body, it was not declared to thee by the Meſſenger, before that thou art ſtrengthened by the Spirit, and augmented in forces, that thou mayſt be able to ſee the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
               <p n="2">2 For then well indeed, and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently the building of the Tower was ſhown to thee by the CHURCH, but thou ſaweſt all, as if ſhown by a Virgin.</p>
               <p>But now by a meſſenger thou art il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrated, indeed by the ſame Spirit; but thou muſt ſee all theſe diligently, for therefore into thy houſe am I ſent to dwell, by that venerable Meſſenger, that ſeeing thou ſeeſt all things potently, thou mayſt be nought afraid as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p n="3">3 And he led me up unto the aſcent of a Mountain of ARCADIA, and we ſat down together in the top thereof, and he ſhew'd me a great field, &amp; about it twelve Mountains, of one figure, and of another, of whom the FIRST was
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:33010:68"/>
black as ſoot; the ſecond bare without herbs; the third full of thorns and thiſtles; the fourth had herbs half wither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, of whom the upper part was green, but that next to the roots, withered, alſo ſome herbs, when the SUN had waxed hot, became withered.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The fift Mountain was moſt rough, but it had green herbs; the ſixt Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain was full of clefts, with ſome leſſer, but with ſome greater; but in theſe clefts there were herbs, not very ſprightly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but they ſeemed as if flagging; but the ſeventh Mountain had delectable herbs, and was all fertile, and every kind of Cattels, and Fowls of Heaven did take food thereof, and how much they did feed of it, by ſo much the more joyous did the herbs grow up.</p>
               <p n="5">5 The eighth Mountain was filled with Fountains, and out of theſe Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains was watered the whole kind of the Creature of God; The ninth Mountain had no water at all, and was all deſtitute, but alſo it nouriſhed deadly ſerpents, and pernitious to men; The tenth Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain contained high trees, and was all ſhady, and under its ſhade the cattel did ly reſting, and chewing the cud.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:33010:69"/>6 The eleventh Mountain was reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with moſt thick ſet trees, and theſe trees were ſeen laden with divers fruits, ſo that whoſoever ſhould ſee, would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to eat of the fruits of them; The TWELFTH Mountain was all white, and had a moſt delectable aſpect, and it ſelf afforded to it ſelf great comlineſs.</p>
               <p n="7">7 But in the middle of the field he ſhewed me a WHITE and Mighty ROCK, which had ariſen from out the field it ſelf: and that Rock was higher then theſe Mountains, and four cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nered, ſo that it could ſuſtain the whole World; but it ſeemed to me to be old, but it had a new gate, which ſeemed lately hewen out, and that gate had a more bright ſplendor then the Sun, ſo that I admired exceedingly its light.</p>
               <p n="8">8 But about that gate ſtood TWELVE VIRGINS, of whom four who held the corners of the Port, ſeemed to me to be more worthy, but alſo the reſt were worthy, but they ſtood in the four parts of the gate; moreover that was alſo for the grace of theſe Virgins, that they, two and two were cloathed with linen coats, and decently girded about out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in their right arms, as if about
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:33010:69"/>
to lighten ſome burden, ſo were they prepared; for they were exceedingly chearful and prompt.</p>
               <p n="9">9 Theſe things when I had ſeen, I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired with my ſelf, that I ſhould ſee ſo great and eminent things, and again I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired, becauſe of theſe Virgins, that they were ſo comly and delicate, and ſhould ſtand ſo conſtantly and ſtrongly, as if about to ſupport the whole Heaven.</p>
               <p n="10">10 And while I thought theſe things within me, <hi>that ſheepherd ſaith to me,</hi> why doſt thou diſpute within thy ſelf, and art perplexed, and doſt add ſolicitude to thy ſelf? What ever things thou canſt not underſtand, do not attend them as if thou be'ſt wiſe; but ask the Lord that having received a ſenſe, thou mayeſt underſtand them.</p>
               <p n="11">11 What things ſoever are behind thee, thou canſt not ſee, but what are before thee, thou ſeeſt; In theſe therefore which thou canſt not ſee, be not perplexed, and receive the underſtanding of theſe which thou ſeeſt, leave off to be curious; But I will demonſtrate to thee all whatſoever I ought to ſhew thee, but now conſider the reſt.</p>
               <p n="12">12 And when he had ſaid theſe things to me, I looked up, and behold I ſaw <pb n="138" facs="tcp:33010:70"/>
coming ſix tall and venerable men, and all al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke in countenance, and calling a certain multitude of men, and theſe that came called by them; they alſo were tall and ſtrong. But theſe ſix commanded them to build a certain TOWER up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Gate; but then began there a great murmuring to be of thoſe that ran too and fro about the Port, of theſe men who had come to build the Tower.</p>
               <p n="13">13 But theſe Virgins who ſtood about the Gate, commanded them to haſt the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Tower, alſo they ſtretched forth their hands, as if about to receive ſomething from them; then theſe ſix commanded that out of a certain Deep they ſhould take up ſtones, and ſhould prepare them for the building of the Tower, and there were lifted up ten ſtones, white, four cornerd, hewen.</p>
               <p n="14">14 But after theſe ſix had called theſe Virgins, they commanded them to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry all the ſtones whatſoever were to be put into the Structure of the Tower, and brought in through the Gate, to deliver them to thoſe who were about to build that Tower; Immediately theſe Virgins began among themſelves all to lift up theſe ſtones which before were
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:33010:70"/>
lifted out from the deep.</p>
               <p n="15">15 But they who ſtood about the gate, did alſo carry ſo, as what [ſtones] ſeemed to be more ſtrong, ſhould be put at the corners, but the reſt of the ſtones were put into the ſides; and ſo they brought all the ſtones, and them being brought in through the port, they delivered to the builders, as they were commanded; but they receiving them builded them up, but this building was made upon that great Rock, and Gate, and by them the whole Tower was ſuſteined.</p>
               <p n="16">16 But the ſtructure of theſe ten ſtones filled all that gate, which began to be in the foundation of that Tower; but after theſe ten ſtones, other twenty five were lifted out of the deep, and theſe were laid into the building of that ſame Tower, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lifted up by theſe Virgins as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; after theſe other thirty five were lifted up, and they likewiſe were made fit in the ſame work; after theſe fourty ſtones aſcended, and all theſe were added into the ſtructure of that Tower.</p>
               <p n="17">17 Therefore four orders began to be in the foundation of that Tower, for the ſtones left off to be extracted from the deep, alſo they who builded reſted a little while.</p>
               <p n="18">
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:33010:71"/>18 Again, theſe ſix men gave command to the multitude, that from theſe twelve Mountains they ſhould bring thither ſtones unto the building of the ſame Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; but they hewed out from all the Mountains ſtones of divers colours, and carrying them away, gave them to the Virgins, which they receiving, carried thorow, and gave unto the building of the Tower, in which when they were buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, they became white, and ſpeckled, and likewiſe all the former changed co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours.</p>
               <p n="19">19 But ſome were given by theſe men, which when they had come into that buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, as they were put, ſuch alſo they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained, theſe became nor white, nor va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, becauſe they were not by the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins tranſlated through the gate; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe ſtones were deformed in the building.</p>
               <p n="20">20 Whom when theſe ſix young men had taken notice of, they commanded to be taken up, and put in their own place whence they had been taken; and they ſay to them, who did bring theſe ſtones, Do not ye at all give ſtones unto us unto this building, but put ye them beſide the Tower, that theſe Virgins may give them,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:33010:71"/>
being carried through, for unleſſe by theſe Virgins they ſhall be tranſlated through this gate, they cannot change their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours; do not ye therefore labour in vain.</p>
               <p n="21">21 Moreover the ſtructure was effected in that day, but the Tower was not fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, for it was about to be, that it ſhould be builded; Therefore alſo now a certain delay is made, and theſe ſix commanded thoſe who builded to go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and as it were a certain time to reſt; but to theſe Virgins they laid charge that they ſhould not depart from the Tower, but therefore they ſeemed to me to be left, that they ſhould keep that Tower.</p>
               <p n="22">22 But after they were departed, I ſay to that Sheepherd, Why Lord is not the building of the Tower finiſhed? for it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be finiſhed, <hi>quoth he,</hi> before that the Lord thereof come, and prove this ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, that if he ſhould find any ſtones not good in it, they may be changed, for at his deſire was this Tower builded.</p>
               <p n="23">23 I would know, <hi>quoth I,</hi> Lord, what the building of this Tower may ſignifie, and of this Rock, and of this Gate, [I would] know, and of the Mountains, and of the Virgins, and of the ſtones
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:33010:72"/>
which were drawn out of the deep, nor were hewn about, but as they aſcended, ſo they were put into the ſtructure; and why firſt ten ſtones were placed in the foundation, after that twenty five, after that thirty five, after that fourty; Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of theſe ſtones which were put into the ſtructure, and again taken away and carried into their own place again. Of all theſe Lord, fulfill the deſire of my ſoul, and demonſtrate them all unto me.</p>
               <p n="24">24 <hi>And he ſaid to me,</hi> if thou ſhalt not be ſlow thou ſhalt know all, and thou ſhalt ſee the reſt of the things which are about to be, to this Tower, and all the ſimilitudes thou ſhalt diligently know. And we came after a few dayes into that ſame place where we had ſitten, <hi>and he ſaith to me,</hi> let us come to the Tower, for the Lord thereof is about to come, that he may conſider it.</p>
               <p n="25">25 We came therefore thither, and none other did we find then theſe Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, and he asked them if the Lord of the Tower had been preſent; <hi>and they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered,</hi> that he would be preſent imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, that he may conſider that ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture.</p>
               <p n="26">26 But after a little, I ſee a great mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:33010:72"/>
of men coming, and in the middle of them ſo tall a man, that with his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe he ſurpaſſed the Tower it ſelf, and about him theſe ſix whom in the building I had ſeen to command, and all thoſe who had builded that Tower, and beſides very many other men eminent in dignity.</p>
               <p n="27">27 And theſe Virgins who did keep that Tower, did run, and kiſſed him, and began to walk near him; but he ſo dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently did conſider that ſtructure, that he touched all the ſtones; Moreover, did ſmite every one of them with the Rod which he held in his hand.</p>
               <p n="28">28 Of whom ſome when they had been ſmitten, became black as ſoot, but certain as it were rugged, ſome having clefts, ſome broken, ſome nor black, nor white, ſome rough, nor agreeing with the reſt of the ſtones, ſome having many ſpots; theſe are the varieties of thoſe ſtones which were not found fit in that building.</p>
               <p n="29">29 The Lord commanded them all to be put out from the Tower, and to be left beſide it, and other ſtones to be brought, and to be put in their place; and they that did build asked him out of what Mountain he would have to be brought, and to be put in the place of theſe eject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed:
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:33010:73"/>
out of the Mountains indeed he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad to be brought, but out of a certain field that was nigh, he commanded to be brought.</p>
               <p n="30">30 For they digged that field, and they found ſhining ſtones, four-corner'd, but ſome alſo round, but whatſoever were in that field they were all brought, and through the gate tranſported by theſe Virgins, and theſe that among them were four corner'd, were formed, and placed into the room of thoſe ejected, but theſe which [were] round were not added into the ſtructure, becauſe they were hard, and it ſeemed tedious to hew them, but they were placed about the Tower, as if it were about to be, that they ſhould be hewn and put into the building, for they were very bright.</p>
               <p n="31">31 Theſe things when that man chief in dignity, and Lord of the whole Tower had ſeen, he called this Sheepherd, and delivered to him the ſtones which were reprobated, and placed about the Tower, and he ſaith to him, Purifie thou diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe ſtones, and thoſe, and fit them for the ſtructure of the Tower, that they may agree with the reſt, but thoſe who do not agree thou ſhalt caſt far from the Tower.</p>
               <p n="32">
                  <pb n="145" facs="tcp:33010:73"/>32 Theſe things when he had injoyned him, with all theſe with whom he had come into the Tower, he went away; but theſe Virgins ſtood about the Tower, keeping it, and I ſaid unto that Sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, by what means can theſe ſtones re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn into the building of this Tower, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they are reprobated? <hi>And he ſaid to me,</hi> I will hew the greater part of theſe ſtones, and add into the ſtructure, and they ſhall agree with the reſt.</p>
               <p n="33">33 <hi>And I ſaid,</hi> how Lord can the hewn ones fill up the ſame place? what [ſtones] ſoever <hi>quoth he,</hi> ſhall be found leſſer, ſhall go into the middle ſtructure, but the greater ſhall be put without, and ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn theſe.</p>
               <p n="34">34 Theſe things when he had ſaid to me, let us go, <hi>quoth he,</hi> and after three dayes let us return; and theſe cleanſed ſtones I will adde into the ſtructure, for theſe which are about the Tower ought to be cleanſed all of them, leaſt perhaps ſuddenly the Maſter come upon [them] and find theſe that are about the Tower unclean, and ſo deſpiſe them, and theſe ſtones be not put into the ſtructure of this Tower, and I ſeem to have been a negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Maſter of the Family.</p>
               <p n="35">
                  <pb n="146" facs="tcp:33010:74"/>35 But after three dayes when we had come to the ſame Tower, <hi>he ſaith to me,</hi> Let us conſider all theſe ſtones, and let us ſee which of them can go into the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; <hi>I ſay to him,</hi> let us conſider Lord: firſt of all we began to conſider thoſe that had been black, for as they were laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide from the ſtructure, ſuch were they found, he commanded them to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from the Tower, and to be laid aſide.</p>
               <p n="36">36 After that he conſidered thoſe which had been rugged, and many of theſe he commanded to be hewn, and by theſe Virgins to be fitted into the ſtructure of the Tower; ſo they fitted them being taken away, in the middle of the ſtructure, but the reſt he commanded to be laid with theſe black ones, for they alſo became black.</p>
               <p n="37">37 After that he conſidered theſe who had clefts, and of them he commanded many to be hewn, and by theſe Virgins to be added into the ſtructure, theſe were placed outmoſt, becauſe they were found intire; but the reſt, becauſe of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of clefts could not be conformed, therefore they were caſt from the building of the Tower.</p>
               <p n="38">
                  <pb n="147" facs="tcp:33010:74"/>38 After that he had conſidered thoſe who had become broken, many of them had clefts, and became black, but others had great clefts whom he commanded to be put with theſe that were rejected; but the reſt being purified, and conformed, he commanded to be added into the ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, whom being taken up, theſe Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins fitted in the middle of the ſtructure, for they were more infirm.</p>
               <p n="39">39 After that he conſidered them who had been found half indeed white, but half black, and many of them were found black, he commanded alſo theſe to be carried unto theſe which had been reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but the reſt were found all white, and theſe were taken up by the Virgins, and fitted in the ſame Tower, but theſe were placed more outward which were found intire, ſo that they might contain them which were builded in the middle, for nothing was cut off from them.</p>
               <p n="40">40 After that he conſidered theſe which were hard and rough, few of theſe were added, becauſe they could not be hewn, for they were found exceeding hard, but the reſt were formed and fitted by the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins in the middle of the ſtructure, for they were more infirm.</p>
               <p n="41">
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:33010:75"/>41 After that he conſidered thoſe that had ſpots, and of theſe a few were found black, and theſe were added to the reſt, but theſe that were remaining were found white and intire, and theſe were by the Virgins fitted, and placed outmoſt becauſe of their ſtrength.</p>
               <p n="42">42 After that he came that he ſhould conſider theſe ſtones which were white and round, <hi>and he ſaith to me,</hi> what ſhall we do concerning theſe ſtones? And I ſaid, Lord, I know not; Doſt thou then think nothing, <hi>quoth he,</hi> concerning them? I, <hi>ſaid I,</hi> know not this Art, nor am a Lapidary, nor can I underſtand any thing; <hi>and he ſaid,</hi> ſeeſt thou not them to be very round? that if I would bring them [to be] four-corner'd, there is very much to be cut off them by me, but it is neceſſary that ſome of theſe go into the ſtructure of the Tower.</p>
               <p n="43">43 And I ſaid if it muſt needs be, why therefore doſt thou cumber thy ſelf, and doſt not chuſe, if thou haſt any to chuſe, and fitteſt them into this ſtructure? And he chuſed whom he ſaw greateſt and moſt ſplendid, and conformed them, whom being taken up, theſe Virgins pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the outmoſt parts of the building,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:33010:75"/>
but the reſt which remained were put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain into that ſame field whence they were taken, but thrown away they were not; becauſe, <hi>quoth he,</hi> as yet a little is wanting to this Tower which ſhall be to be buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and perhaps the Lord will fit theſe ſtones in that ſtructure, becauſe they are very white.</p>
               <p n="44">44 After that were called twelve moſt beautiful women cloathed in black cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ungirded, and with bare ſhoulders, and hairs looſned, but theſe women ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to me to be ruſtick, and that Sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd commanded them to take up theſe ſtones which were ejected from the ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, and them to be carried into the Mountains whence they had been brought.</p>
               <p n="45">45 But after that no ſtone lay about the Tower, <hi>He ſaith to me,</hi> Let us go round this Tower, and let us ſee if any thing be wanting to it; We began therefore to go about it, and as ſoon as he ſaw it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently builded, he began to be exceeding chearfull.</p>
               <p n="46">46 For it was ſo decently builded, that he who had ſeen it, ſhould have co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veted its fructure, becauſe it ſeemed to be as of one ſtone, nor did a commixture
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:33010:76"/>
any where appear, but of one Rock it ſeemed exculpted; But I attentively con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering this Tower was exceeding joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
               <p n="47">47 <hi>And he ſaith to me,</hi> bring lime and ſmall ſhells that I may fill up the forms of theſe ſtones which were taken away from the ſtructure and again placed; For all theſe which are about the Tower ought to be equalled. And I did as he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded me, and I brought [them] to him, <hi>and he ſaith to me,</hi> be reddily preſent <hi>to me quoth he,</hi> and ſuddainly this work ſhall be perfected.</p>
               <p n="48">48 He filled up therefore the forms of thoſe ſtones, and he commanded the place to be made clean about the Tower; Then theſe Virgins took beeſoms, and made it all clean, and took away the rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſh, and ſprinkled water, which being fulfilled, the place was made delectable, and the Tower comely.</p>
               <p n="49">49 After that he ſaith to me, all are made clean; If the Lord ſhall come to conſummate this Tower, he ſhall find no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which he may complain of us for; Theſe [words] when he had ſaid he would be gone, but I took hold of his bag, and began to entreat him by the Lord, that
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:33010:76"/>
he would unfold all things which he had ſhewn me.</p>
               <p n="50">50 <hi>He ſaith to me,</hi> I have a little buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but I will unfold all things unto thee, But expect thou me here, while I come; <hi>I ſay to him,</hi> Lord what ſhall I do here alone? <hi>He anſwered,</hi> thou art not alone, for all the Virgins are with thee; <hi>And I ſaid,</hi> deliver me then Lord to them; So he called them, and ſaid to them, I commend unto you this man untill I come.</p>
               <p n="51">51 Therefore I remained with theſe Virgins, but they were chearfull, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fable to me, but chiefly four who excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the reſt in dignity; After that theſe Virgins ſay unto me, that Sheepherd is not to come here to day, <hi>And I ſaid,</hi> what then ſhall I do? And they ſay to me, expect him untill the evening if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps he will come, and will ſpeak with thee, but if not, thou ſhalt ſtay with us till he come.</p>
               <p n="52">52 <hi>I ſaid to them,</hi> I will wait for him untill the evening, but if he ſhall not come, I will go home, and return in the morning, they anſwered me, to us thou art aſſigned, thou canſt not depart from us, and I ſaid where ſhall I ſtay? They
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:33010:77"/>
ſay unto me, thou ſhalt ſleep with us as a Brother, not as a husband, for thou art our Brother, and hencefore we are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to dwell with thee, for very dear do we hold thee.</p>
               <p n="53">53 But I was aſhamed to ſtay with them; But ſhe who ſeemed to be the chief of them, imbraced me, and began to kiſs me, and the reſt when they had ſeen me to be imbraced by her, alſo they began to kiſs me as a Brother, and to lead me about the Tower, and to play with me; But ſome of them ſung hymns, ſome led dances, but I walked with them about that Tower IN SILENCE joyful, and did ſeem to my ſelf to be made more young.</p>
               <p n="54">54 But after it began to be night, ſuddainly I would go home, but they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained me, and ſuffered me not to go away; I ſtayed therefore that night with them beſides that ſame Tower; But they ſpread their linnen coats upon the ground, and placed me in the middle, nor did they do any thing elſe, but that they prayed; But alſo I with them prayed without intermiſſion, and no leſs then they, who when they had ſeen me ſo pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they took great delight.</p>
               <p n="55">
                  <pb n="153" facs="tcp:33010:77"/>55 And there I was with them untill the next day, and when we had prayed to the Lord, then came that Sheepherd, <hi>and ſaid unto them,</hi> have ye done no injury to him? And they ſaid to him, ask him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; <hi>I ſay to him,</hi> Lord great joy hath taken me that I have ſtayed with them; <hi>And he ſaid to me,</hi> what haſt thou ſupped [on]? <hi>And I ſaid</hi> I have ſupped Lord, all the night [on] the WORDS of the Lord; have they entertained thee well? <hi>ſaith he,</hi> And I ſaid, well Lord.</p>
               <p n="56">56 Wilt thou now hear? <hi>And I ſaid,</hi> I will Lord, and firſt as I ſhall ask thee, I beſeech that ſo thou demonſtrate to me, even as thou wilt ſaith he, ſo I will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain the thing unto thee, nor will I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal any thing from thee.</p>
               <p n="57">57 Firſt of all, <hi>Lord quoth I,</hi> demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate this to me, This ROCK and GATE what are they? <hi>Hear ſaith he,</hi> Tis Rock and Gate is the SON of God; Wherefore <hi>ſaid I,</hi> Lord is the Rock old and the Port new? <hi>Hear ſaith he,</hi> thou unwiſe and underſtand, indeed the Son of God is more antient then every creature, ſo that in Counſel he was preſent with his Father, to frame the Creature; But the Gate is therefore new, becauſe in the
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:33010:78"/>
conſummation in the laſt days he appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that they who are about to attain ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, may through him enter into the Kingdome of God.</p>
               <p n="58">58 Saweſt thou, <hi>quoth he,</hi> theſe ſtones which through the port were tranſlated placed in the ſtructure of the Tower; But theſe who were not tranſlated through the Gate, caſt way into their own place? <hi>And I ſaid</hi> I ſaw them Lord, ſo quoth he, none ſhall enter into the Kingdome of God, except he who ſhall get the Name of the Son of God, for if thou wouldeſt enter into any City, and that City be compaſt with a Wall, and have only one Gate, what? Canſt thou otherwiſe enter that City, then by the Gate which it hath?</p>
               <p n="59">59 And by what way <hi>ſaid I</hi> Lord, can it otherwiſe be done? Therefore <hi>quoth he,</hi> as into that City he cannot be entered, but through its gate; So neither into the Kingdome of God can otherwiſe [any] be entered, then by the Name of his Son, who is to him moſt dear.</p>
               <p n="60">60 <hi>And he ſaid to me,</hi> Saweſt thou the troup of them that builded that Tower? I ſaw them <hi>quoth I</hi> Lord, <hi>and he ſaid,</hi> all theſe are Meſſengers honourable in dignity;
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:33010:78"/>
Therefore with theſe as with a Wall is the Lord encompaſſed, but the port is the ſon of God which alone is the acceſſe unto God, for otherwiſe ſhall no man enter into God, except through his Son.</p>
               <p n="61">61 Sawſt thou <hi>quoth he</hi> theſe ſix men, and in the mideſt that great and tall man, who walked about the Tower, and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated the ſtones from the ſtructure? I ſaw them Lord ſaid I, that tall one <hi>quoth he</hi> is the Son of God; And theſe ſix meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers are eminent in dignity, on the right and left hand ſtanding about him. Of theſe excellent meſſengers <hi>ſaith he,</hi> none without him ſhall enter in to God; <hi>And he ſaid,</hi> whoſoever therefore ſhall not get his Name, he ſhall not enter into the Kingdom of God.</p>
               <p n="62">62 <hi>And I ſaid,</hi> What then is this TOWER? This <hi>ſaith he,</hi> is the CHURCH and theſe VIRGINS who are they Lord? <hi>and he ſaid to me,</hi> theſe <hi>quoth he</hi> are the HOLY SPIRITS; For no otherwiſe can a man enter into the Kingdome of God, unleſs theſe ſhall cloath him with their veſture, for why it ſhall profit thee nothing to get the Name of the Son of God, except alſo thou ſhalt get their garment from them;
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:33010:79"/>
for theſe Virgins are the POWERS of the Son of God, ſo in vain ſhall any one bear his Name, except alſo he ſhall bear his Powers.</p>
               <p n="63">63 <hi>And he ſaid to me,</hi> ſaweſt thou theſe ſtones which were thrown away? for they indeed have born the name, but have not put on their garment. <hi>And I ſaid,</hi> what is their garmenr, Lord? Their very names <hi>quoth he,</hi> is their Garment; Whoſoever therefore <hi>quoth he,</hi> doth bear the Name of the Son of God, ought alſo to carry the names of them, for alſo the Son bears their names.</p>
               <p n="64">64 Whatſoever ſtones, <hi>quoth he,</hi> thou ſaweſt to have remained in the ſtructure, delivered by their hands, have been cloathed with the power of them; And therefore thou ſeeſt the whole Tower agreeing with the Rock, and made as it were out of one ſtone.</p>
               <p n="65">65 So likewiſe they who have believed God through his Son, have put on this ſpirit, behold there ſhall be one ſpirit, and one body and one colour of their gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; But alſo they ſhall attain theſe, who ſhall carry the names of theſe Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins.</p>
               <p n="66">66 <hi>And I ſaid,</hi> why therefore Lord
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:33010:79"/>
are the ſtones thrown away which were reprobated, ſeeing alſo they were tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated through the Gate, and delivered by the hands of theſe Virgins, into the ſtructure of this Tower? Becauſe <hi>quoth he,</hi> thou takeſt care to inquire all things diligently; Here concerning theſe ſtones which were caſt away.</p>
               <p n="67">67 All theſe have got the name of the ſon of God, but alſo and the power of theſe Virgins; Therefore having got theſe ſpirits they were perfected, and brought in the number of the ſervants of God, and one body of them began to be, and one veſture: For the ſame righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs did they feel, which they did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like excerciſe.</p>
               <p n="68">68 But after that they had ſeen theſe women, whom thou perceivedſt firſt clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with a black garment, with naked ſhoulders, and looſned hair, they luſted to ſolicite them, becauſe of their beauty, and they were indued with their power; but the cloathings of the Virgins they have caſt off; Theſe therefore are thrown out from the houſe of God, and deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to theſe women, but theſe that are not corrupted through their beauty have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in the houſe of God. Thou haſt
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:33010:80"/>
                  <hi>quoth he,</hi> the explication of theſe ſtones which were abjected.</p>
               <p n="69">69 <hi>And I ſaid,</hi> if therefore Lord any of the men which are of this ſort ſhall do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and ſhall throw away the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of theſe women, and being converted ſhall return to the Virgins, and ſhall put on their power, ſhall they not enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the houſe of the Lord? They ſhall enter <hi>quoth he,</hi> if they ſhall caſt off all the works of theſe women, and ſhall reſume the power of theſe Virgins, and in their works ſhall walk; And therefore is there made an intermiſſion of building, that if theſe ſhall do repentance, they may be added into the ſtructure of the Tower, but if they ſhall not do repentance, others ſhall be builded in their place, and then they ſhall be thrown away together.</p>
               <p n="70">70 <hi>For all theſe things I gave thanks to the Lord, that over all in whom his Name was invo'kt, being mov'd with clemency he ſhould ſend the Preſident Meſſenger of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, unto us who have offended him; and that he ſhould renew our Spirits now ſurely decaying, nor having hope of Salvation, but now he recreateth [them] unto the renewing of life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="71">71 <hi>And I ſaid,</hi> now Lord demonſtrate to me why this Tower is builded not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:33010:80"/>
on the <hi>Earth,</hi> but upon the Rock and Gate; Becauſe, <hi>quoth he,</hi> thou art unwiſe, and without underſtanding, therefore thou askeſt; <hi>And I ſaid,</hi> I have need Lord to ask thee all things, becauſe I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand nothing at all, for all [thy] anſwers are great and excellent, and which men can ſcarcely underſtand.</p>
               <p n="72">72 Here, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> the Name of the Son of God is great and mighty, and by it the WHOLE WORLD IS SUSTEI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NED; if then, <hi>quoth I,</hi> every Creature of God is ſuſteined by his Son, why doth he not alſo ſuſtein thoſe who are invited by him, and bear his Name, and in his Commandments do walk? Seeſt thou not alſo, <hi>quoth he,</hi> that he ſuſteineth thoſe, who from their whole hearts carry his NAME? Therefore he is their founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and willingly doth bear them who deny not his Name, but willingly ſuſtein him.</p>
               <p n="73">73 <hi>And I ſaid,</hi> demonſtrate to me, Lord, the names of theſe Virgins, and of theſe women who were cloathed with a black veſture; Hear, <hi>quoth he,</hi> the names of the Virgins that are more powerful, who ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined the corners of the gate, are theſe; The firſt is called FAITH, the ſecond
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:33010:81"/>
ABSTINENCE, the third POWER, the fourth PATIENCE; but the reſt which conſiſt below theſe, are called by theſe names, Simplicity, Innocency, Chaſtity, Chearfulneſſe, Truth, Wiſdom, Concord, Charity; Therefore whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever bear theſe names, and the Name of the Son of God, they ſhall be able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into Gods Kingdom.</p>
               <p n="74">74 Hear now the names of the women who are cloathed with black cloathing, and of theſe, four are more powerful, of whom the firſt is called TREACHERY, the ſecond INTEMPERANCE, the third UNBELIEF, the fourth VOLUPTUOUSNESSE, but the followers of theſe are ſo called, Sadneſſe, Malice, Luſt, Wrath, Lying, Folly, Puf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing up, Hatred. The Servant of God that beareth theſe Spirits, ſhall indeed ſee the Kingdom of God, but ſhall not enter into it.</p>
               <p n="75">75 But theſe ſtones, Lord, which from the deep were fitted in the ſtructure, who are they? The TEN <hi>quoth he,</hi> which were placed in the foundations, is the firſt age; The following TWENTY FIVE, is the ſecond age of juſt men, but theſe THIRTY are the Prophets
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:33010:81"/>
of the Lord, and Miniſters, but the FORTY, are the Apoſtles and teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Preaching of the Son of God.</p>
               <p n="76">76 <hi>And I ſaid,</hi> why therefore Lord did theſe Virgins alſo hold forth theſe ſtones unto the ſtructure of the Tower, tranſlated through the Port? <hi>And he ſaid,</hi> for theſe firſt have born theſe ſpirits, and they have not at all departed, one from another, nor the ſpirits from the men, nor the men from the ſpirits, but theſe ſpirits have been joyned to them, even untill the day of [their] reſt, who except they had had theſe ſpirits with them, they had not been profitable to the ſtructure of this Tower.</p>
               <p n="77">77 <hi>And I ſaid,</hi> alſo now Lord demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to me, what ſeekeſt thou, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> why <hi>quoth</hi> I, aſcended theſe ſtones out of the deep, and were placed into the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Tower? Seeing long ago they carri'd the juſt ſpirits. It muſt needs be <hi>quoth he,</hi> that by WATER they have to aſcend, that they may reſt, for they could not otherwiſe enter into the Kingdome of God, then that they ſhould lay down the mortality of the former life.</p>
               <p n="78">
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:33010:82"/>78 Therefore they being dead, were ſealed with the SEAL of the Son of God, and have entered into the Kingdom of God; For before that a man get the name of the Son of God, he is deſigned for death, but as ſoon as he hath got the Seal, he is freed from death, and deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to life; But that ſeal is WATER, into which men deſcend being bound un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death, but they aſcend, aſſigned to life; And to them therefore is preached that ſeal, and they have uſed it, that they might enter into the Kingdome of God.</p>
               <p n="79">79 <hi>And I ſaid</hi> Therefore why Lord did theſe forty ſtones aſcend with them from the deep, having already that ſeal? <hi>And he ſaid</hi> becauſe theſe Apoſtles and Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, who have preached the name of the Son of God, when having his faith and power, they had died; They preached to theſe who had died before [them] and they gave to them that Seal; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they deſcended into the water with them, and again they aſcended; But theſe aſcended alive, but they who were deceaſed before, deſcended indeed dead, but aſcended alive.</p>
               <p n="80">80 Therefore by them they received
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:33010:82"/>
life, and knew the Son of God, and therefore they aſcended with them, and agreed into the ſtructure of the Tower, neither hewed, but they were builded in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, becauſe being full of righteouſneſſe, they deceaſed with great chaſtity, but only this ſeal was wanting to them; Thou haſt the explanation of theſe.</p>
               <p n="81">81 <hi>And I ſaid,</hi> now again Lord, alſo demonſtrate to me concerning theſe Mountains, why they are diverſe, and of one, and of another figure? <hi>Hear quoth he,</hi> Theſe TVVELVE MOUN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAINS whom thou ſeeſt, are twelve Nations which obtain the whole world; Therefore the Son of God was preached in them, by thoſe whom he ſent unto them; But why they are various, and of one, and of another figure, Hear thou.</p>
               <p n="82">82 Theſe twelve generations which obtain the whole world are twelve Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; And as thou ſaweſt all the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains diverſe, ſo alſo theſe Nations; The ſenſes likewiſe, and the acts of every Mountain I will teach thee.</p>
               <p n="83">83 Firſt <hi>quoth I,</hi> Lord demonſtrate this to me, ſince theſe Mountains are ſo various, by what manner ſhall they agree
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:33010:83"/>
into the ſtructure of this Tower, and be brought to one colour, and be no leſs ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, then theſe that aſcended out of the deep? Becauſe <hi>ſaith he,</hi> all the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which are under Heaven, have heard and believed, and are called by the one Name of the Son of God. Therefore having gotten his Seal, they have all got the ſame prudence and the ſame under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and the faith and charity of them is one, and the ſpirits of theſe Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, with his Name did they bear.</p>
               <p n="84">84 And therefore the ſtructure of this Tower, did ſeem alike in colour, and did ſhine even unto the Suns clearneſs; But after they have ſo underſtood, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be one body of them all; Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding certain of them ſtained them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and have been caſt from the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the juſt, and again have return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to their former ſtare, and alſo have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come worſe then before.</p>
               <p n="85">85 How, <hi>quoth I,</hi> Lord, worſe, who have known the Lord? <hi>And he ſaid,</hi> he indeed who knoweth not the Lord, if he live wickedly, he remains in that puniſhment of his wickedneſſe; but he who knows the Lord, ought altogether to abſtein from all wickedneſſe, and more and mor
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:33010:83"/>
ſerve unto goodneſſe, ſeems not he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, who ought to follow goodneſſe, if he eſteem parts of wickedneſſe, to ſin more, than he who hath failed, being ignorant of the power of God?</p>
               <p n="86">86 And therefore theſe indeed are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate to death; but theſe who have known the Lord, and his wonders, and works have ſeen; if they live wickedly they ſhall be puniſhed more by the double, and they ſhall dye for ever. As therefore thou didſt ſee, after the ſtones were caſt out from the Tower, which were reprobated, they were delivered to pernicious and evil Spirits; and ſo thou ſaweſt the Tower pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, ſo that it would have been believed to be all of one ſtone.</p>
               <p n="87">87 So alſo the Church of God, when it ſhall be purified, the evil, and the feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the wicked and dubious, being caſt out of it, and whoſoever have carried themſelves wickedly in it, and the divers kinds of the wickedneſſe of ſinners, it's body ſhall be one, intellect one, ſenſe one, one faith, and charity the ſame, and then the Son of God ſhall be joyful a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, and ſhall receive with a pure deſire, his people.</p>
               <p n="88">88 <hi>And</hi> I <hi>ſaid,</hi> Lord, magnificently,
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:33010:84"/>
and honourably all [theſe] things carry themſelves; now demonſtrate to me the effect and force of every ſort of moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that every ſoul truſting in the Lord, theſe being heard, may honour his great and admirable, and holy NAME; Hear <hi>quoth he,</hi> the truth of theſe Mountains, that is, of TWELVE NATIONS.</p>
               <p n="89">89 In the FIRST black Mountain, they who have believed, are the fugitives, and thoſe that ſpeak hainous things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord, and the betrayers of the Servants of God; to them is appointed death, repentance is not; and therefore they are black, becauſe their kind is wicked.</p>
               <p n="90">90 But of the SECOND rough Mountain, are the feigned, who have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, and are the Teachers of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and theſe are next to the former, not having among themſelves the fruit of equity; for as their Mountain is barren, and without fruit, ſo alſo this ſort of men have indeed a name, but from faith are empty, nor is there in them any fruit of the Truth; yet to theſe is given Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, if ſwiftly they follow it, but if they delay, they alſo ſhall be conſorts of the death of the former.</p>
               <p n="91">
                  <pb n="167" facs="tcp:33010:84"/>91 Why <hi>quoth I,</hi> Lord, is there indeed an acceſſe for them unto Repentance, but to the former not? for the treſpaſſes of them are almoſt the ſame; Therefore <hi>quoth he,</hi> is there to theſe returning through Repentance, to Life, becauſe they have ſpoken nothing hanous againſt their Lord, nor have been betrayers of the Servants of God, but through a certain covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of having, have deceived men, leading them according to the luſts of thoſe that ſin, therefore ſhall they give a certain payment of that thing, but yet to them is offered Repentance, who have ſpoken nothing hainous againſt the Lord.</p>
               <p n="92">92 But of the THIRD Mountain which had thorns and thiſtles, are ſuch who have believed, ſome rich, but ſome hindred by many imployments, for the thiſtles are riches, but the thorns, they who are cumbred with many buſineſſes; Theſe therefore who are hindred by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny buſineſſes, and various affairs, do not adjoyn themſelves to the Servants of God, but wander away, being called back by theſe imployments by which they are choaked.</p>
               <p n="93">93 Alſo and theſe who are rich, they do with difficulty give themſelves unto the
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:33010:85"/>
converſation of Gods Servants, fearing leaſt any thing be required of them; theſe therefore difficultly ſhall enter into the Kingdom of God; for as with unſhod feet men walk difficultly in thiſtles, ſo alſo it is difficult for this ſort of men to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kingdom of God.</p>
               <p n="94">94 But alſo to all theſe is regreſſe grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto Repentance, if ſwiftly they ſhall return unto it; that becauſe in their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer dayes they have ceaſed from work, having renewed the time they may be able to do ſomething of good; therefore repentance being acted, if they ſhall do the works of goodneſſe, they ſhall live, but if in their tranſgreſſions they ſhall remain, they ſhall be delivered to theſe women, who will take away life from them.</p>
               <p n="95">95 But of the FOURTH Mountain having very much herbs, whoſe upper part was green, but the very roots wither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, alſo ſome touched by the heat of the Sun did wither, of this ſort are certain doubtful ones, who have believed, and certain others carrying the Lord in their lips, NOT IN THEIR HEART, and therefore they are withered, and their herbs having no foundation, for
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:33010:85"/>
onely in words they live, but their works are dead; Theſe therefore are nor dead, nor alive, and they are likewiſe doubtful, for theſe doubtful ones are neither green nor withered; that is, nor alive, nor dead.</p>
               <p n="96">96 For as their herbs having ſeen the Sun, withered, ſo alſo the doubtful, as ſoon as they have heard of perſecution, fearing diſcommodities they have retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to images, and again have ſerved them, and have been aſhamed to bear the Name of the Lord; Therefore this ſort of men are nor alive, nor dead, but alſo they may live, if ſuddenly they ſhall do Repentance, but if not, already are they delivered to theſe women who will take away their LIFE.</p>
               <p n="97">97 But of the FIFTH rough Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and having green herbs, are of this ſort who have believed, faithful indeed but difficultly believing, and bold, and pleaſing themſelves, willing to be ſeen to know all things, and knowing nothing at all; Therefore becauſe of this boldneſs, ſenſe hath departed from them, and raſh arrogance hath entred into them, but they have carried themſelves high, and as if wiſe, and whilſt they are fools, they
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:33010:86"/>
covet to ſeem Teachers, becauſe of this folly, while they magnifie themſelves, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them are emptied.</p>
               <p n="98">98 For a great Devil is audaciouſneſſe, and vain confidence; Therefore of theſe many are abjected, but others, having acknowledged their errour, have done Repentance, and have ſubjected them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to thoſe that have a perceiving; But alſo to the reſt, the like of theſe, is Repentance held forth, for neither were they evil, but rather unwiſe, and fools; Therefore theſe, if they ſhall do Repentance, ſhall LIVE TO GOD, but if not, they ſhall dwell with theſe women, who ſhall exerciſe their wickedneſſes IN THEM.</p>
               <p n="99">99 Of the SIXT Mountain, having clefts more and leſſe, are of this ſort who have believed, and theſe in whom the clefts were leſſe, theſe are they who have ſtrived among themſelves, and becauſe of their complaints languiſh in the faith; But many of them have done Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and the reſt ſhall do the ſame, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving heard my Commandments, for their contentions are ſmall, and eaſily do they return to Repentance.</p>
               <p n="100">100 But theſe who have greater, as
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:33010:86"/>
ſtones will be ſtubborn, they are mindful of grudges &amp; offences, excerciſing wrath among themſelves; Theſe therefore are thrown away from the Tower, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probated from its Structure; therefore theſe ſort of men ſhall hardly LIVE.</p>
               <p n="101">101 Our God and Lord, who hath Dominion over all things, and hath po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of his univerſal Creature, will not remember offences, but by thoſe that confeſſe their ſins, is he eaſily plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. But man ſeeing he is languiſhing, Mortal, Infirm, and filled with ſins, is perſeveringly angry with man, as if he could preſerve or deſtroy him.</p>
               <p n="102">102 But I, THE MESSENGER and SET OVER TO REPENT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ANCE do admoniſh you, that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever [of you] have ſuch a purpoſe, lay it by and run again to Repentance; and the Lord ſhall heal your former fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, if from this Devil ye ſhall purifie your ſelves, but if not, ye ſhall be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to him unto Death.</p>
               <p n="103">103 But of the SEVENTH Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, in which the herbs were green and ſprightly, and the whole Mountain was fertile, and all kind of cattel took paſture of the herbs of that Mountain, and how
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:33010:87"/>
much the more theſe herbs were pluckt, by ſo much the more joyous did they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flouriſh; Theſe are of this ſort, who have believed, ſimple, and good alwayes.</p>
               <p n="104">104 And having no diſſentions among themſelves, but always being joyful of the Servants of God, having indued the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of theſe Virgins, and alwayes prompt to do loving kindneſſe on all men, and of their labours affording eaſily to all men, without upbraiding, and deliberation; the Lord therefore having ſeen their ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, and all their child-likeneſſe, hath increaſed them in the labours of their hands, and hath given them in every work favour.</p>
               <p n="105">105 But I exhort you the Meſſenger ſet over to Repentance, to remain in the ſame purpoſe, whoſoever are of this ſort, LEAST YOUR SEED BE ROOT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ED OUT FOR EVER; for the Lord hath tryed you, and hath written [you] into our number, and all your SEED with the Son of God he hath inriched, for of his Spirit are ye all.</p>
               <p n="106">106 But of the EIGHT Mountain, in which were many Fountains, in whom was watered every kind of the Creature of God; are ſuch who have
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:33010:87"/>
believed the APOSTLES, whom the Lord hath ſent over the whole World to preach; and ſome <hi>Teachers who have chaſtly and ſincerely preached, and tought, nor have ſubſcribed any thing at all evilly to luſt, but dayly in equity and truth have walked;</hi> Theſe therefore have their converſation among the ANGELS.</p>
               <p n="107">107 But of the NINTH deſerted Mountain, and having ſerpents are of this ſort, who have believed, but alſo had blots; theſe are the MINISTERS doing their Miniſtry badly, SNATCH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ING AWAY THE GOODS OF WIDDOWS AND PUPILS, PROFFERING OTHERS IN THEIR STEAD, WITH THESE [GOODS] WHICH THEY HAVE GOT; Theſe if they ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the ſame coveteouſneſſe, have delivered themſelves to death, nor was any hope of life in them; but if they ſhall be converted and ſhall chaſtly finiſh their Miniſtry, they may live.</p>
               <p n="108">108 But theſe who were found rugged, are they who have denied the Name of the Lord, nor to the Lord again have returned, but have become wild and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, not applying themſelves to Gods
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:33010:88"/>
ſervants, but ſeparate from them, for a little ſolicitude have let go THEIR LIFE; for as a vine left in a hedge, to whom there happeneth no dreſſing doth periſh, and is choaked by weeds, and in time becomes wilde (for it ceaſeth to be profitable to its Lord.)</p>
               <p n="109">109 So alſo this ſort of men diſpair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of themſelves, becoming imbit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, have begun to be unprofitable to their Lord; to theſe therefore is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance committed. If from his heart, he ſhall not be found to have denied [it] whither he can attain life, I am igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant.</p>
               <p n="110">110 <hi>And therefore I ſay,</hi> that in theſe dayes if any hath denied [it] he may return to Repentance, for it cannot be, that any one now denying his Lord, can afterward attain unto ſalvation; but to them is the propoſed Repentance reput<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who in times paſt have denied [it] for he that is about to act Repentance, ought to haſten before the ſtructure of this Tower is finiſhed; but if not, by theſe WOMEN he ſhall be dragged unto Death.</p>
               <p n="111">111 But they who being maimed are deceitful, and threatning one againſt
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:33010:88"/>
an other; Theſe are the ſerpents mixed in that Mountain; for as the poyſon of ſerpents is deſtructive to men, ſo alſo the words of ſuch infect men and deſtroy them; therefore they are maimed from their faith, becauſe of this kind of their life in which they linger; but ſome of them having received Repentance, have attain'd ſalvation; but alſo the reſt of this ſort of men ſhall equally attain [it] if they ſhall do Repentance, but if not, they ſhall die with theſe Women, whoſe force and power they poſſeſſe.</p>
               <p n="112">112 But of the TENTH Mountain, in which there were trees covering the Cattel, are ſuch who have believed, ſome overſeers, that is Preſidents of Churches; but others, theſe ſtones, who not with a feigned but with a cheerful mind, alwayes into their houſes have received the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God; And after that they who are overſeers of Miniſtrings, who have both protected the Poor and the Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, and have perpetually had a chaſt converſation; therefore theſe men are protected by the Lord, theſe things who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall do, are honoured with the Lord; and among the MESSEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GERS is their place, if they ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere,
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:33010:89"/>
even until the Conſummation, to obey the Lord.</p>
               <p n="113">113 Of the ELEVENTH Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, in which were trees loaden with divers fruits, are theſe who have believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and for the Name of the Lord have undergone Death, and with a ready mind have ſuffered, and with their whole heart have delivered up their ſouls.</p>
               <p n="114">114 <hi>And I ſaid,</hi> why then Lord have all theſe trees certain fruits, but of them ſome more fair? Hear <hi>quoth he,</hi> whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver for the Name of the Lord have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, are eſteemed honoured, with the Lord, and the failings of them all are blotted our, becauſe for the Name of the Son of God, they have undergone Death.</p>
               <p n="115">115 But why the fruits of them are unlike, and ſome among them excel, <hi>Hear thou,</hi> for whoſoever being led to the POWERS, being asked, have not denied the Lord, but with a ready mind have ſuffered, are more honoured with God, therefore the fruits that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel are theirs; But they who have been timorous and doubtful, and have deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berated in their heart, whether they
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:33010:89"/>
ſhould confeſſe or deny, and have ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, their fruits are ſmaller.</p>
               <p n="116">116 Therefore beware ye who have ſuch cogitations, leaſt this mind remain in you, and YE DIE TO GOD; ye therefore whoſoever for this names ſake do undergo death, ought to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the Lord, that the Lord eſteemes you worthy, that ye may bear his Name, and all your ſins may be redeemed.</p>
               <p n="117">117 Therefore do ye not rather e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem your ſelves happy? Think ye ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if any of you ſuffereth; [him] to accompliſh a great work, for to you the Lord giveth life; nor do you underſtand, for your failings did burthen you; and unleſſe ye ſhould have ſuffered for the cauſe of this Name, for your ſins ye had ſurely been dead to God; Theſe things therefore I ſay to you, whoſoever do deliberate of confeſſing or of denying.</p>
               <p n="118">118 Confeſſe ye therefore your ſelves TO HAVE THE LORD GOD, leaſt perhaps denying, ye be delivered into bonds; for if all the Nations pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh their Servants, whoſoever have denied their Lord. What think ye the Lord about to do to you, who hath power of all things? Remove therefore from your
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:33010:90"/>
hearts theſe diſputations, that for ever ye may LIVE TO GOD.</p>
               <p n="119">119 But of the TWELVTH white Mountain, are ſuch who have believed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as INFANTS ſincere, to whom no malice aſcended over their ſenſe, nor have they known what is malice, but alwayes have remain'd in ſincerity; Therefore this ſort of men without any dubitation, ſhall inhabit the Kingdom of God; becauſe in no buſineſſe have they ſtained the commands of God, but with ſincerity have remained all the dayes of their life in the ſame tenour of ſenſe.</p>
               <p n="120">120 Whoſoever therefore <hi>quoth he,</hi> ſhall remain as Infants, not having malice, ſhall be more honourable then all thoſe whom I have already ſpoken of, FOR ALL INFANTS ARE HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOURED WITH THE LORD, AND ARE ESTEEMED FIRST; happy therefore ye, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall remove from you malice, and ſhall put on innocency; becauſe, firſt, ye ſhall ſee God.</p>
               <p n="121">121 <hi>After he had finiſhed the explanation of all the Mountains, I ſay to him;</hi> Lord, now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound unto me concerning theſe ſtones, who being brought out of the field, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:33010:90"/>
the place of the Reprobate ones, were put unto the Structure of the Tower: Likewiſe of theſe round ſtones which were added unto the Structure of the Tower; and of theſe who as yet remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed round.</p>
               <p n="122">122 Hear <hi>quoth he,</hi> of the ſtones, theſe which being brought from off the field, were placed into the Structure of the Tower, in their place which had been reprobate, are the ROOTS of that white Mountain; when therefore they who of that Mountain have believed, are become innocent, the Lord of that Tower hath commanded theſe which were of the Roots of the Mountain, to be put into the Structure.</p>
               <p n="123">123 For he hath underſtood, if they had gone to the building, that they would remain ſhining, nor would any whit of them grow black any more; but if he had ſo added of the reſt of the Mountains, he had not needed again to viſit that Tower and purge it; But theſe are all white who have believed, and who are about to believe, for they are of the ſame kind, happy this kind, becauſe it is innocent.</p>
               <p n="124">124 Hear now alſo of theſe round and
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:33010:91"/>
ſplendid ſtones, all theſe are of this white Mountain; but why they are found round, the cauſe is, becauſe their riches have a little obſcured them from the Truth, and have darkned them; But from God they have never departed, nor hath any evil word proceeded out of their mouth, but all Equity, Vertue, and Truth.</p>
               <p n="125">125 The MINDE therefore of theſe when the Lord had ſeen, and them to be able to favour the Truth; he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them likewiſe to remain good, and their riches to be circumciſed, for he would not have them to be for alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether taken away, that they might do ſomething of good, of that which was left to them, and LIVE TO GOD, becauſe alſo they are of the good kind; Therefore for that cauſe are they hewn a little, and put into the ſtructure of this Tower.</p>
               <p n="126">126 But the reſt who have as yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued round, nor are found fit unto that ſtructure, becauſe they have not yet got the SEAL, are put again in their own place, for they are found very round; but this World muſt be hew'n from them, and the vanities of their riches, and
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:33010:91"/>
then they ſhall be fit in the Kingdom of God.</p>
               <p n="127">127 For it muſt needs be that they enter into the Kingdom of God, for this harmleſſe kind hath the Lord bleſſed; Therefore out of this kind ſhall not any one periſh, yea even although any one of them, tempted by the moſt wicked Devil, ſhould ſomewhat fail, he will ſuddenly run back to the Lord his God.</p>
               <p n="128">128 But happy do I the Meſſenger of Repentance, judge you, whoſoever are innocent as Infants, becauſe your part is good, and honoured with God; but I ſay unto you all, whoſoever have got this SEAL, have ye ſimplicity, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be ye mindful of offences, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main ye in malice, neither let bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes become in the Spirit of any one of you, in the memory of offences; but to theſe evil rents procure ye remedy, and remove them from you, that the Lord of the ſheep may rejoyce concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you.</p>
               <p n="129">129 For he ſhall rejoyce if he ſhall find all things ſound, but if he ſhall find of ſuch any ſheep ſcattered, wo ſhall be to the ſheepherds; but if the ſheepherds themſelves ſhall be ſcuttered, what ſhall
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:33010:92"/>
they anſwer to him for the ſheep? What? will they ſay themſelves to have been ſmitten by the ſheep? it will not be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved to them; for IT IS AN IN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CREDIBLE THING THAT THE SHEEPHERD CAN SUFFER BY THE SHEEP, and he is the rather puniſhed for his lye.</p>
               <p n="130">130 And I am a Sheepherd, and <hi>I</hi> muſt ſtrongly render an account of you; therefore provide for your ſelves while as yet the Tower is building; THE LORD DWELLET IN THE MEN THAT LOVE PEACE, for true peace is dear; but from the contentious, and deſtroy'd with malice, he is far a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. RENDER therefore to him YOUR SPIRIT INTIRE AS YE RECEIVED IT.</p>
               <p n="131">131 For if thou ſhould'ſt give to a FULLER a whole garment, and would'ſt laſtly receive it whole, but the Fuller reſtores it to thee rent, would'ſt thou receive it? Wilt thou not immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately wax angry, and purſue him with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes? Saying, <hi>I gave my Garment to thee intire, why haſt thou torn it, and made it uſeleſſe? Now becauſe of the rent which thou haſt made in it, it cannot be of uſe;</hi>
                  <pb n="183" facs="tcp:33010:92"/>
Wilt thou not therefore ſpeak all theſe words to the Fuller, and [that] of the rent which he makes in thy garment?</p>
               <p n="132">132 If therefore thou grieveſt for thy garment, and complaineſt that thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveſt it not intire, what thinkeſt thou THE LORD about to do to thee, who HATH GIVEN THEE AN INTIRE SPIRIT, and thou haſt renderd it all unprofitable; ſo that it can be of no uſe to its Lord? for its uſe hath begun to be uſeleſs, when it is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by thee; will not therefore the Lord do the ſame concerning his ſpirit, for this deed? Plainly I ſay, to all theſe whomſoever he ſhall find to remain in the memory of offences, he will do the ſame.</p>
               <p n="133">133 His clemency, <hi>quoth he,</hi> do not ye ſpurn, but rather honour ye him, that he is ſo patient at your treſpaſſes, and is not like you; Do ye repentance, for that is profitable to you. <hi>All theſe things which are above written, have I, the Sheepherd, the Meſſenger of Repentance, ſhown, and ſpoken to the ſervants of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="134">134 If therefore ye ſhall believe, and ſhall hear my words, and ſhall walk in them, and ſhall correct your walkings,
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:33010:93"/>
ye ſhall be able to live; But if ye ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in malice, and in the memory of offences, none of this ſort of ſinners ſhall LIVE TO GGD, all theſe things to be ſpoken by me, are ſpoken to you.</p>
               <p n="135">135 <hi>That Sheepherd ſaith to me,</hi> haſt thou asked all things of me? <hi>And I ſaid,</hi> yea Lord; why therefore haſt thou not asked me of the form of the ſtones placed in the ſtructure, that to thee I ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain their forms? <hi>And I ſaid</hi> I forgot Lord; Hear now therefore <hi>quoth he,</hi> alſo of theſe.</p>
               <p n="136">136 Theſe are they who have now heard theſe commands, and from their whole hearts have done repentance; and when the Lord had ſeen their repentance good and pure, and them to be able to remain in it, he commanded their former ſins to be blotted out; For theſe forms were their ſins, and they are made even, leaſt they ſhould appear.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="similitude">
               <head>SIMIL. X.</head>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>AFter I had written out this book, that Meſſenger who had delivered me to that Sheepherd, came into the houſe,
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:33010:93"/>
in which I was, and ſat down upon the bed, and that Sheepherd ſtood at his right hand. After that he called me, and ſaid theſe things to me,</hi> I have delivered thee <hi>quoth he,</hi> and thy houſe to this Sheepherd, that by him thou mayeſt be protected.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Yea quoth</hi> I, Lord: if thou wilt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be protected, <hi>quoth he,</hi> from all vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, and from all cruelty, or have ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe in EVERY good work, and word, and all the vertue of Righteouſneſs: walk thou in theſe commandments which I have given to thee, and thou ſhalt be able to rule over ALL wickedneſs: For to thee keeping theſe Commands, ſhall ALL the luſt &amp; ſweetneſs of this world be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, alſo ſucceſs ſhall follow thee in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very good imployment.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The maturity of him, and the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty receive thou in thee, and ſay to all, him to be in great honour and dignity with God, and him to be the preſident of great power, and potent in his office. To him alone, through the whole world the power of Repentance is given; ſeemeth he not to thee to be potent? But YE deſpiſe the perfection and modeſty of him, which he hath over YOU.</p>
               <p n="4">4 I <hi>ſay to him,</hi> ask him Lord, from the
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:33010:94"/>
[time] wherein he is in my houſe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I have done any thing-out of order, or in any thing have offended him; And I, <hi>quoth he,</hi> know thee to have done no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing out of order, neither to be about to do, and therefore theſe ſpeak I with thee, that thou mayſt perſevere, for he hath eſteemed well of thee with me, but thou ſhalt tell theſe words to the reſt, that alſo they who have done, or are about to do Repentance, may perceive the ſame things which thou [feeleſt] and he with me may interpret concerning them, and I with the Lord.</p>
               <p n="5">5 And I, <hi>quoth I,</hi> Lord, to every man do declare the great things of God, but I hope, thoſe all who love them, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have ſinned, having heard theſe, to be about to do Repentance, recovering LIFE; Remain therefore, <hi>quoth he</hi> in this Miniſtry, and conſummate the ſame, but whoſoever obey this [mans] com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, ſhall have life, alſo here, and with the Lord, great honour.</p>
               <p n="6">6 But whoſoever keep not his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, fly from their own LIFE, and oppoſe it, and they who follow not his commandments, deliver themſelves to DEATH, and every one of them ſhall
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:33010:94"/>
be GUILTY OF HIS OWN BLOOD; but to thee I ſay, that thou keep theſe commands, and thou ſhalt have remedy of all thy ſins, but I have ſent thee theſe VIRGINS, that they may dwell with thee, for I have ſeen them to be very affable to thee; Therefore thou ſhalt have them helpers, that by ſo much the rather thou mayeſt keep his commands.</p>
               <p n="7">7 For it cannot be done, that theſe commands be kept without theſe Virgins, but thou ſeeſt them to be willingly with thee; but alſo I will injoyn them, that at all from thy houſe they depart not, only do thou make clean thy houſe, for in a clean houſe they will willingly dwell, for they are clean, and chaſte, and induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and all having favour with the Lord.</p>
               <p n="8">8 If therefore thou ſhalt have thine houſe pure, they will remain with thee, but if any little of pollution ſhall happen, forthwith they will depart from thy HOUSE, for theſe Virgins love no pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution at all; <hi>I ſay to him,</hi> I hope, Lord, me to be about to pleaſe them, ſo that in my houſe they may willingly inhabit al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies; And as he to whom thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:33010:95"/>
me, complains nothing of me, ſo neither ſhall they complain.</p>
               <p n="9">9 <hi>He ſaith to that Sheepherd,</hi> I ſee the Servant of God would be willing to ſee, and to keep theſe commands, and to be about to place theſe Virgins in a clean habitation; <hi>Theſe when he had ſaid, again to that Sheepherd he delivered me, and called the Virgins, and ſaid to them,</hi> Becauſe I perceive you to dwell willingly in this mans houſe, I commend him to you, and his houſe, that from his houſe ye depart not at all; <hi>and they willingly heard theſe words.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10 <hi>After that he ſaith to me,</hi> Converſe thou manfully in this Miniſtry, to every man declare thou the great things of God, and thou ſhalt have acceptance in this Miniſtry; therefore whoſoever ſhall walk in theſe commands, he ſhall live, and ſhall be happy in his life, but whoſoever ſhall neglect them, ſhall not live, and ſhall be unhappy in his life. Say to all, that they ceaſe not, whoſoever can do rightly, to exerciſe good works, it is profitable for them.</p>
               <p n="11">11 But I ſay that every man muſt be delivered out of diſcommodities, for he that needs, and in his daily life ſuffers
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:33010:95"/>
diſcommodities, is in great torment and neceſſity; who ſo therefore delivers ſuch a ſoul out of neceſſity, acquireth great joy to himſelf, for he who is vexed with this diſcommodity, is vexed with like torment and tortures himſelf as he who is in fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
               <p n="12">12 For many becauſe of this ſort of calamities, when they cannot ſtuſtein them, they bring death to themſelves; Therefore he who knoweth the calamity of ſuch a man, and plucks him not out, he admits great ſin, and becomes GUIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TY OF HIS BLOOD; Therefore do ye good works, whoſoever have gotten from the Lord, leaſt while ye delay to do, the ſtructure of the TOWER be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummate.</p>
               <p n="13">13 For becauſe of you is the work of its building left off for a time, unleſſe therefore ye ſhall haſten to do rightly, the Tower ſhall be finiſhed, and ye ſhall be excluded. <hi>But after he had ſpoken with me, he aroſe from the bed, and having taken the SHEEPHERD, and the VIRGINS, he went away, but he ſaid to me, that he would ſend back that Sheepherd and theſe Virgins into mine HO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:33010:96"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33010:96"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 10. l. 19 r. words, p. 11. l. 8. r. Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances, p. 26. l. 8. r. there, p. 44. l. 8. r. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, p. 45. l. 21. r. become, p. 51. l. 6. r. remiſſion p. 54. l. 4. r. equal mindedneſſe, p. 57. l. 17. r. noxious, p. 59. l. 13. r. <hi>Genius,</hi> p. 78. l. 29. r. haſt p. 88. l. 3. r. perceive, p. 103. l. 6. r. conſorts, p. 123. l. 15. r. their rods, p. 131. l. 23. r. there hope, p. 157. l. 7. r. hear.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:33010:97" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33010:97"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
